<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-22T19:10:47+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Martin Holub Blog</title><subtitle>Personal Blog</subtitle><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><entry><title type="html">Five Essays That Challenged My Thinking This Year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Essays That Challenged My Thinking This Year" /><published>2023-12-22T17:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-22T17:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/booksessays.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;essays&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@impatrickt&quot;&gt;Patrick Tomasso&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was the year when I started reading lot of essays. An essay is somewhat neglected writing form - it’s basically thinking laid bare, with an attempt to figure something out. The word essay itself comes from the French &lt;em&gt;essayer&lt;/em&gt; which means &lt;em&gt;to try&lt;/em&gt;. Now unless you are a philosophy geek, that does not sound terribly interesting. But wait, good essay happens to have one more important feature – it comes up with something surprising. Consequently, it is a (relatively) short form that reveals new ways to understand the world around you. Being a short form, it not only means you don’t have to deal with a whole book (and there is lot of them that waste 300+ pages to get one page worth of a point across), but also that authors who do not write books still can get a shot at expressing their thoughts through essays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read some twenty to thirty essays wide range of topics. Bellow I present the five that either felt the most relatable or challenged my exiting mental models the most. Dealing with topics as diverse as economic inequality, impostor syndrome, and transformational festivals, chances are you will love reading them too. So, without further ado, here are the five essays, with a favorite quote from each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-beyond-belief-erik-davis-2006&quot;&gt;5. Beyond Belief (Erik Davis, 2006)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably don’t have to remind you, we live in a consumerist society. That’s good and bad, but one aspect I became particularly frustrated about is that it puts us in a passive position where entertainment is being catered to us. Seems to not to be a problem, as our phones, computers, TVs and movie theaters are full with it, right? Well not quite, because I think it has important implications - disempowering most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that most of us would be much happier in society where everybody plays and active and recognizable role in entertaining the rest. This is something that probably worked quite naturally when communities consisted of 50 people seated around one campfire. &lt;a href=&quot;https://burningman.org/&quot;&gt;Burning Man&lt;/a&gt;, a countercultural transformational festival held annually in Black Rock Desert (Nevada, US), is an attempt at more participatory society, and much more than that. Any attempt to describe it will probably fall short, but Erik Davis at least does it with extreme literally skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“At its best, Burning Man twists authenticity and irony into a Möbius strip that never lets you know what side you’re on but always keeps you going. […] The specifically religious elements of the Burn are important not in themselves, but in relation to one another and to the less ethereal aspects of the festival: the carnality, the trash, the desert dust. This wider field of relations is not holistic but multiple: a promiscuous carnival of souls, a metaphysical flea-market, a demolition derby of reality constructs colliding in a parched void.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://techgnosis.com/beyond-belief-cults-of-burning-man/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-learning-the-elite-class-aella-2022&quot;&gt;4. Learning the Elite Class (Aella, 2022)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is ambitious will inevitably find themselves surrounded by smart people, more often than one would like this may end up in experiences of imposter syndrome. Written as a story of fetish-researcher at posh party &lt;em&gt;Learning the Elite Class&lt;/em&gt; is probably its best description I read this year (and maybe thus far).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The next person I talk to is a startup founder; she’s working on some company that aims to help crypto companies deal with the legal system. I don’t understand most of what she says, but it still feels familiar - I got into crypto early and was around the edges of the formation of the cryptosphere, and the basic culture isn’t arcane to me. I have vague background intuitions around what sorts of things are scams and aren’t, the ways crypto carries risk, the way the public views it. When she uses words like “community” in relation to crypto, it touches lightly into a web of other concepts, and I feel I understand the nuance and implications of it.  She tells me she’s doing a fundraising round and it’s looking promising; her team is building an app that’s going into beta next week and she is flying to a conference tomorrow morning and she was in calls all day earlier fixing an emergency with bank payments not going through to one of her contractors. Her life seems intense to me, and I don’t understand how she’s here at this party looking lively.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aella.substack.com/p/learning-the-elite-class&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-how-to-do-great-work-paul-graham-2023&quot;&gt;3. How to Do Great Work (Paul Graham, 2023)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham is a computer scientist, entrepreneur, and investor. He is not only a coder who made seminal contributions to the programming language Lisp, but perhaps more notably, he is one of the four founders of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ycombinator.com/&quot;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;. Y Combinator is probably the world most renown start up accelerator. It funded over 4’000 startups that now have combined valuation of 600 Billion USD. Companies that started through it include Airbnb, Codeacademy, Coinbase, Disqus, Dropbox, Reddit, Scribd, Stripe, and Twitch. In this essay, he distils advice on how to get great stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Take as much risk as you can afford.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/greatwork.html&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-becoming-a-magician-autotranslucencecom-2018&quot;&gt;2. Becoming a Magician (autotranslucence.com, 2018)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An essay on why going 10x improvements can be much better idea than 2x, at least where you really care. Illustrated on World Bodypainting Competition. Recommended for magicians, body-painters, and anyone who is less cerebral than Paul Graham (which is probably 99% of population).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t necessarily need to make nonlinear jumps in all aspects of our lives, particularly if (according to your values) making such a jump would require a sacrifice you don’t endorse. But for the things you care about most, or are causing you the most suffering, there is probably a nonlinear strategy that you will miss if you pay too close attention to the linear strategy you current have or that people recommend.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://autotranslucence.com/2018/03/30/becoming-a-magician/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-in-praise-of-idleness-bertrand-russell-1932&quot;&gt;1. In Praise of Idleness (Bertrand Russell, 1932)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bertrand Russell was a British mathematician and philosopher. He made seminal contributions to the field of logic, influencing the development of programming languages and design of computer systems. That it is more than almost anyone would attempt before claiming their right for peaceful retirement, but Bertrand Russel did not stop there, by far. Out of many other achievements, he is also the awardee oof 1950 Nobel Prize in Literature “in recognition of his varied and significant writings in which he champions humanitarian ideals and freedom of thought”. This is what his essay “In Praise of Idleness” is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In Praise of Idleness” is a literary gem - skillfully penned, it is an argument to stop glorifying work, and value leisure more. Reading it makes one wonder how did we make so little progress on it since he wrote it (and if he is self-reflecting, as his numerous achievements likely required that he tolled for most of his adult life, putting leisure into background).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for the others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://harpers.org/archive/1932/10/in-praise-of-idleness/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find essays an intriguing writing form, I would highly suggest to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://readsomethingwonderful.com/&quot;&gt;readsomethingwonderful.com&lt;/a&gt; website. It does an amazing job in aggregating lot of great essay writing (but is somewhat computer science centric).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you read any of these essays? What have you thought about them? Or is there an essay you love and that is not on this list? Let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="literature" /><category term="essay" /><category term="literature" /><summary type="html">Photo by Patrick Tomasso on Unsplash. This year was the year when I started reading lot of essays. An essay is somewhat neglected writing form - it’s basically thinking laid bare, with an attempt to figure something out. The word essay itself comes from the French essayer which means to try. Now unless you are a philosophy geek, that does not sound terribly interesting. But wait, good essay happens to have one more important feature – it comes up with something surprising. Consequently, it is a (relatively) short form that reveals new ways to understand the world around you. Being a short form, it not only means you don’t have to deal with a whole book (and there is lot of them that waste 300+ pages to get one page worth of a point across), but also that authors who do not write books still can get a shot at expressing their thoughts through essays. I read some twenty to thirty essays wide range of topics. Bellow I present the five that either felt the most relatable or challenged my exiting mental models the most. Dealing with topics as diverse as economic inequality, impostor syndrome, and transformational festivals, chances are you will love reading them too. So, without further ado, here are the five essays, with a favorite quote from each: 5. Beyond Belief (Erik Davis, 2006) I probably don’t have to remind you, we live in a consumerist society. That’s good and bad, but one aspect I became particularly frustrated about is that it puts us in a passive position where entertainment is being catered to us. Seems to not to be a problem, as our phones, computers, TVs and movie theaters are full with it, right? Well not quite, because I think it has important implications - disempowering most of us. I am convinced that most of us would be much happier in society where everybody plays and active and recognizable role in entertaining the rest. This is something that probably worked quite naturally when communities consisted of 50 people seated around one campfire. Burning Man, a countercultural transformational festival held annually in Black Rock Desert (Nevada, US), is an attempt at more participatory society, and much more than that. Any attempt to describe it will probably fall short, but Erik Davis at least does it with extreme literally skill. “At its best, Burning Man twists authenticity and irony into a Möbius strip that never lets you know what side you’re on but always keeps you going. […] The specifically religious elements of the Burn are important not in themselves, but in relation to one another and to the less ethereal aspects of the festival: the carnality, the trash, the desert dust. This wider field of relations is not holistic but multiple: a promiscuous carnival of souls, a metaphysical flea-market, a demolition derby of reality constructs colliding in a parched void.” Link to the essay 4. Learning the Elite Class (Aella, 2022) Anyone who is ambitious will inevitably find themselves surrounded by smart people, more often than one would like this may end up in experiences of imposter syndrome. Written as a story of fetish-researcher at posh party Learning the Elite Class is probably its best description I read this year (and maybe thus far). “The next person I talk to is a startup founder; she’s working on some company that aims to help crypto companies deal with the legal system. I don’t understand most of what she says, but it still feels familiar - I got into crypto early and was around the edges of the formation of the cryptosphere, and the basic culture isn’t arcane to me. I have vague background intuitions around what sorts of things are scams and aren’t, the ways crypto carries risk, the way the public views it. When she uses words like “community” in relation to crypto, it touches lightly into a web of other concepts, and I feel I understand the nuance and implications of it. She tells me she’s doing a fundraising round and it’s looking promising; her team is building an app that’s going into beta next week and she is flying to a conference tomorrow morning and she was in calls all day earlier fixing an emergency with bank payments not going through to one of her contractors. Her life seems intense to me, and I don’t understand how she’s here at this party looking lively.” Link to the essay 3. How to Do Great Work (Paul Graham, 2023) Paul Graham is a computer scientist, entrepreneur, and investor. He is not only a coder who made seminal contributions to the programming language Lisp, but perhaps more notably, he is one of the four founders of Y Combinator. Y Combinator is probably the world most renown start up accelerator. It funded over 4’000 startups that now have combined valuation of 600 Billion USD. Companies that started through it include Airbnb, Codeacademy, Coinbase, Disqus, Dropbox, Reddit, Scribd, Stripe, and Twitch. In this essay, he distils advice on how to get great stuff done. “Take as much risk as you can afford.” Link to the essay 2. Becoming a Magician (autotranslucence.com, 2018) An essay on why going 10x improvements can be much better idea than 2x, at least where you really care. Illustrated on World Bodypainting Competition. Recommended for magicians, body-painters, and anyone who is less cerebral than Paul Graham (which is probably 99% of population). “We don’t necessarily need to make nonlinear jumps in all aspects of our lives, particularly if (according to your values) making such a jump would require a sacrifice you don’t endorse. But for the things you care about most, or are causing you the most suffering, there is probably a nonlinear strategy that you will miss if you pay too close attention to the linear strategy you current have or that people recommend.” Link to the essay 1. In Praise of Idleness (Bertrand Russell, 1932) Bertrand Russell was a British mathematician and philosopher. He made seminal contributions to the field of logic, influencing the development of programming languages and design of computer systems. That it is more than almost anyone would attempt before claiming their right for peaceful retirement, but Bertrand Russel did not stop there, by far. Out of many other achievements, he is also the awardee oof 1950 Nobel Prize in Literature “in recognition of his varied and significant writings in which he champions humanitarian ideals and freedom of thought”. This is what his essay “In Praise of Idleness” is about. “In Praise of Idleness” is a literary gem - skillfully penned, it is an argument to stop glorifying work, and value leisure more. Reading it makes one wonder how did we make so little progress on it since he wrote it (and if he is self-reflecting, as his numerous achievements likely required that he tolled for most of his adult life, putting leisure into background). “Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for the others.” Link to the essay If you find essays an intriguing writing form, I would highly suggest to check out the readsomethingwonderful.com website. It does an amazing job in aggregating lot of great essay writing (but is somewhat computer science centric). Have you read any of these essays? What have you thought about them? Or is there an essay you love and that is not on this list? Let me know in the comments!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Movies to Watch to Understand the Czech Humor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cz/film/2023/12/18/FiveCzechMovies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Movies to Watch to Understand the Czech Humor" /><published>2023-12-18T17:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T17:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cz/film/2023/12/18/FiveCzechMovies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cz/film/2023/12/18/FiveCzechMovies.html">&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been asked about some Czech movie recommendations which made me think what to recommend to people interested in the Czech history, culture and mentality. “Luckily” the Czech history is rich with drama and oppression, which gave breeding ground to great storytelling. Unluckily, much of the Czech cinematography has not been dubbed in English. But hopefully you should able to find these movies with English subtitles online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are five movies I would recommend to anyone who wants to get better understanding of Czech history, culture and mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pelíšky--cozy-dens-1998&quot;&gt;Pelíšky – Cozy Dens (1998)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a Czech festive occasion turned idyllic something would be fishy. In that spirit, Christmas is more likely to be a catastrophe than anything else, as depicted by this dark comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/pelisky.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;movie poster&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0167331/&quot;&gt;IMDB link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;s-tebou-mě-baví-svět---i-enjoy-the-world-with-you-1983&quot;&gt;S tebou mě baví svět - I Enjoy the World with You (1983)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three middle aged made go on skiing vacation with their children, leaving their wives at home. This surely can’t go wrong, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/steboumnebavisvet.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;movie poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0084620/?ref_=ext_shr_lnk&quot;&gt;IMDB link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;samotáři--loners-2000&quot;&gt;Samotáři – Loners (2000)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You did not expect to become lighter and more positive as we go right? It’s Czech movies in the end! Samotáři is a dark comedy about young people, for young people, putting their complicated relationships with friends and partners in the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/samotari.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;movie poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0219288/&quot;&gt;IDMB link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;na-samotě-u-lesa---seclusion-near-a-forest-1976&quot;&gt;Na samotě u lesa - Seclusion Near a Forest (1976)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Directed by Jan Menzel (also known for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0090257/?ref_=ttloc_ov&quot;&gt;My Sweet Little Village, 1985&lt;/a&gt;) and written by Jaroslav Smoljak and Zdeněk Svěrák (known for their plays about fictive Czechoslovak multi-talent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%A1ra_Cimrman&quot;&gt;Jára Cimrman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/nasamoteulesa.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;movie poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0074947/?ref_=tt_mv_close&quot;&gt;IMDB link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hoří-má-panenko---the-firemens-ball-1967&quot;&gt;Hoří, má panenko - The Firemen’s Ball (1967)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another comedy, this time not that dark, directed by Miloš Forman. You know it’s gonna be good because Forman is two-time Oscar winner. He received Oscars in 1975 and 1984 (and was nominated in 1996) for his movies One Flew Over the Cuckoo’s Nest (starring Jack Nicholson) and Amadeus (a magical drama about life of Mozart), beating nominees like Woody Allen, Frederico Fellini, and Stanley Kubrick. Really, if you did not know Forman yet, go watch some of his movies, they are iconic. Apart from the two above, I suggest The Hair (a musical about hippie counterculture and anti-war movement), Taking Off (featuring a parodical scene of group of posh parents smoking pot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/horimapanenko.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;movie poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0061781/&quot;&gt;IMDB link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the movies on the list that were made before 1993 are Czechoslovak (not Czech). With exception of &lt;em&gt;S tebou mě baví svět&lt;/em&gt; which was directed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie_Poled%C5%88%C3%A1kov%C3%A1&quot;&gt;Marie Poledňáková&lt;/a&gt; the other movies were directed by men (sad but not surprising ratio, given that only three (!) women have ever won an Oscar for directing, all after 2010).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a favorite movie that you think should be on the list? Have you seen any of the movies and want to share how you liked it? Let me know in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="cz" /><category term="film" /><category term="cz" /><category term="film" /><summary type="html">Lately, I have been asked about some Czech movie recommendations which made me think what to recommend to people interested in the Czech history, culture and mentality. “Luckily” the Czech history is rich with drama and oppression, which gave breeding ground to great storytelling. Unluckily, much of the Czech cinematography has not been dubbed in English. But hopefully you should able to find these movies with English subtitles online. Below are five movies I would recommend to anyone who wants to get better understanding of Czech history, culture and mentality. Pelíšky – Cozy Dens (1998) If a Czech festive occasion turned idyllic something would be fishy. In that spirit, Christmas is more likely to be a catastrophe than anything else, as depicted by this dark comedy. IMDB link S tebou mě baví svět - I Enjoy the World with You (1983) Three middle aged made go on skiing vacation with their children, leaving their wives at home. This surely can’t go wrong, right? IMDB link Samotáři – Loners (2000) You did not expect to become lighter and more positive as we go right? It’s Czech movies in the end! Samotáři is a dark comedy about young people, for young people, putting their complicated relationships with friends and partners in the center. IDMB link Na samotě u lesa - Seclusion Near a Forest (1976) Directed by Jan Menzel (also known for My Sweet Little Village, 1985) and written by Jaroslav Smoljak and Zdeněk Svěrák (known for their plays about fictive Czechoslovak multi-talent Jára Cimrman. IMDB link Hoří, má panenko - The Firemen’s Ball (1967) Another comedy, this time not that dark, directed by Miloš Forman. You know it’s gonna be good because Forman is two-time Oscar winner. He received Oscars in 1975 and 1984 (and was nominated in 1996) for his movies One Flew Over the Cuckoo’s Nest (starring Jack Nicholson) and Amadeus (a magical drama about life of Mozart), beating nominees like Woody Allen, Frederico Fellini, and Stanley Kubrick. Really, if you did not know Forman yet, go watch some of his movies, they are iconic. Apart from the two above, I suggest The Hair (a musical about hippie counterculture and anti-war movement), Taking Off (featuring a parodical scene of group of posh parents smoking pot). IMDB link It is important to note that the movies on the list that were made before 1993 are Czechoslovak (not Czech). With exception of S tebou mě baví svět which was directed by Marie Poledňáková the other movies were directed by men (sad but not surprising ratio, given that only three (!) women have ever won an Oscar for directing, all after 2010). Do you have a favorite movie that you think should be on the list? Have you seen any of the movies and want to share how you liked it? Let me know in the comments below!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Books to Read to Better Understand Czech People</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cz/literature/2023/12/17/FiveCzechBooks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Books to Read to Better Understand Czech People" /><published>2023-12-17T11:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T11:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cz/literature/2023/12/17/FiveCzechBooks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cz/literature/2023/12/17/FiveCzechBooks.html">&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been asked about some Czech book recommendations which made me think what to recommend to people interested in the Czech history, culture and mentality. “Luckily” the Czech history is rich with drama and oppression, which gave breeding ground to great storytelling. Unluckily, much of it has not been translated to English. Necessary then, when recommending books to foreigners, I have to limit the recommendation to translations. These were more often than not penned by authors living in exile, which does carry the benefit that these authors were often able to contrast the Czech and foreign experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are five books I would recommend to anyone who wants to get better understanding of Czech history, culture and mentality, with one bonus book for those who can read Czech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-unbearable-lightness-of-being&quot;&gt;The Unbearable Lightness of Being&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list would not be complete without Kundera on it. The Unbearable Lightness of being is one of the most widely read books by a Czech author. He penned it after 10 years living in France. The book actually first appeared in French. It follows a turbulent relationship of a romantic couple on the background of events following the Prague Spring of 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/kundera.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9717.The_Unbearable_Lightness_of_Being&quot;&gt;Goodreads link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;believe-in-people-the-essential-karel-capek&quot;&gt;Believe in People: The Essential Karel Capek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karel Capek was a writer extraordinaire who penned masterpieces of plays, novels, travel journals, letters and columns. It’s the latter two that the most directly showcase his talent to describe the human condition with his characteristic empathy, understanding and wit. Nominated for the Nobel Prize seven times without receiving one, he is probably my favorite Czech author. You can find some of his essays translated at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarsbank.uoregon.edu/xmlui/handle/1794/22915&quot;&gt;public depository of the University of Oregon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/karel_capek.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9151556-believe-in-people&quot;&gt;Goodreads link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-poetry-of-jaroslav-seifert&quot;&gt;The Poetry of Jaroslav Seifert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jaroslav Seifert is the only Czechoslovak who ever won a Nobel Prize in Literature “for his poetry which endowed with freshness, sensuality and rich inventiveness provides a liberating image of the indomitable spirit and versatility of man”. A complicated figure in the Czech post-war history, he was a supporter of communism for many years before he started criticizing the party and siding with pro-democracy movements. Nevertheless, his poetry does match up to the Nobel Prize committee judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/seifert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1009079.The_Poetry_of_Jaroslav_Seifert&quot;&gt;Goodreads link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-good-soldier-svejk&quot;&gt;The Good Soldier Svejk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satire is Czech’s favorite type of humor. This comic book mocking the war and showcasing its futility is one of the Czech classics. Arguable, at nearly 800 pages the book is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; long, so you are better of watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0049147/&quot;&gt;the movie of the same name&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/svejk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7629.The_Good_Soldier_vejk&quot;&gt;Goodreads link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;open-letters-selected-writings-1965-1990&quot;&gt;Open Letters: Selected Writings, 1965-1990&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaclav Havel is the most prominent political figure of the late 20th century of Czechoslovakia, and one of the most prominent leaders in that period worldwide. His influence spans well beyond the national borders, and he was pivotal in the end of Soviet rule throughout the central and eastern Europe. He received honors and awards from over 25 distinct countries, including the highest civilian award of the United States, the Presidential Medal of Freedom. Apart from his political career he has written numerous theater plays and poems. It’s in his letters and essays that his literary and politics personas come the closest together and offer an unique view to the events that lead up to the Velvet Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/havel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/839087.To_the_Castle_and_Back&quot;&gt;Goodreads link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-kapesní-průvodce-inteligentní-ženy-po-vlastním-osudu&quot;&gt;Bonus: Kapesní průvodce inteligentní ženy po vlastním osudu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my point of view, this is the best book to understand the Czech mentality and the events of the 20th century that shaped it. Written as a dialogue between the author, and young woman considering emigration from Czechoslovakia, it will help you understand what were the pivotal events in Czechoslovakian 20th century history and how they shaped the Czech mentality. Unfortunately, as it has not been translated to English, you would have to learn Czech first to read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot; style=&quot;width:45%;min-width:100px;&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/tigrid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;book cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9578104-kapesn-pr-vodce-inteligentn-eny-po-vlastn-m-osudu&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the authors on the list are, at least to some degree, Slovak as well, as they worked in Czechoslovakia. Similarly, it won’t take you a long time to notice: none of the books on the list are by female writers. Unfortunately, they are severely underrepresented in the Czechoslovak literary space of the 19th 20th century. If you wish to learn more about the handful of somewhat more prominent ones, check the profiles of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bo%C5%BEena_N%C4%9Bmcov%C3%A1&quot;&gt;Božena Němcová&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriela_Preissov%C3%A1&quot;&gt;Gabriela Preissová&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karolina_Sv%C4%9Btl%C3%A1&quot;&gt;Karolina Světlá&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eva_Kant%C5%AFrkov%C3%A1&quot;&gt;Eva Kantůrková&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a favorite book that you think should be on the list? Have you read any of these books and want to share how you liked it? Let me know in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="cz" /><category term="literature" /><category term="cz" /><category term="literature" /><summary type="html">Lately, I have been asked about some Czech book recommendations which made me think what to recommend to people interested in the Czech history, culture and mentality. “Luckily” the Czech history is rich with drama and oppression, which gave breeding ground to great storytelling. Unluckily, much of it has not been translated to English. Necessary then, when recommending books to foreigners, I have to limit the recommendation to translations. These were more often than not penned by authors living in exile, which does carry the benefit that these authors were often able to contrast the Czech and foreign experience. Below are five books I would recommend to anyone who wants to get better understanding of Czech history, culture and mentality, with one bonus book for those who can read Czech. The Unbearable Lightness of Being This list would not be complete without Kundera on it. The Unbearable Lightness of being is one of the most widely read books by a Czech author. He penned it after 10 years living in France. The book actually first appeared in French. It follows a turbulent relationship of a romantic couple on the background of events following the Prague Spring of 1968. Goodreads link Believe in People: The Essential Karel Capek Karel Capek was a writer extraordinaire who penned masterpieces of plays, novels, travel journals, letters and columns. It’s the latter two that the most directly showcase his talent to describe the human condition with his characteristic empathy, understanding and wit. Nominated for the Nobel Prize seven times without receiving one, he is probably my favorite Czech author. You can find some of his essays translated at the public depository of the University of Oregon Goodreads link The Poetry of Jaroslav Seifert Jaroslav Seifert is the only Czechoslovak who ever won a Nobel Prize in Literature “for his poetry which endowed with freshness, sensuality and rich inventiveness provides a liberating image of the indomitable spirit and versatility of man”. A complicated figure in the Czech post-war history, he was a supporter of communism for many years before he started criticizing the party and siding with pro-democracy movements. Nevertheless, his poetry does match up to the Nobel Prize committee judgment. Goodreads link The Good Soldier Svejk Satire is Czech’s favorite type of humor. This comic book mocking the war and showcasing its futility is one of the Czech classics. Arguable, at nearly 800 pages the book is very long, so you are better of watching the movie of the same name. Goodreads link Open Letters: Selected Writings, 1965-1990 Vaclav Havel is the most prominent political figure of the late 20th century of Czechoslovakia, and one of the most prominent leaders in that period worldwide. His influence spans well beyond the national borders, and he was pivotal in the end of Soviet rule throughout the central and eastern Europe. He received honors and awards from over 25 distinct countries, including the highest civilian award of the United States, the Presidential Medal of Freedom. Apart from his political career he has written numerous theater plays and poems. It’s in his letters and essays that his literary and politics personas come the closest together and offer an unique view to the events that lead up to the Velvet Revolution. Goodreads link Bonus: Kapesní průvodce inteligentní ženy po vlastním osudu In my point of view, this is the best book to understand the Czech mentality and the events of the 20th century that shaped it. Written as a dialogue between the author, and young woman considering emigration from Czechoslovakia, it will help you understand what were the pivotal events in Czechoslovakian 20th century history and how they shaped the Czech mentality. Unfortunately, as it has not been translated to English, you would have to learn Czech first to read it. Goodreads It is important to note that the authors on the list are, at least to some degree, Slovak as well, as they worked in Czechoslovakia. Similarly, it won’t take you a long time to notice: none of the books on the list are by female writers. Unfortunately, they are severely underrepresented in the Czechoslovak literary space of the 19th 20th century. If you wish to learn more about the handful of somewhat more prominent ones, check the profiles of Božena Němcová, Gabriela Preissová, Karolina Světlá, andEva Kantůrková. Do you have a favorite book that you think should be on the list? Have you read any of these books and want to share how you liked it? Let me know in the comments below!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prioritizing the Right Type of Rest May Be the Best Biohack. Here Is Why.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prioritizing the Right Type of Rest May Be the Best Biohack. Here Is Why." /><published>2023-12-06T08:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-06T08:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest.html">&lt;p&gt;Kate woke up early, knowing she had a packed day ahead of her. She went through her morning routine assuredly and quickly. As usual, she brewed her favorite ginger-mint tea, this time with an extra drop of honey as if it could give her the extra energy, she felt she lacked after a poor night’s sleep. While waiting for the tea to cool down a bit, she quickly typed few supportive messages to her college best friend … her mother has recently gotten quite ill and the friend struggles to cope. Pity they cannot meet up she thought, by now they became geographically too separated. Before brushing her teeth, she put on music in the bathroom, her favorite singer just put out a new album and it’s really good. On her way out she passes by the bedroom to kiss her lover goodbye, and out she goes. No breakfast, that she will have to grab on her way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/trainwoman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by Jeffrey Czum on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/time-lapse-photography-of-person-standing-near-train-2120010/&quot;&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things go well for her at the office. The presentation she was nervous about runs well and she receives positive feedback from her supervisors, so the extra hours she has been putting in apparently have paid off. Some more meetings, a bit of editing work on a report she is finishing, a coffee break with coworkers. On the way home she stops by her favorite yoga studio as a small reward for the day. Finally, home, hungry as she had just a sandwich for lunch. The fridge is quite empty, and by now she is not in the mood for doing groceries, so it will be dinner delivery, maybe tacos? She finishes them while lounging on the sofa, rewatching one of her favorite shows while also texting her mum about the day she had, and looking up tickets for a concert that is coming up in her favorite club next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;busy-ness-has-become-the-default-condition&quot;&gt;Busy-ness has become the default condition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like an average day, doesn’t it? It even sounds quite nice. In many ways probably akin to your average day. If someone asked Kate, how is she doing, how likely do you think her answer would include the word ‘busy’ in it? Probably quite likely, and not dissimilar to how would you have replied. 
‘How are you’ is a standard question we get, but how about the following ones: Do you think Kate likes being busy? Do you think ‘busyness’ works for her? Do you think she is getting enough rest and in the right form? These are quite simple questions, and the answers to them are not that difficult to guess, but strangely enough, we rarely raise them with our friends, or ourselves for that matter. So, in this post I want to ask them: &lt;strong&gt;Do you like being busy? Are you getting an adequate amount of rest?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become the semi-default that we stopped questioning. Most of us lead busy lives. Maybe it’s the price we must pay to be financially comfortable? And why not actually? Many of us (including me) like it (maybe bit too much). But the moment you really let the question of whether you like being busy or not sink in, something changes. Because the chances are, you don’t. And even if you do like it, not all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;not-all-rest-is-made-equal&quot;&gt;Not all rest is made equal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of us will probably be able to say that they are getting some rest during an average week, few will have a sense of whether it is enough or not. I certainly did not, until recently when I was prompted to think about times when I felt really relaxed. The middle-of-vacation falling asleep on a beach type of relaxed. Or when you have done a good yoga session and just sink down to savasana that you don’t want to end. You probably can think of similar experiences when obligations temporarily vanished from your horizon and your body melted as well. So sure, I have memories of feeling super relaxed, but when was the last time I got a chance to feel like it? It must be a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, &lt;strong&gt;most of us are not getting enough rest&lt;/strong&gt;. Partially because we don’t get enough time in our busy lives for it, but &lt;strong&gt;mainly because we are not prioritizing the right type of rest&lt;/strong&gt;. In her recent book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/60750102-the-stress-prescription&quot;&gt;The Stress Prescription&lt;/a&gt;, Elissa Epel defines four different mind states as they relate to stress, red mind (acute stress), yellow (baseline cognitive load), green mind (rest), blue mind (deep rest). We spend most of our days in the &lt;strong&gt;yellow zone&lt;/strong&gt;. Not only at work, but also most of the time around it, when our mind is processing obligations, making plans, engaging in socially, or just plain scrolling or browsing on our devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rest_stress_illustration.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Stress and rest scale illustration.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;strong&gt;red zone&lt;/strong&gt; looks down-right undesirable, it actually is a place we should &lt;strong&gt;actively seek out&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s healthy to engage in activities that get you there for a limited period of time, provided they are self-inflicted (HIIT, cold and heat exposure, hyperventilation, …) as these &lt;strong&gt;mount up your general stress resilience&lt;/strong&gt; on a long run. 
&lt;strong&gt;Green mind&lt;/strong&gt; is what we commonly associate with rest. It’s a pleasant state of relaxation when we are fully engaged in leisure activities. It’s a state when you are just being, not being asked to do something. This is facilitated by &lt;strong&gt;observation and engagement in a single task&lt;/strong&gt; (so no multitasking). Think of being in nature or watching a performance. Watching a show on your TV at home would fit here as well, as long as you are fully immersed and don’t have your attention to repeatedly drift to your phone, the fridge, or some responsibilities coming up (which is unlikely - it’s easier to reach this state of mind in a theater or cinema, as your mind associates these places with the single task of observing art). Engaging in sports is an area that is ambiguous. At times you will be in the yellow or even red zones, at brief times in the green one. If you feel you are fully engaged (i.e. in a state of ‘flow’) you are probably in the green zone. It’s also something that has large learned factor to it – if you have been performing this sport or playing this game for some time already, such that you feel some sense of mastery doing it, the time you spend it the green zone will likely be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how about the &lt;strong&gt;blue zone&lt;/strong&gt;? It turns out that one is both &lt;strong&gt;vital for restoration, and barely visited by most during wake time&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s a state of rest that occurs when we are in a quiet and safe environment, typically physically secluded, focusing on just one thing (e.g. our breath) or having attention openly drifting. This type of rest occurs during a deep sleep (and that also why it’s important to get enough sleep!) and during mind mind-body practices such as meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-enough-deep-rest-is-vital-for-health-and-wellbeing&quot;&gt;Getting enough deep rest is vital for health and wellbeing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I learnt about this, I tried looking at my daily activities through the red-yellow-green-blue lens and realized that I am by far not prioritizing rest the way I thought I am, or nearly as much. Chances are you will feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should you care? Is this anyhow a big deal? Well it kind of is. Researchers have looked at various ways people achieve deep rest (i.e., blue state of mind). In one study, they had people meditate for 20 minutes daily, and meet with a coach weekly. This not only left the people feeling better, but &lt;strong&gt;resulted in positive gene expression changes related to energy metabolism, insulin secretion, telomere maintenance, and inflammation&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0062817&quot;&gt;Bhasin et al., 2013&lt;/a&gt;). In another study, people were invited to join 6-day long meditation retreat and, again, left not only feeling better but also reporting similar health benefits on the gene expression level. This effect applied even to a control group, that just spent 6-day of free time, without meditation (something the researchers called the ‘vacation effect’), and was further strengthen in those who meditated and were accustomed to the meditation practice (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/tp2016164&quot;&gt;Epel et al., 2016&lt;/a&gt;). As it turns out, &lt;strong&gt;restorative rest is a powerful modulator of our health and biology&lt;/strong&gt;. Evidence suggests that &lt;strong&gt;not leaving time and space for it can lead to disease and faster the progression of aging&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the face of it we do have enough time for leisure, and many would use it to also engage in it, we rarely see it as an opportunity to get deeply immersed in something. In fact, lot of things we would do in our leisure time, such as engaging in sports, catching up with friends, browsing the internet, are just the yellow time creeping in into our green and blue zones. Don’t get me wrong, these are important and fun, but we should not allow them to take up all our leisure time. We &lt;strong&gt;must protect our time and capacity to engage if fully restorative rest&lt;/strong&gt;, to enter, and stay in, the green and blue states of mind. In terms of &lt;strong&gt;return on investment, it may be one of the best things to do for our health and wellbeing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more thorough write-up on deep rest, check the article &lt;em&gt;Deep Rest: An Integrative Model of How Contemplative Practices Combat Stress and Enhance the Body’s Restorative Capacity&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://psyarxiv.com/bkg3j/download?format=pdf&quot;&gt;psyarxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="health" /><category term="health" /><category term="science" /><category term="mind" /><summary type="html">Kate woke up early, knowing she had a packed day ahead of her. She went through her morning routine assuredly and quickly. As usual, she brewed her favorite ginger-mint tea, this time with an extra drop of honey as if it could give her the extra energy, she felt she lacked after a poor night’s sleep. While waiting for the tea to cool down a bit, she quickly typed few supportive messages to her college best friend … her mother has recently gotten quite ill and the friend struggles to cope. Pity they cannot meet up she thought, by now they became geographically too separated. Before brushing her teeth, she put on music in the bathroom, her favorite singer just put out a new album and it’s really good. On her way out she passes by the bedroom to kiss her lover goodbye, and out she goes. No breakfast, that she will have to grab on her way. Photo by Jeffrey Czum on Pexels. Things go well for her at the office. The presentation she was nervous about runs well and she receives positive feedback from her supervisors, so the extra hours she has been putting in apparently have paid off. Some more meetings, a bit of editing work on a report she is finishing, a coffee break with coworkers. On the way home she stops by her favorite yoga studio as a small reward for the day. Finally, home, hungry as she had just a sandwich for lunch. The fridge is quite empty, and by now she is not in the mood for doing groceries, so it will be dinner delivery, maybe tacos? She finishes them while lounging on the sofa, rewatching one of her favorite shows while also texting her mum about the day she had, and looking up tickets for a concert that is coming up in her favorite club next month. Busy-ness has become the default condition This looks like an average day, doesn’t it? It even sounds quite nice. In many ways probably akin to your average day. If someone asked Kate, how is she doing, how likely do you think her answer would include the word ‘busy’ in it? Probably quite likely, and not dissimilar to how would you have replied. ‘How are you’ is a standard question we get, but how about the following ones: Do you think Kate likes being busy? Do you think ‘busyness’ works for her? Do you think she is getting enough rest and in the right form? These are quite simple questions, and the answers to them are not that difficult to guess, but strangely enough, we rarely raise them with our friends, or ourselves for that matter. So, in this post I want to ask them: Do you like being busy? Are you getting an adequate amount of rest? It has become the semi-default that we stopped questioning. Most of us lead busy lives. Maybe it’s the price we must pay to be financially comfortable? And why not actually? Many of us (including me) like it (maybe bit too much). But the moment you really let the question of whether you like being busy or not sink in, something changes. Because the chances are, you don’t. And even if you do like it, not all the time. Not all rest is made equal While most of us will probably be able to say that they are getting some rest during an average week, few will have a sense of whether it is enough or not. I certainly did not, until recently when I was prompted to think about times when I felt really relaxed. The middle-of-vacation falling asleep on a beach type of relaxed. Or when you have done a good yoga session and just sink down to savasana that you don’t want to end. You probably can think of similar experiences when obligations temporarily vanished from your horizon and your body melted as well. So sure, I have memories of feeling super relaxed, but when was the last time I got a chance to feel like it? It must be a while. As it turns out, most of us are not getting enough rest. Partially because we don’t get enough time in our busy lives for it, but mainly because we are not prioritizing the right type of rest. In her recent book, The Stress Prescription, Elissa Epel defines four different mind states as they relate to stress, red mind (acute stress), yellow (baseline cognitive load), green mind (rest), blue mind (deep rest). We spend most of our days in the yellow zone. Not only at work, but also most of the time around it, when our mind is processing obligations, making plans, engaging in socially, or just plain scrolling or browsing on our devices. Stress and rest scale illustration. While the red zone looks down-right undesirable, it actually is a place we should actively seek out. It’s healthy to engage in activities that get you there for a limited period of time, provided they are self-inflicted (HIIT, cold and heat exposure, hyperventilation, …) as these mount up your general stress resilience on a long run. Green mind is what we commonly associate with rest. It’s a pleasant state of relaxation when we are fully engaged in leisure activities. It’s a state when you are just being, not being asked to do something. This is facilitated by observation and engagement in a single task (so no multitasking). Think of being in nature or watching a performance. Watching a show on your TV at home would fit here as well, as long as you are fully immersed and don’t have your attention to repeatedly drift to your phone, the fridge, or some responsibilities coming up (which is unlikely - it’s easier to reach this state of mind in a theater or cinema, as your mind associates these places with the single task of observing art). Engaging in sports is an area that is ambiguous. At times you will be in the yellow or even red zones, at brief times in the green one. If you feel you are fully engaged (i.e. in a state of ‘flow’) you are probably in the green zone. It’s also something that has large learned factor to it – if you have been performing this sport or playing this game for some time already, such that you feel some sense of mastery doing it, the time you spend it the green zone will likely be higher. And how about the blue zone? It turns out that one is both vital for restoration, and barely visited by most during wake time. It’s a state of rest that occurs when we are in a quiet and safe environment, typically physically secluded, focusing on just one thing (e.g. our breath) or having attention openly drifting. This type of rest occurs during a deep sleep (and that also why it’s important to get enough sleep!) and during mind mind-body practices such as meditation. Getting enough deep rest is vital for health and wellbeing After I learnt about this, I tried looking at my daily activities through the red-yellow-green-blue lens and realized that I am by far not prioritizing rest the way I thought I am, or nearly as much. Chances are you will feel the same. Should you care? Is this anyhow a big deal? Well it kind of is. Researchers have looked at various ways people achieve deep rest (i.e., blue state of mind). In one study, they had people meditate for 20 minutes daily, and meet with a coach weekly. This not only left the people feeling better, but resulted in positive gene expression changes related to energy metabolism, insulin secretion, telomere maintenance, and inflammation (Bhasin et al., 2013). In another study, people were invited to join 6-day long meditation retreat and, again, left not only feeling better but also reporting similar health benefits on the gene expression level. This effect applied even to a control group, that just spent 6-day of free time, without meditation (something the researchers called the ‘vacation effect’), and was further strengthen in those who meditated and were accustomed to the meditation practice (Epel et al., 2016). As it turns out, restorative rest is a powerful modulator of our health and biology. Evidence suggests that not leaving time and space for it can lead to disease and faster the progression of aging. While on the face of it we do have enough time for leisure, and many would use it to also engage in it, we rarely see it as an opportunity to get deeply immersed in something. In fact, lot of things we would do in our leisure time, such as engaging in sports, catching up with friends, browsing the internet, are just the yellow time creeping in into our green and blue zones. Don’t get me wrong, these are important and fun, but we should not allow them to take up all our leisure time. We must protect our time and capacity to engage if fully restorative rest, to enter, and stay in, the green and blue states of mind. In terms of return on investment, it may be one of the best things to do for our health and wellbeing. References For more thorough write-up on deep rest, check the article Deep Rest: An Integrative Model of How Contemplative Practices Combat Stress and Enhance the Body’s Restorative Capacity on psyarxiv.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Clean Indoor Air Manifesto</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clean Indoor Air Manifesto" /><published>2023-12-02T11:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-02T11:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto.html">&lt;p&gt;Humans spend 90% or more of their time indoors. 90%, that’s more than some species of whale spend underwater. Spending most time indoors means breathing mainly indoor air, and it thus goes that its quality has important impact on our health. Most of us care about what we eat and drink, yet we rarely question the quality of air we breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While standards exist for quality of indoor air, they are mostly limited to concentrations of pollutants and temperature. There are limited and rare regulations for concentration of CO2 (levels of which are even more rarely measured) and virtually no regulations on concentrations of airborne pathogens. That’s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;indoor-co2-and-aerosols&quot;&gt;Indoor CO2 and aerosols&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CO2 levels affect our immediate cognitive ability. In areas with low CO2, cognitive test scores have been reported &lt;a href=&quot;https://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/doi/10.1289/ehp.1510037&quot;&gt;61% higher than in areas with relatively high CO2&lt;/a&gt;. Mind you, this study designated ‘high CO2’ as a level just half of what has &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/ina.12403&quot;&gt;another study&lt;/a&gt; found to be a common level in classrooms!
Poor air quality not only makes us dumb, it also makes us sick. Indoor airborne transmission is the major route of spread for the most common viruses such as influenza, and now SARS-CoV-2 as well. And not only directly from someone coughing at us, but also from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.abd9149&quot;&gt;breathing indoor air&lt;/a&gt; where they remain suspended in the air for extended amount of time as aerosols. &lt;a href=&quot;https://raeng.org.uk/media/fupdixju/nera-social-cost-benefit-analysis.pdf&quot;&gt;One study estimated&lt;/a&gt; that half of all infections happen in just 5% of all indoor areas, high occupancy public buildings such as airports, schools, gyms, exhibition halls, theaters, music venues, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ventilation-is-helpful-but-not-sufficient&quot;&gt;Ventilation is helpful, but not sufficient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot, and should not, opt out of indoors. This is most of where we work, socialize, meet our needs, and enjoy conveniences. We, therefore, must ventilate and sterilize the indoor air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Ventilate?’, you say, ‘aren’t we doing it already?’ We are, but very very poorly. The high occupancy areas described above tend to have ventilation with air exchange per hour (ACH, a common way how to quantify the rate of ventilation in an indoor environment) of 1 or 2. At this rate, it will take hours before airborne contaminant concentration is reduced by 99.9%. That’s incredibly slow. For comparison, at ACH 6 it is still pretty slow and will take over an hour for the same reduction. As another point of reference, pharmaceutical manufacturing spaces, where environmental quality is very important for the manufacturing process, often require &lt;strong&gt;several hundreds (!) of ACH&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, we have a long way to go before significantly improving the quality of our indoor environments. Technologically, we are not even quite there yet. While ventilation with very high ACH is possible, it needs to be designed for at construction (something that is not possible in existing buildings), requires high energy input and frequent maintenance, and may actually not be pleasant for building occupants (e.g., due to noise and air streams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;far-uvc-inactivates-airborne-pathogens&quot;&gt;Far-UVC inactivates airborne pathogens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an early-stage alternative that holds a lot of promise: far UVC. Far UVC, is light at the high energy spectrum. With wavelength of ~220 nm it does not penetrate human skin or retina, but being UV it does kill microorganisms including viruses, bacteria and fungi. Early scientific studies showed that it can efficiently sterilize indoor air and surfaces (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-67211-2&quot;&gt;Buonanno, 2020&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-022-08462-z&quot;&gt;Eadie, 2022&lt;/a&gt;). It can deliver &lt;strong&gt;50-100-fold improvement over current ventilation systems&lt;/strong&gt; in terms of relative air exchange (ACHe) and could also be mounted in already existing buildings. Bringing manufacturing costs down, as well as carrying out epidemiological studies needs to be done before large scale deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plants-have-many-qualities-but-air-purification-is-not-one-of-them-yet&quot;&gt;Plants have many qualities, but air-purification is not one of them (yet)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UVC seems great, but you must be wondering how about good old plants – aren’t they also cleaning the air? Can’t we just have more plants everywhere? I would love that as well, so I looked into it. It turns out that the only thing plants can do reasonably well is regulating indoor humidity. When it comes to CO2 removal, &lt;strong&gt;plants sequester only negligible amount of the indoor CO2&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-08-088504-9.00325-1&quot;&gt;Llewellyn and Dixon, 2011&lt;/a&gt;). This is because they need just a tiny amount of it for photosynthesis. Moreover, &lt;strong&gt;some potted plant systems are even net positive CO2 emitters&lt;/strong&gt; due to the composition of substrate in the pot (!). Finally, even if plants would photosynthesize like crazy, they would still only deal with CO2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not ready to give up on plants. Being a synthetic biologist, I am aware that there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erz029&quot;&gt;efforts to engineer plants for higher CO2 sequestration rates&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, their &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tibtech.2018.10.008&quot;&gt;microbial symbions can be engineered to do the same&lt;/a&gt;. There are also &lt;a href=&quot;https://neoplants.com/&quot;&gt;startups that engineer plants to remove pollutants from the indoor air&lt;/a&gt;. I remain a plant-optimist. When coupled together with building design that brings in more light and improves passive indoor ventilation, I believe plants will have a small but important role to play in improving the quality of indoor air in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;become-an-indoor-clean-air-activist&quot;&gt;Become an indoor clean air activist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can you do while waiting for UVC to hit the mass market and synthetic biologists to engineer more plants? You can certainly use the information you saw here to remind yourself to &lt;strong&gt;ventilate your indoor spaces frequently&lt;/strong&gt;. I would also &lt;strong&gt;get a CO2 meter and measure the ambient concentration in spaces where you spend the most time&lt;/strong&gt; (at home in your living room and bedroom, at the office). When &lt;strong&gt;you walk into a crowded space&lt;/strong&gt;, be proactive and &lt;strong&gt;ask for it to be better ventilated&lt;/strong&gt; if you can. If you are maybe feeling slightly sick, like your immunity may not be in the best shape that day, &lt;strong&gt;consider skipping that party or concert that you know will be crowded and poorly ventilated&lt;/strong&gt; – the chances that you catch an airborne virus are quite high, and that may not be worth it. If you are an employer, &lt;strong&gt;ask your employees about the indoor environment and whether they recall getting sick while at the office&lt;/strong&gt;, especially if you implement some changes (occupancy, ventilation, …) or move offices. &lt;strong&gt;Show your love for local businesses that make the effort to create a nice indoor environment&lt;/strong&gt;. If you consistently notice the place has fresh air, is well ventilated, is not overbooked, and maybe even uses UVC (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wgbh.org/news/local/2022-07-06/with-ultraviolet-protection-one-boston-cabaret-may-be-safer-from-covid-19-than-almost-anywhere&quot;&gt;this bar in Boston&lt;/a&gt;) – thank the owners and spread the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take a while but together, we will make indoor spaces healthier environments for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/indoor-air-quality/&quot;&gt;a great article&lt;/a&gt; by Juan Cambeiro and Brian Potter over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/&quot;&gt;Institute for Progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="health" /><category term="biosecurity" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html">Humans spend 90% or more of their time indoors. 90%, that’s more than some species of whale spend underwater. Spending most time indoors means breathing mainly indoor air, and it thus goes that its quality has important impact on our health. Most of us care about what we eat and drink, yet we rarely question the quality of air we breathe. While standards exist for quality of indoor air, they are mostly limited to concentrations of pollutants and temperature. There are limited and rare regulations for concentration of CO2 (levels of which are even more rarely measured) and virtually no regulations on concentrations of airborne pathogens. That’s not enough. Indoor CO2 and aerosols CO2 levels affect our immediate cognitive ability. In areas with low CO2, cognitive test scores have been reported 61% higher than in areas with relatively high CO2. Mind you, this study designated ‘high CO2’ as a level just half of what has another study found to be a common level in classrooms! Poor air quality not only makes us dumb, it also makes us sick. Indoor airborne transmission is the major route of spread for the most common viruses such as influenza, and now SARS-CoV-2 as well. And not only directly from someone coughing at us, but also from breathing indoor air where they remain suspended in the air for extended amount of time as aerosols. One study estimated that half of all infections happen in just 5% of all indoor areas, high occupancy public buildings such as airports, schools, gyms, exhibition halls, theaters, music venues, etc. Ventilation is helpful, but not sufficient We cannot, and should not, opt out of indoors. This is most of where we work, socialize, meet our needs, and enjoy conveniences. We, therefore, must ventilate and sterilize the indoor air. ‘Ventilate?’, you say, ‘aren’t we doing it already?’ We are, but very very poorly. The high occupancy areas described above tend to have ventilation with air exchange per hour (ACH, a common way how to quantify the rate of ventilation in an indoor environment) of 1 or 2. At this rate, it will take hours before airborne contaminant concentration is reduced by 99.9%. That’s incredibly slow. For comparison, at ACH 6 it is still pretty slow and will take over an hour for the same reduction. As another point of reference, pharmaceutical manufacturing spaces, where environmental quality is very important for the manufacturing process, often require several hundreds (!) of ACH. Clearly, we have a long way to go before significantly improving the quality of our indoor environments. Technologically, we are not even quite there yet. While ventilation with very high ACH is possible, it needs to be designed for at construction (something that is not possible in existing buildings), requires high energy input and frequent maintenance, and may actually not be pleasant for building occupants (e.g., due to noise and air streams). Far-UVC inactivates airborne pathogens There is an early-stage alternative that holds a lot of promise: far UVC. Far UVC, is light at the high energy spectrum. With wavelength of ~220 nm it does not penetrate human skin or retina, but being UV it does kill microorganisms including viruses, bacteria and fungi. Early scientific studies showed that it can efficiently sterilize indoor air and surfaces (Buonanno, 2020 and Eadie, 2022). It can deliver 50-100-fold improvement over current ventilation systems in terms of relative air exchange (ACHe) and could also be mounted in already existing buildings. Bringing manufacturing costs down, as well as carrying out epidemiological studies needs to be done before large scale deployment. Plants have many qualities, but air-purification is not one of them (yet) UVC seems great, but you must be wondering how about good old plants – aren’t they also cleaning the air? Can’t we just have more plants everywhere? I would love that as well, so I looked into it. It turns out that the only thing plants can do reasonably well is regulating indoor humidity. When it comes to CO2 removal, plants sequester only negligible amount of the indoor CO2 (Llewellyn and Dixon, 2011). This is because they need just a tiny amount of it for photosynthesis. Moreover, some potted plant systems are even net positive CO2 emitters due to the composition of substrate in the pot (!). Finally, even if plants would photosynthesize like crazy, they would still only deal with CO2. I am not ready to give up on plants. Being a synthetic biologist, I am aware that there are efforts to engineer plants for higher CO2 sequestration rates. Similarly, their microbial symbions can be engineered to do the same. There are also startups that engineer plants to remove pollutants from the indoor air. I remain a plant-optimist. When coupled together with building design that brings in more light and improves passive indoor ventilation, I believe plants will have a small but important role to play in improving the quality of indoor air in the future. Become an indoor clean air activist So what can you do while waiting for UVC to hit the mass market and synthetic biologists to engineer more plants? You can certainly use the information you saw here to remind yourself to ventilate your indoor spaces frequently. I would also get a CO2 meter and measure the ambient concentration in spaces where you spend the most time (at home in your living room and bedroom, at the office). When you walk into a crowded space, be proactive and ask for it to be better ventilated if you can. If you are maybe feeling slightly sick, like your immunity may not be in the best shape that day, consider skipping that party or concert that you know will be crowded and poorly ventilated – the chances that you catch an airborne virus are quite high, and that may not be worth it. If you are an employer, ask your employees about the indoor environment and whether they recall getting sick while at the office, especially if you implement some changes (occupancy, ventilation, …) or move offices. Show your love for local businesses that make the effort to create a nice indoor environment. If you consistently notice the place has fresh air, is well ventilated, is not overbooked, and maybe even uses UVC (such as this bar in Boston) – thank the owners and spread the word. It will take a while but together, we will make indoor spaces healthier environments for everyone. This post was inspired by a great article by Juan Cambeiro and Brian Potter over at Institute for Progress.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Holiday Season, I Choose To Be Grateful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Holiday Season, I Choose To Be Grateful" /><published>2023-11-26T12:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-26T12:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason.html">&lt;p&gt;The holiday season is coming, and the cultural message is that we need to host amazing dinner parties and buy expensive and well-thought-out gifts. While that certainly won’t hurt, it takes the attention away from why we are doing this in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this holiday season, I am deciding to focus on something that actually matters to me, namely on expressing gratitude and appreciation to people that touched my life this year. I am going to make this really easy. Imagine an advent calendar (a sort of bonbonniere where children and adults alike eat one piece of chocolate for each day in December before Christmas Eve), but in inverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/adventcalendar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
A photo of an advent calendar by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@miracleday?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Elena Mozhvilo&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each day in December, I will spend five to ten minutes thinking about an experience that happened this year, that someone enabled and/or touched my life during. I will then &lt;strong&gt;write down a thank-you note&lt;/strong&gt; where I specifically describe &lt;strong&gt;how this person affected me at that moment and in the time that followed, what I learnt from them and the experience, how I remember their efforts and why I am grateful.&lt;/strong&gt; I will &lt;strong&gt;write this by hand, using complete sentences&lt;/strong&gt;. If I still have their contact, I will &lt;strong&gt;share this note with them*, either direclty as handwriting, the photo therof, or as a typed message&lt;/strong&gt;. Finally, I will crumple up the note and put it in a glass jar. At the end of the month, the jar will contain some twenty to thirty gratitude notes. I guess you could call it the emotional equivalent of a piggy bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, this sounds like a good idea. For sure it’s a nice gift to give to someone and the other person will appreciate it. As I am writing this down, I am already super excited about reconnecting with my friends and others and sharing how they impacted my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it goes quite a bit further, it is also a fantastic gift for oneself. There is lot of scientific literature to attest that gratitude practice is an extremely effective way to improve one’s mental and physical health. It encourages the savoring of positive life experiences and strengthens socials bonds. There is host of physiological benefits that have been reported in literature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-reported physical health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engagement in healthy and prosocial activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Willingness to ask for help and advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More feelings of happiness, pride, and hope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater feeling of social connection, strengthening of intimate bonds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduction in risk for depression, anxiety, and substance abuse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved biomarker profile for cardiovascular disease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvement of sleep and energy levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress and illness resilience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holiday season, I choose to be grateful. Will you join me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-resources&quot;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/WHOLEHEALTHLIBRARY/tools/creating-gratitude-practice.asp&quot;&gt;Creating a Gratitude Practice&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This document contains further rationale for estabilishing a gratitude practice, as well as more detailed instructions on how to implement it. It has multiple references for the health benefits described above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ZizdB0TgAVM?si=Lms7EVbikBXPU1PH&amp;amp;t=1922&quot;&gt;Dr. Laurie Santos on the importance of gratitude&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This part of Laurie Santos’s talk highlights the importance of gratitude practice, and how sharing it with others is beneficial for both the one sharing, as well as the one receving it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="mental-health" /><category term="mental-health" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">The holiday season is coming, and the cultural message is that we need to host amazing dinner parties and buy expensive and well-thought-out gifts. While that certainly won’t hurt, it takes the attention away from why we are doing this in the first place. For this holiday season, I am deciding to focus on something that actually matters to me, namely on expressing gratitude and appreciation to people that touched my life this year. I am going to make this really easy. Imagine an advent calendar (a sort of bonbonniere where children and adults alike eat one piece of chocolate for each day in December before Christmas Eve), but in inverse. A photo of an advent calendar by Elena Mozhvilo on Unsplash. Each day in December, I will spend five to ten minutes thinking about an experience that happened this year, that someone enabled and/or touched my life during. I will then write down a thank-you note where I specifically describe how this person affected me at that moment and in the time that followed, what I learnt from them and the experience, how I remember their efforts and why I am grateful. I will write this by hand, using complete sentences. If I still have their contact, I will share this note with them*, either direclty as handwriting, the photo therof, or as a typed message. Finally, I will crumple up the note and put it in a glass jar. At the end of the month, the jar will contain some twenty to thirty gratitude notes. I guess you could call it the emotional equivalent of a piggy bank. Intuitively, this sounds like a good idea. For sure it’s a nice gift to give to someone and the other person will appreciate it. As I am writing this down, I am already super excited about reconnecting with my friends and others and sharing how they impacted my life. But it goes quite a bit further, it is also a fantastic gift for oneself. There is lot of scientific literature to attest that gratitude practice is an extremely effective way to improve one’s mental and physical health. It encourages the savoring of positive life experiences and strengthens socials bonds. There is host of physiological benefits that have been reported in literature: Self-reported physical health Engagement in healthy and prosocial activities Willingness to ask for help and advice More feelings of happiness, pride, and hope Greater feeling of social connection, strengthening of intimate bonds Reduction in risk for depression, anxiety, and substance abuse Improved biomarker profile for cardiovascular disease Improvement of sleep and energy levels Stress and illness resilience This holiday season, I choose to be grateful. Will you join me? Further Resources Creating a Gratitude Practice This document contains further rationale for estabilishing a gratitude practice, as well as more detailed instructions on how to implement it. It has multiple references for the health benefits described above. Dr. Laurie Santos on the importance of gratitude This part of Laurie Santos’s talk highlights the importance of gratitude practice, and how sharing it with others is beneficial for both the one sharing, as well as the one receving it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World on Scientific Canvas - Three Plots to Make You Think</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World on Scientific Canvas - Three Plots to Make You Think" /><published>2023-11-02T19:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T19:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots.html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first post in a new series where I highlight plots that I came across in scientific literature that will be interesting for a broad audience. Today I look at why poor stay poor (economic inequality), why you should move to Italy but not Singapore (labor productivity), and why buying processed foods costs you more than you think (microbiome diversity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot-1-economic-connectedness-is-by-far-the-most-impactful-way-to-increase-economic-mobility-in-the-us&quot;&gt;Plot 1. Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility (in the US)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/social_capital_i_EC.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility. Figure from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04996-4.pdf&quot;&gt;Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot comes from the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04996-4.pdf&quot;&gt;Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility&lt;/a&gt; which, already from the title, is absolutely a stunning read. The researchers looked at what are drivers of upward economic mobility (in the US!) and concluded that one that matters by far the most is the relative share of high socioeconomic status (SES) friends, a quantity they termed economic connectedness. They find that if low-income children had the same type of friends as high-income children do, they would earn 20% more on average in adulthood! So what does this mean? You, dear reader, are probably relatively wealthy or have a good chance of being so in the future so if you care about economic inequality (and you should, because in the long run it hurst everybody!) go ahead and make friends with everyone, especially with people of relatively low SES!
Equally stunningly, many places which you would have thought are great destinations to elevate one’s or one’s family SES (e.g., Bay Area) are performing very poorly on economic connectedness, and consequently you would be better off moving to plenty of other places, many of which are much cheaper to live in. If you did not think segregation or gentrification is a problem, now you know it is. You can find the map of economic connectedness in the US here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.socialcapital.org/&quot;&gt;socialcapital.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot-2-the-harder-you-work-the-poorer-you-get-geographically-speaking&quot;&gt;Plot 2. The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking). Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would probably think that considering a country’s GDP is relevant when trying to find out where to relocate to, but that number tells you very little about how hard attaining that level of income may be. It turns out that labor productivity, how many hours you have to work to earn a certain wage, is more informative. The plot I chose shows that if you live in Singapore, you will have about double the annual income of someone living in Italy, but you will pay for this by working over 600 hours per year more on average. That’s over 75 8-hour working days a year! You can make many more comparisons yourself if you head over to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked&quot;&gt;interactive plot at ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;. 
There is more insight that can be gleaned from the plot. One is, for example, that while we have done away with slavery as conventionally defined, its modern-day equivalent is rampant. The GDP of Bangladesh is 8% that of the Netherlands, while people in Bangladesh work nearly 1’000 hours per year more to earn it. That’s over 120 8-hour days a year! And that says nothing about the conditions this work is done in! This becomes even more obscene of one makes the comparison with Luxembourg, Switzerland, or Norway. 
If you consider the trend on the plot, you will quickly see that in countries with more productive workers, people tend to work less. That by extension leads to another insight: Don’t be afraid AI will take our jobs! Look forward to it instead! It is the most effective tool for increasing labor productivity we have nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot3-the-western-diet-makes-up-in-calories-for-what-it-lacks-in-diversity&quot;&gt;Plot3. The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/westernizedMicrobiome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity. Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.10.029&quot;&gt;US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome&lt;/a&gt; showing participants BMI and dietary patterns at the beginning end and of study. Faith’s phylogenetic distance (PD) quantifies diversity (in this case in participants’ diets)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.10.029&quot;&gt;US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome&lt;/a&gt;) looked at Thai immigrants to the US over tens of years (including first and second gen immigrants) and compared their dietary patterns and some biomarkers to the control of US population. It found out that the immigrant microbiome gradually becomes US-like which also means it loses much of the original bacterial strains that can digest plant fiber. This appears to be a product of dietary changes. The US diet is markedly less diverse than the original Thai one and the immigrants gradually gravitate towards. The western diet is higher in fat and sugar and relatively lower in protein. Not surprisingly this leads to BMI increase, as well as increase of prevalence of obesity among immigrants over the years they reside in the US. The immediate takeaway here is, if you move to the US or live there already, do watch your diet (eating &lt;a href=&quot;/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html&quot;&gt;plant-based&lt;/a&gt; would help)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-remarks&quot;&gt;Final remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok those were three of the many figures I looked at recently that made me stop and think! I hope you have gotten something useful from them as well. All three plots come from papers or resources that are freely accessible so go ahead and dig deeper into the studies if you find them interesting! Thanks for reading everyone 😊&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="scicomm" /><summary type="html">This is the first post in a new series where I highlight plots that I came across in scientific literature that will be interesting for a broad audience. Today I look at why poor stay poor (economic inequality), why you should move to Italy but not Singapore (labor productivity), and why buying processed foods costs you more than you think (microbiome diversity). Plot 1. Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility (in the US) Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility. Figure from Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility This plot comes from the paper Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility which, already from the title, is absolutely a stunning read. The researchers looked at what are drivers of upward economic mobility (in the US!) and concluded that one that matters by far the most is the relative share of high socioeconomic status (SES) friends, a quantity they termed economic connectedness. They find that if low-income children had the same type of friends as high-income children do, they would earn 20% more on average in adulthood! So what does this mean? You, dear reader, are probably relatively wealthy or have a good chance of being so in the future so if you care about economic inequality (and you should, because in the long run it hurst everybody!) go ahead and make friends with everyone, especially with people of relatively low SES! Equally stunningly, many places which you would have thought are great destinations to elevate one’s or one’s family SES (e.g., Bay Area) are performing very poorly on economic connectedness, and consequently you would be better off moving to plenty of other places, many of which are much cheaper to live in. If you did not think segregation or gentrification is a problem, now you know it is. You can find the map of economic connectedness in the US here: socialcapital.org. Plot 2. The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking) The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking). Figure adapted from ourworldindata.org You would probably think that considering a country’s GDP is relevant when trying to find out where to relocate to, but that number tells you very little about how hard attaining that level of income may be. It turns out that labor productivity, how many hours you have to work to earn a certain wage, is more informative. The plot I chose shows that if you live in Singapore, you will have about double the annual income of someone living in Italy, but you will pay for this by working over 600 hours per year more on average. That’s over 75 8-hour working days a year! You can make many more comparisons yourself if you head over to the interactive plot at ourworldindata.org. There is more insight that can be gleaned from the plot. One is, for example, that while we have done away with slavery as conventionally defined, its modern-day equivalent is rampant. The GDP of Bangladesh is 8% that of the Netherlands, while people in Bangladesh work nearly 1’000 hours per year more to earn it. That’s over 120 8-hour days a year! And that says nothing about the conditions this work is done in! This becomes even more obscene of one makes the comparison with Luxembourg, Switzerland, or Norway. If you consider the trend on the plot, you will quickly see that in countries with more productive workers, people tend to work less. That by extension leads to another insight: Don’t be afraid AI will take our jobs! Look forward to it instead! It is the most effective tool for increasing labor productivity we have nowadays. Plot3. The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity. Figure adapted from US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome showing participants BMI and dietary patterns at the beginning end and of study. Faith’s phylogenetic distance (PD) quantifies diversity (in this case in participants’ diets) This study (US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome) looked at Thai immigrants to the US over tens of years (including first and second gen immigrants) and compared their dietary patterns and some biomarkers to the control of US population. It found out that the immigrant microbiome gradually becomes US-like which also means it loses much of the original bacterial strains that can digest plant fiber. This appears to be a product of dietary changes. The US diet is markedly less diverse than the original Thai one and the immigrants gradually gravitate towards. The western diet is higher in fat and sugar and relatively lower in protein. Not surprisingly this leads to BMI increase, as well as increase of prevalence of obesity among immigrants over the years they reside in the US. The immediate takeaway here is, if you move to the US or live there already, do watch your diet (eating plant-based would help)! Final remarks Ok those were three of the many figures I looked at recently that made me stop and think! I hope you have gotten something useful from them as well. All three plots come from papers or resources that are freely accessible so go ahead and dig deeper into the studies if you find them interesting! Thanks for reading everyone 😊</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive Into Plant-Based Diets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive Into Plant-Based Diets" /><published>2023-10-18T19:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T19:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html">&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets have become increasingly popular in recent years, with many people choosing to adopt them for health, environmental, or ethical reasons. In this article, I will explore the origins of plant-based diets, their current state, health benefits, potential side effects, and their suitability for athletes. I will also discuss how plant-based diets can help with weight loss and their impact on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origins-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Origins of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets have been around for thousands of years. Much of their history arose in 1500 – 500 BCE on the Indian subcontinent. Also, the ancient Greeks, including athletes, were known to consume plant-based diets, with records dating as far back as 6th century BCE. Aside from that, the early hominids from roughly 2 million years ago were primarily vegan, with opportunistic omnivorous behavior.
Today, while plant-based diets are becoming more popular, relatively modest proportion of 5-10% of people worldwide are eating them. There is a spectrum of plant-based diets, ranging from pescatarian to lacto(-ovo-)vegetarian to vegan. No diet is perfect for everyone, and it’s critical that you consider what foods are available to you, what foods are your staples, and what you can do without, when determining which diet to follow (i.e. the structure of your diet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/michelin_diet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://guide.michelin.com/us/en/article/wellness/a-guide-to-the-vegetarian-spectrum&quot;&gt;guide.michelin.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/diettypes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.precisionnutrition.com/plant-based-nutrition&quot;&gt;precisionnutrition.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health-benefits-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Health Benefits of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main motivations to opt for a plant-based diet is that they have been linked to a variety of health benefits. For example, plant-based were reported to reduce the risk of ischemic disease by 25% and even lower the overall risk of cancer by approximately 10% for some types (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2016.1138447&quot;&gt;Dinu, Abbate, Gensini, Casini, &amp;amp; Sofi, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). There is also strong evidence that they reduce the risk of diabetes by 28% (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9060603&quot;&gt;Lee &amp;amp; Park, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Let’s note in passing that 10% of the worldwide population has diabetes(&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/diabetes-prevalence?tab=table&quot;&gt;ourwoldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;), which is a tremendous socioeconomic cost, so anything that can help alleviate that should be seriously considered. 
While the above benefits are very concrete, the studies could not control for the confounding fact that people who decide to adopt-plant based diet tend to lead healthier lifestyles (fewer smokers, less overweight, more frequent exercise, less alcohol, …). It remains disputable whether there is any inherent benefit to eating plant-based per-se, and if there is one, it will most probably be small. It’s more likely that the true benefits of plant-based diet come from increasing our awareness about what we eat, supporting adoption of healthy lifestyle patterns and facilitating adherence. This includes removing processed meat, which is known to increase the risk of cardiovascular disease, stroke, colon, and rectal cancers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1161/circulationaha.109.924977&quot;&gt;Micha, Wallace, &amp;amp; Mozaffarian, 2010&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1161/circheartfailure.113.000921&quot;&gt;Kaluza, Akesson, &amp;amp; Wolk, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, there is strong evidence that high temperature cooking (such as pan frying, charring, barbecuing) leads to formation of carcinogenic compounds and that amounts of these are particularly elevated in red meats (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/01635580802710741&quot;&gt;Zheng &amp;amp; Lee, 2009&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2011.2287&quot;&gt;Pan et al., 2012&lt;/a&gt;). Plant-based diets avoid consuming meats prepared in this way as they avoid meat in the first place (duh :)).
While the health benefits of plant-based diets may be indirect, this in my opinion does not subtract from their attractiveness for reaching certain health goals. However, even a plant diet can be an unhealthy one. It’s critical to eat whole and healthy foods, irrespective of diet’s structure. That means avoiding processed and high-added sugar foods and consuming equilibrated profile of macro and micronutrients. Such a diet would also lead to higher fiber intake which is implicated in the reduction of risk for colon and rectal cancers. There is nothing wrong with fat either, it’s unprocessed sources such as nuts and seeds tend to be high in fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K) and the healthy mono/poly-unsaturated fatty acids. Consuming an unhealthy plant-based diet is associated with poor health outcomes, even worse than control (so people who keep eating whatever they ate, including processed meat, and not adjusting their lifestyle) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1002039&quot;&gt;Satija et al., 2016&lt;/a&gt;). 
Finally, the above highlights the importance of lifestyle when it comes to health outcomes. To optimize health outcomes, it’s vital to look beyond diet and consider your sleep, exercise, alcohol intake, smoking, and mental fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-weight-loss&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for Weight Loss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets are generally effective for weight loss. However, research shows that other diets can be equally effective, irrespective of their structure (i.e. if they are plant-based or not) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.297.9.969&quot;&gt;Gardner et al., 2007&lt;/a&gt;). In the end, it turns out, the rule of weight loss is quite simple (that is, for most healthy individuals): On day one, consume fewer calories than you burn, on all consequent days, repeat. The advantage of plant-based diets is that they facilitate this, as plant-based, unprocessed (!), foods tend to be less calorie dense. Vegan diets are in this sense even more effective than other plant-based diets. Finally, being a (lacto/ovo-) vegetarian or vegan, is for many a part of their identity, and stops being a decision they would have to face every time when deciding what to eat, which greatly helps with adherence (an idea popularize by James Clear in his book Atomic Habits).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-side-effects-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Potential Side Effects of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many will be held back from adopting or trying plant-based diets due to concerns about their side effects. Let’s look at how much these are substantiated. It’s true of any diet, that by omission of certain foods, it may be harder to reach macro and micronutrient goals.
This is not an exception for any plant-based diet. On large sample level, these tend to lead to nutritional deficiencies. For example, up to 86.5% of vegetarians do not have adequate levels of vitamin B12 (largest of the B-complex vitamins containing cobalt in its structure essential in multitude of processes in our bodies) in their blood (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/ejcn.2014.46&quot;&gt;Pawlak, Lester, &amp;amp; Babatunde, 2014&lt;/a&gt;), and iron deficiency can be seen in up to 79% of females and up to 29% of males who adopt plant-based diets (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1177/1559827616682933&quot;&gt;Pawlak, Berger, &amp;amp; Hines, 2016&lt;/a&gt;). This is not because plant-based diets contain less iron, but because it comes in forms and combinations that make it less bioavailable. Plant-based diets are also deficient in choline (an essential nutrient and a source of methyl groups needed for many steps in our metabolism and required for synthesis of neurotransmitter acetylcholine), but there is insufficient research to show if this has any negative health implications.
Next, plant-based diets are generally deficient in omega-3 fatty acids. While some plants are good sources of the short-chain form, the long-form is found mainly in fish. Our body can to some degree convert the short-chain into long-chain fatty acids but does so only with 2-5% efficiency. 
Plant-based diets are also generally higher in carbohydrates, lower in fat, and lower in protein. A person following a plant-based diet eats on average 20-30% less protein than an omnivore. This is generally not a problem but may become a concern for someone with a very active lifestyle (see below).
There is evidence to suggest that individuals who follow a plant-based diet, especially those who follow a vegan-diet, are exposed to more phytoestrogens (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2016.10.018&quot;&gt;Tordjman et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;), which are plant derived hormone-like molecules that activate the estrogen receptor. While this has been associated with lower testosterone levels in males, more recent research shows lack of correlation and additionally suggests that estrogens have positive effects in treatment and prevention in rage of indications including skin aging, osteoporosis, cancer, cardiovascular, neurodegenerative, immune, and metabolic diseases. Additionally, estrogens have been reported to help alleviate menopausal symptoms in women (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2014.07.057&quot;&gt;Sirotkin &amp;amp; Harrath, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Overall, there seems to be little to no negative effect associated with elevated phytoestrogen exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-athletes&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for Athletes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets are compatible with active lifestyle and can be even preferable for endurance athletes such as runners and cyclists. The elevated carbohydrate consumption provided by plant-based diets translates to an increase in the amount of stored muscle glycogen. Glycogen fuels muscle contractions during intense or prolonged exercise and its increased storage helps with endurance. The general lower calorie intake of plant-based diets can also help maintain weight in certain categories and overall optimize lean muscle mass. However, a chronic insufficient calorie intake is one of major risk factors for injury and illness among athletes. 
Besides general calories insufficiency, plant-based diets tend to lead to micronutrient deficiencies, as highlighted earlier, and these can negatively impact athlete’s health and performance. Furthermore, athletes who follow a plant-based diet consume about 70% of the protein that their omnivorous counterparts consume (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu6031318&quot;&gt;Clarys et al., 2014&lt;/a&gt;), which may not be sufficient depending on one’s exercise regime and fitness goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;importance-of-tracking-supplementation-and-fortification&quot;&gt;Importance of Tracking, Supplementation and Fortification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever diet you adopt, or even if you are an omnivore, there is a chance that your micro and macronutrient intake may result in some insufficiencies in the long run. If you opt for a plant-based diet, you have good chances of having to deal with B12, choline, iron and omega-3 deficiencies. It’s equally important that your calorie and macronutrient intake matches your exercise regimen and fitness goals. 
To keep the micronutrient levels in check, I would highly recommend getting your blood work done on a regular basis. It’s the best way to see how the diet patterns that you adopt translate to micronutrient levels, and it can help identify problems in their infancy or prevent them becoming problems in the first place. It is probably clear by now that for anyone following a plant-based diet consistently, it’s extremely likely that they will have to rely on supplementation and/or fortification for some, or all, of the micronutrients listed above. There is absolutely nothing wrong with that. If you are plant-based, please don’t insist on eating 100% naturally! Get some high-quality supplements, even if it were just for prevention, and your body will thank you for that. Do some research on which supplements to choose – lately there are plenty of them on the market and many come wide widely varying micronutrient levels or levels that are well beyond what you would need. 
Similarly, and in particular if you live an active lifestyle, you should get a good sense of the amount of calories and macronutrients you are digesting, and whether this matches your expenditure and goals. There are tools that can be used to calculate how many calories do you burn at your maintenance, given your exercise patterns. Look online for TDEE, total daily energy expenditure, calculator and use a few of them and take an average for more robust estimate. If you have somewhat smart bodyweight scale, it can give you pretty good estimate as well.
Next, it’s mandatory to track the calories and specific foods that you are eating consistently, at least for some limited period. It’s not that long ago that I tried it for the first time, and I was very surprised with the result. I was on average eating about 30% less calories than I thought! Doing this will also help you understand whether you are meeting your macronutrient needs. Besides these ‘smart’ calculators, it is important to check in with your energy levels. If you feel low, make sure you are getting adequate sleep. If that is in check, look at decreasing intensity or frequency of your exercise (more rest) or increasing calorie input. Finally, if you are very active and plant-based, there is a chance you may be running too low on protein intake and then you would either want to adjust your diet or look for some high-quality vegetarian or vegan protein powder (again, nothing wrong with that!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-the-environment&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for the Environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people opt for plant-based diet to limit their environmental impact. All evidence suggests that this is a step in the right direction, yet the situation is certainly not black and white. How much of a positive impact on the environment will you have, if any, will depend on the individual products you consume on regular basis. Did you, for example, know that some types of cheese will have double to triple the emission footprint of chicken meat? Or that coffee and chocolate have similar emission footprints as some types of beef? (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/carbon-footprint-food-methane&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;). 
Furthermore, choices other than dietary ones can have a larger impact on the environment. Opting to live without a car, skipping one long-haul flight per year or moving over to renewable sources of energy can have double to triple the positive impact of going plant-based. Better home insulation, using more public transport or opting to live without a pet all have comparable effects to becoming plant-based (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab8589&quot;&gt;Ivanova et al., 2020&lt;/a&gt;). And of course, not all plant-based diets are made equal, vegan diet is about twice as effective as general plant-based diet in this regard. Somewhat unpopular, having one less child seems by far the most effective climate impact mitigation strategy (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aa7541&quot;&gt;Wines &amp;amp; Nicholas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). However, I personally choose not to weigh the environmental concerns in this aspect too heavily, as there are tons of problems associated with the aging of society as well (hope to write on that in the future!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/food_emissions.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/carbon-footprint-food-methane&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/carbon_footprint.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-52719662&quot;&gt;bbc.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever diet you adopt, make sure it works for you: Does it make you feel good? Can you stick to it? Can you afford it? Doesn’t it feel overly restrictive?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diet is a step in the right direction when aiming to improve health outcomes, but it won’t be (nearly as) effective if not accompanied by other lifestyle choices such as exercise, cigarette, and alcohol use, as well as mental health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even a plant-based diet can be an unhealthy one. Make sure to prioritize whole, unprocessed foods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maybe the largest benefit of plant-based diets is that they avoid some foods that are known to be causing disease, and that they facilitate adherence by becoming part of one’s identity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your blood work done with some periodicity and track what you eat (at least for an initial period). Supplement accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant based diets can be safely followed by athletes and are even advantageous for some forms of exercise. Supplementation is very likely to be helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant-based diets are only one the ways how to mitigate once environmental impact, and they are not the most effective ones. If the environment and health of our planet matters to you, please don’t stop here!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading everyone! Do you have any questions or thoughts spurred by the article? Did I forget to mention something obvious? I will be happy if you let me know in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post is based on an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasm.org/continuing-education/free-nasm-courses&quot;&gt;online course by the National Academy of Sports Medicine&lt;/a&gt; that is on sale as part of their promo for the vegetarian awarness month (Oct’23). I can only suggest taking it if you are interested in the topic!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="diet" /><category term="environment" /><category term="fitness" /><category term="sport" /><summary type="html">Plant-based diets have become increasingly popular in recent years, with many people choosing to adopt them for health, environmental, or ethical reasons. In this article, I will explore the origins of plant-based diets, their current state, health benefits, potential side effects, and their suitability for athletes. I will also discuss how plant-based diets can help with weight loss and their impact on the environment. Origins of Plant-Based Diets Plant-based diets have been around for thousands of years. Much of their history arose in 1500 – 500 BCE on the Indian subcontinent. Also, the ancient Greeks, including athletes, were known to consume plant-based diets, with records dating as far back as 6th century BCE. Aside from that, the early hominids from roughly 2 million years ago were primarily vegan, with opportunistic omnivorous behavior. Today, while plant-based diets are becoming more popular, relatively modest proportion of 5-10% of people worldwide are eating them. There is a spectrum of plant-based diets, ranging from pescatarian to lacto(-ovo-)vegetarian to vegan. No diet is perfect for everyone, and it’s critical that you consider what foods are available to you, what foods are your staples, and what you can do without, when determining which diet to follow (i.e. the structure of your diet). From guide.michelin.com From precisionnutrition.com Health Benefits of Plant-Based Diets One of the main motivations to opt for a plant-based diet is that they have been linked to a variety of health benefits. For example, plant-based were reported to reduce the risk of ischemic disease by 25% and even lower the overall risk of cancer by approximately 10% for some types (Dinu, Abbate, Gensini, Casini, &amp;amp; Sofi, 2017). There is also strong evidence that they reduce the risk of diabetes by 28% (Lee &amp;amp; Park, 2017). Let’s note in passing that 10% of the worldwide population has diabetes(ourwoldindata.org), which is a tremendous socioeconomic cost, so anything that can help alleviate that should be seriously considered. While the above benefits are very concrete, the studies could not control for the confounding fact that people who decide to adopt-plant based diet tend to lead healthier lifestyles (fewer smokers, less overweight, more frequent exercise, less alcohol, …). It remains disputable whether there is any inherent benefit to eating plant-based per-se, and if there is one, it will most probably be small. It’s more likely that the true benefits of plant-based diet come from increasing our awareness about what we eat, supporting adoption of healthy lifestyle patterns and facilitating adherence. This includes removing processed meat, which is known to increase the risk of cardiovascular disease, stroke, colon, and rectal cancers (Micha, Wallace, &amp;amp; Mozaffarian, 2010; Kaluza, Akesson, &amp;amp; Wolk, 2014). Furthermore, there is strong evidence that high temperature cooking (such as pan frying, charring, barbecuing) leads to formation of carcinogenic compounds and that amounts of these are particularly elevated in red meats (Zheng &amp;amp; Lee, 2009; Pan et al., 2012). Plant-based diets avoid consuming meats prepared in this way as they avoid meat in the first place (duh :)). While the health benefits of plant-based diets may be indirect, this in my opinion does not subtract from their attractiveness for reaching certain health goals. However, even a plant diet can be an unhealthy one. It’s critical to eat whole and healthy foods, irrespective of diet’s structure. That means avoiding processed and high-added sugar foods and consuming equilibrated profile of macro and micronutrients. Such a diet would also lead to higher fiber intake which is implicated in the reduction of risk for colon and rectal cancers. There is nothing wrong with fat either, it’s unprocessed sources such as nuts and seeds tend to be high in fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K) and the healthy mono/poly-unsaturated fatty acids. Consuming an unhealthy plant-based diet is associated with poor health outcomes, even worse than control (so people who keep eating whatever they ate, including processed meat, and not adjusting their lifestyle) (Satija et al., 2016). Finally, the above highlights the importance of lifestyle when it comes to health outcomes. To optimize health outcomes, it’s vital to look beyond diet and consider your sleep, exercise, alcohol intake, smoking, and mental fitness. Plant-Based Diets for Weight Loss Plant-based diets are generally effective for weight loss. However, research shows that other diets can be equally effective, irrespective of their structure (i.e. if they are plant-based or not) (Gardner et al., 2007). In the end, it turns out, the rule of weight loss is quite simple (that is, for most healthy individuals): On day one, consume fewer calories than you burn, on all consequent days, repeat. The advantage of plant-based diets is that they facilitate this, as plant-based, unprocessed (!), foods tend to be less calorie dense. Vegan diets are in this sense even more effective than other plant-based diets. Finally, being a (lacto/ovo-) vegetarian or vegan, is for many a part of their identity, and stops being a decision they would have to face every time when deciding what to eat, which greatly helps with adherence (an idea popularize by James Clear in his book Atomic Habits). Potential Side Effects of Plant-Based Diets Many will be held back from adopting or trying plant-based diets due to concerns about their side effects. Let’s look at how much these are substantiated. It’s true of any diet, that by omission of certain foods, it may be harder to reach macro and micronutrient goals. This is not an exception for any plant-based diet. On large sample level, these tend to lead to nutritional deficiencies. For example, up to 86.5% of vegetarians do not have adequate levels of vitamin B12 (largest of the B-complex vitamins containing cobalt in its structure essential in multitude of processes in our bodies) in their blood (Pawlak, Lester, &amp;amp; Babatunde, 2014), and iron deficiency can be seen in up to 79% of females and up to 29% of males who adopt plant-based diets (Pawlak, Berger, &amp;amp; Hines, 2016). This is not because plant-based diets contain less iron, but because it comes in forms and combinations that make it less bioavailable. Plant-based diets are also deficient in choline (an essential nutrient and a source of methyl groups needed for many steps in our metabolism and required for synthesis of neurotransmitter acetylcholine), but there is insufficient research to show if this has any negative health implications. Next, plant-based diets are generally deficient in omega-3 fatty acids. While some plants are good sources of the short-chain form, the long-form is found mainly in fish. Our body can to some degree convert the short-chain into long-chain fatty acids but does so only with 2-5% efficiency. Plant-based diets are also generally higher in carbohydrates, lower in fat, and lower in protein. A person following a plant-based diet eats on average 20-30% less protein than an omnivore. This is generally not a problem but may become a concern for someone with a very active lifestyle (see below). There is evidence to suggest that individuals who follow a plant-based diet, especially those who follow a vegan-diet, are exposed to more phytoestrogens (Tordjman et al. 2016), which are plant derived hormone-like molecules that activate the estrogen receptor. While this has been associated with lower testosterone levels in males, more recent research shows lack of correlation and additionally suggests that estrogens have positive effects in treatment and prevention in rage of indications including skin aging, osteoporosis, cancer, cardiovascular, neurodegenerative, immune, and metabolic diseases. Additionally, estrogens have been reported to help alleviate menopausal symptoms in women (Sirotkin &amp;amp; Harrath, 2014). Overall, there seems to be little to no negative effect associated with elevated phytoestrogen exposure. Plant-Based Diets for Athletes Plant-based diets are compatible with active lifestyle and can be even preferable for endurance athletes such as runners and cyclists. The elevated carbohydrate consumption provided by plant-based diets translates to an increase in the amount of stored muscle glycogen. Glycogen fuels muscle contractions during intense or prolonged exercise and its increased storage helps with endurance. The general lower calorie intake of plant-based diets can also help maintain weight in certain categories and overall optimize lean muscle mass. However, a chronic insufficient calorie intake is one of major risk factors for injury and illness among athletes. Besides general calories insufficiency, plant-based diets tend to lead to micronutrient deficiencies, as highlighted earlier, and these can negatively impact athlete’s health and performance. Furthermore, athletes who follow a plant-based diet consume about 70% of the protein that their omnivorous counterparts consume (Clarys et al., 2014), which may not be sufficient depending on one’s exercise regime and fitness goals. Importance of Tracking, Supplementation and Fortification Whatever diet you adopt, or even if you are an omnivore, there is a chance that your micro and macronutrient intake may result in some insufficiencies in the long run. If you opt for a plant-based diet, you have good chances of having to deal with B12, choline, iron and omega-3 deficiencies. It’s equally important that your calorie and macronutrient intake matches your exercise regimen and fitness goals. To keep the micronutrient levels in check, I would highly recommend getting your blood work done on a regular basis. It’s the best way to see how the diet patterns that you adopt translate to micronutrient levels, and it can help identify problems in their infancy or prevent them becoming problems in the first place. It is probably clear by now that for anyone following a plant-based diet consistently, it’s extremely likely that they will have to rely on supplementation and/or fortification for some, or all, of the micronutrients listed above. There is absolutely nothing wrong with that. If you are plant-based, please don’t insist on eating 100% naturally! Get some high-quality supplements, even if it were just for prevention, and your body will thank you for that. Do some research on which supplements to choose – lately there are plenty of them on the market and many come wide widely varying micronutrient levels or levels that are well beyond what you would need. Similarly, and in particular if you live an active lifestyle, you should get a good sense of the amount of calories and macronutrients you are digesting, and whether this matches your expenditure and goals. There are tools that can be used to calculate how many calories do you burn at your maintenance, given your exercise patterns. Look online for TDEE, total daily energy expenditure, calculator and use a few of them and take an average for more robust estimate. If you have somewhat smart bodyweight scale, it can give you pretty good estimate as well. Next, it’s mandatory to track the calories and specific foods that you are eating consistently, at least for some limited period. It’s not that long ago that I tried it for the first time, and I was very surprised with the result. I was on average eating about 30% less calories than I thought! Doing this will also help you understand whether you are meeting your macronutrient needs. Besides these ‘smart’ calculators, it is important to check in with your energy levels. If you feel low, make sure you are getting adequate sleep. If that is in check, look at decreasing intensity or frequency of your exercise (more rest) or increasing calorie input. Finally, if you are very active and plant-based, there is a chance you may be running too low on protein intake and then you would either want to adjust your diet or look for some high-quality vegetarian or vegan protein powder (again, nothing wrong with that!) Plant-Based Diets for the Environment Many people opt for plant-based diet to limit their environmental impact. All evidence suggests that this is a step in the right direction, yet the situation is certainly not black and white. How much of a positive impact on the environment will you have, if any, will depend on the individual products you consume on regular basis. Did you, for example, know that some types of cheese will have double to triple the emission footprint of chicken meat? Or that coffee and chocolate have similar emission footprints as some types of beef? (ourworldindata.org). Furthermore, choices other than dietary ones can have a larger impact on the environment. Opting to live without a car, skipping one long-haul flight per year or moving over to renewable sources of energy can have double to triple the positive impact of going plant-based. Better home insulation, using more public transport or opting to live without a pet all have comparable effects to becoming plant-based (Ivanova et al., 2020). And of course, not all plant-based diets are made equal, vegan diet is about twice as effective as general plant-based diet in this regard. Somewhat unpopular, having one less child seems by far the most effective climate impact mitigation strategy (Wines &amp;amp; Nicholas, 2017). However, I personally choose not to weigh the environmental concerns in this aspect too heavily, as there are tons of problems associated with the aging of society as well (hope to write on that in the future!). From ourworldindata.org From bbc.com Conclusions Whatever diet you adopt, make sure it works for you: Does it make you feel good? Can you stick to it? Can you afford it? Doesn’t it feel overly restrictive? Diet is a step in the right direction when aiming to improve health outcomes, but it won’t be (nearly as) effective if not accompanied by other lifestyle choices such as exercise, cigarette, and alcohol use, as well as mental health. Even a plant-based diet can be an unhealthy one. Make sure to prioritize whole, unprocessed foods. Maybe the largest benefit of plant-based diets is that they avoid some foods that are known to be causing disease, and that they facilitate adherence by becoming part of one’s identity. Get your blood work done with some periodicity and track what you eat (at least for an initial period). Supplement accordingly. Plant based diets can be safely followed by athletes and are even advantageous for some forms of exercise. Supplementation is very likely to be helpful. Plant-based diets are only one the ways how to mitigate once environmental impact, and they are not the most effective ones. If the environment and health of our planet matters to you, please don’t stop here! Thanks for reading everyone! Do you have any questions or thoughts spurred by the article? Did I forget to mention something obvious? I will be happy if you let me know in the comments section below! The post is based on an online course by the National Academy of Sports Medicine that is on sale as part of their promo for the vegetarian awarness month (Oct’23). I can only suggest taking it if you are interested in the topic!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 ADE Festival Personal Highligths</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 ADE Festival Personal Highligths" /><published>2023-10-16T15:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-16T15:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-19th&quot;&gt;Thursday 19th&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pieter-de-graaf--live-at-planetarium-artis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/pieter-de-graaf-live-at-planetarium-artis/279312/&quot;&gt;Pieter de Graaf | Live at Planetarium Artis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artis Planetarium, 20:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-dance-is-to-be-free&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/to-dance-is-to-be-free/279313/&quot;&gt;To Dance is to be Free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stadsarchief Amsterdam, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;live-from-earth&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/live-from-earth/279314/&quot;&gt;Live From Earth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lofi, 22:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awakenings-ade-2023-adam-beyer-presents-drumcode&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/awakenings-ade-2023-adam-beyer-presents-drumcode/279315/&quot;&gt;Awakenings ADE 2023: Adam Beyer Presents Drumcode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gashouder, 22:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kntxt-turbo-club&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/kntxt-turbo-club/279316/&quot;&gt;KNTXT Turbo Club&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Theater Amsterdam, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friday-20th&quot;&gt;Friday 20th&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ineffekt---ar-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/ineffekt-ar-experience/279317/&quot;&gt;Ineffekt - AR experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black Gold Amsterdam, 17:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;538-dj-hotel-showcase-hardwell&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/538-dj-hotel-showcase-hardwell/279318/&quot;&gt;538 DJ Hotel showcase: Hardwell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Social Hub Amsterdam City, 20:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alle&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/alle/279319/&quot;&gt;ALLE$&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sexyland World, 21:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saturday-21st&quot;&gt;Saturday 21st&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;11-1-club-couture-with-sven-marquardt&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/11-1-club-couture-with-sven-marquardt/279320/&quot;&gt;11 +1: Club Couture with Sven Marquardt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fosbury &amp;amp; Sons, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-ecstatic-morning-rave&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/free-ecstatic-morning-rave/279321/&quot;&gt;Free Ecstatic Morning Rave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vondelkerk, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-deep-club-at-the-bassment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/the-deep-club-at-the-bas-sment/279322/&quot;&gt;The Deep club at the Bas[s]ment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Bas[s]ment, 19:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cinematique-label-showcase&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/cinematique-label-showcase/279323/&quot;&gt;Cinematique Label Showcase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JD Williams Whisky Bar, 21:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kollektiv-turmstrasse-pres-unity-of-opposites&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/kollektiv-turmstrasse-pres-unity-of-opposites/279324/&quot;&gt;Kollektiv Turmstrasse pres. Unity of Opposites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noordwaards, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;het-weekend&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/het-weekend/279325/&quot;&gt;Het Weekend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;De School, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sunday-22nd&quot;&gt;Sunday 22nd&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ade-hangover---free-entrance&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/ade-hangover-free-entrance/279326/&quot;&gt;ADE Hangover - Free entrance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NDSM, 12:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intercell-x-i-hate-models-invites&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/intercell-x-i-hate-models-invites/279327/&quot;&gt;Intercell x I Hate Models Invites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warehouse Elementenstraat, 23:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The schedule is subject to change. Please check the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/&quot;&gt;ADE website&lt;/a&gt; for the latest updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="event" /><category term="event" /><summary type="html">Thursday 19th Pieter de Graaf | Live at Planetarium Artis Artis Planetarium, 20:30 To Dance is to be Free Stadsarchief Amsterdam, 10:00 Live From Earth Lofi, 22:00 Awakenings ADE 2023: Adam Beyer Presents Drumcode Gashouder, 22:00 KNTXT Turbo Club Theater Amsterdam, 23:00 Friday 20th Ineffekt - AR experience Black Gold Amsterdam, 17:00 538 DJ Hotel showcase: Hardwell The Social Hub Amsterdam City, 20:00 ALLE$ Sexyland World, 21:30 Saturday 21st 11 +1: Club Couture with Sven Marquardt Fosbury &amp;amp; Sons, 10:00 Free Ecstatic Morning Rave Vondelkerk, 10:00 The Deep club at the Bas[s]ment The Bas[s]ment, 19:00 Cinematique Label Showcase JD Williams Whisky Bar, 21:00 Kollektiv Turmstrasse pres. Unity of Opposites Noordwaards, 23:00 Het Weekend De School, 23:00 Sunday 22nd ADE Hangover - Free entrance NDSM, 12:00 Intercell x I Hate Models Invites Warehouse Elementenstraat, 23:30 Note: The schedule is subject to change. Please check the official ADE website for the latest updates.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">12 Lessons I Learnt In the Past 12 Months</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="12 Lessons I Learnt In the Past 12 Months" /><published>2023-10-01T15:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T15:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023.html">&lt;p&gt;I celebrated my birthday past weekend and wanted to use this moment to reflect on how the year has been. Here is a list of twelve lessons the year taught me. Admittedly, I am not the best student so I have to keep relearning them as I go, therfore writing them down. Couple of them should be useful for you as well! If a particrular one resonates, I would be happy to hear about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-you-dont-have-to-own-a-home&quot;&gt;1. You don’t have to own a home.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would feel inferior to my peers who bought their own homes, and when asked, try to fathom a plan for doing so, going to happen soon, thanks for asking.
Most of us were led to believe that owning a home is a no-brainer that anyone who is serious about their personal finances must aspire to, and ideally achieve as soon as possible. I certainly thought so until very recently and struggled a lot with the fact that as an expat that moves countries about every three years, I am shooting myself in the foot as this makes me virtually unable to own a property anywhere. My opinion changed recently, and I came to think that NOT owning a home may be a smarter financial decision for lot of people, including me, given the current prices and the career mobility this lends me. I will write a whole post on this so stay tuned. For now, I am not thinking of buying a home and I am at peace with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/housingmarket.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-dont-spend-energy-on-someone-who-does-not-give-it-back&quot;&gt;2. Don’t spend energy on someone who does not give it back.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an obvious one but took me way too long to learn. Identify the people in your life who reciprocate when you spend time and energy and go on a positive spiral with them. Distance yourself from the rest and don’t look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-good-things-come-to-those-who-dont-wait-but-many-good-things-take-a-long-time&quot;&gt;3. Good things come to those who don’t wait (but many good things take a long time).&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are doubting whether you should do something, you are probably better of just doing it and learning from the outcome. I found out that acting on the first impulse is an effective strategy for someone who tends to overanalyze like me, because often I would just end up regretting not doing it.
That said, some of the really good things require sustained effort and making progress towards them is an absolute cornerstone for my happiness. The way I try to make sure I get to eat the cake and keep it to is to reserve regular time slots for sustained distraction free work.
If still in doubts, it is useful to think of your life in stages of exploring and exploiting. In the exploring stage, you would say yes to most things. In the exploiting stage, you would say yes only to very few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-results-compound&quot;&gt;4. Results compound.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know interest compounds and mostly tend to act on this knowledge. And I would also agree with anyone who claims that the same must apply to effort. Yet, until recently I would hope for anything I do to feel somehow special, noteworthy, or pleasurable. If I would not achieve results within the tiniest time, I would feel like I must have done something wrong. Only this year I came to fully apprehend that the fact that something feels boring may be a sign I am doing the right thing. This came with the experience that I can spend every day of a week doing things that feel amazing, but still end up feeling empty at the end if it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-the-more-you-can-work-from-home-the-better&quot;&gt;5. The more you can work from home the better.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/wfh_dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies that require you to show up four days per week to the office? Seriously? I run experiments in the lab and for the time being there is not an alternative to showing up in person, but for many other things I am at least as efficient working from home. For some things, such as conceptualization and reading, I am much more efficient if I avoid the office, which is always full of distractions.
Earlier in my career I would equate the time in the office with the amount of work I am doing. Lately I see them as mostly detached and prefer to go to work in person only if I really must be there. As a byproduct, I am more rigorous about scheduling meetings in times that work for my energy levels, and more consistent with when and how often I work out and get to work on my side projects (such as writing this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-you-can-eat-perfectly-well-in-just-6-to-8-hour-window-every-day&quot;&gt;6. You can eat perfectly well in just 6 to 8-hour window every day.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would grow up thinking I need to eat every 2-3 hours, 5-6 times a day. I don’t want to make the argument that there is no rationale for this, but I am convinced most of the conditioning is driven by the desire of different food companies to market as many different products as possible to you. Lately I have been limiting my food intake to about 8-hour window without any apparent drop in energy or fitness levels. On the contrary, I notice that it makes me more conscious about what I eat, and that translates to me feeling better throughout the day. It also leaves me with large chunks of unbroken time before and after my eating window, which I found out to be the most productive and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-cycling-beats-squats-for-quads&quot;&gt;7. Cycling beats squats for quads.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anytime. I started spinning early this year and my knees keep thanking me for it. Chances are yours would be thankful too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-to-really-improve-you-must-give-yourself-permission-to-experiment-and-fail&quot;&gt;8. To really improve, you must give yourself permission to experiment (and fail).&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/swing-dance.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this one is also kind of obvious on the face of it, but I doubt most would really be living by it. I came to appreciate it as I started taking bachata dancing classes this summer. While I was making good progress, I could only use moves that I learnt and practiced in the class. Quickly, I would fall into a pattern of always repeating the same sequence of moves that I knew ’worked’.
As I looked for ways to improve beyond this status quo, I watched people on the dance floor and realized that what makes some of them stand out is that they dance with their unique style and seem like having fun doing so. It did not take long to realize I have to do more than just keep doing what I learn in classes to become a better dancer. 
To become better, and eventually maybe great, at something, you have to dare to try things that you have not done before. You have to become playful and see where it takes you. You have to give yourself permission to be terrible (or at least arguably bad) first, only then you can become better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: One of my fav essays of all times deals with this topic: &lt;a href=&quot;https://autotranslucence.com/2018/03/30/becoming-a-magician/&quot;&gt;Becoming a Magician&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-stay-till-the-end-of-the-party&quot;&gt;9. Stay till the end of the party.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/afterparty.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy a night out, but I am also introverted so most of the time the energy is just too high to make more than a superficial connection while a party goes on. Not to even mention that when I am going out clubbing or dancing, there is usually very little room for a conversation other than shouting at each other about what you are drinking.
Staying until the end of a party is a straightforward opportunity to have a relaxed conversation. As a bonus, it removes the annoying guesswork about what time to leave, and frees me from feeling like I have to socialize extensively during it, which in turns allows me to focus more on myself end enjoying the event,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-to-feel-rich-decide-what-you-want-to-spend-lavishly-on-and-save-on-the-rest&quot;&gt;10. To feel rich, decide what you want to spend lavishly on, and save on the rest.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an important one for me and I am certainly still learning it. I come from a quite modest upbringing and would grow up thinking that the right financial decision is the one that leads to spending lesser amount of money, ideally none if possible. That certainly made me resourceful and was quite good for my personal finances, but also left me missing out on lot of opportunities and spending time instead of money. I started to try to look at money as a tool, and figuring out how to use it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is quite difficult to get right, because spending as little as possible is a straightforward decision to make, and the opposite end spectrum, which is allowing yourself to spend money on everything you desire, is not feasible unless you are financially extremely well of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared frustration with this with a friend, and she pointed out to me the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/money-dials/&quot;&gt;money dials&lt;/a&gt;, which are “the things that you are willing to spend extravagantly on by cutting back mercilessly on the things you don’t care about.” You probably can’t live in modern spacious apartment in city center, travel out of your country once a month, have a membership for the best gym in town, all that while donating 10% of your income. But you most likely can do one of them, maybe two if you are lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common money dials are: Convenience, Travel, Health&amp;amp;Fitness, Experiences, Freedom, Relationships, Generosity, Luxury, Social status and Self-improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-you-can-maintain-only-a-handful-of-close-connections&quot;&gt;11. You can maintain only a handful of close connections.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we grow into adulthood, lives tend to fill up with work, ambitions and obligations. The time left for making friends is quite scarce and its something most of us notice. But what fewer of us appreciate is that it also means fewer time to upkeep the close connections we already have. And if we don’t consciously carve out time to refuel these connections evey once so often, they will slowly dry out.
The key here really is to decide to spend time on reaching out to old friends, and specially if you are geographically separated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-prioritize-recovery&quot;&gt;12. Prioritize recovery.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise is important, but if you don’t want to jeopardize your results and energy levels, put recovery at the top of your priority list.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">I celebrated my birthday past weekend and wanted to use this moment to reflect on how the year has been. Here is a list of twelve lessons the year taught me. Admittedly, I am not the best student so I have to keep relearning them as I go, therfore writing them down. Couple of them should be useful for you as well! If a particrular one resonates, I would be happy to hear about it! 1. You don’t have to own a home. I would feel inferior to my peers who bought their own homes, and when asked, try to fathom a plan for doing so, going to happen soon, thanks for asking. Most of us were led to believe that owning a home is a no-brainer that anyone who is serious about their personal finances must aspire to, and ideally achieve as soon as possible. I certainly thought so until very recently and struggled a lot with the fact that as an expat that moves countries about every three years, I am shooting myself in the foot as this makes me virtually unable to own a property anywhere. My opinion changed recently, and I came to think that NOT owning a home may be a smarter financial decision for lot of people, including me, given the current prices and the career mobility this lends me. I will write a whole post on this so stay tuned. For now, I am not thinking of buying a home and I am at peace with it. 2. Don’t spend energy on someone who does not give it back. This is an obvious one but took me way too long to learn. Identify the people in your life who reciprocate when you spend time and energy and go on a positive spiral with them. Distance yourself from the rest and don’t look back. 3. Good things come to those who don’t wait (but many good things take a long time). If you are doubting whether you should do something, you are probably better of just doing it and learning from the outcome. I found out that acting on the first impulse is an effective strategy for someone who tends to overanalyze like me, because often I would just end up regretting not doing it. That said, some of the really good things require sustained effort and making progress towards them is an absolute cornerstone for my happiness. The way I try to make sure I get to eat the cake and keep it to is to reserve regular time slots for sustained distraction free work. If still in doubts, it is useful to think of your life in stages of exploring and exploiting. In the exploring stage, you would say yes to most things. In the exploiting stage, you would say yes only to very few things. 4. Results compound. I know interest compounds and mostly tend to act on this knowledge. And I would also agree with anyone who claims that the same must apply to effort. Yet, until recently I would hope for anything I do to feel somehow special, noteworthy, or pleasurable. If I would not achieve results within the tiniest time, I would feel like I must have done something wrong. Only this year I came to fully apprehend that the fact that something feels boring may be a sign I am doing the right thing. This came with the experience that I can spend every day of a week doing things that feel amazing, but still end up feeling empty at the end if it. 5. The more you can work from home the better. Companies that require you to show up four days per week to the office? Seriously? I run experiments in the lab and for the time being there is not an alternative to showing up in person, but for many other things I am at least as efficient working from home. For some things, such as conceptualization and reading, I am much more efficient if I avoid the office, which is always full of distractions. Earlier in my career I would equate the time in the office with the amount of work I am doing. Lately I see them as mostly detached and prefer to go to work in person only if I really must be there. As a byproduct, I am more rigorous about scheduling meetings in times that work for my energy levels, and more consistent with when and how often I work out and get to work on my side projects (such as writing this). 6. You can eat perfectly well in just 6 to 8-hour window every day. I would grow up thinking I need to eat every 2-3 hours, 5-6 times a day. I don’t want to make the argument that there is no rationale for this, but I am convinced most of the conditioning is driven by the desire of different food companies to market as many different products as possible to you. Lately I have been limiting my food intake to about 8-hour window without any apparent drop in energy or fitness levels. On the contrary, I notice that it makes me more conscious about what I eat, and that translates to me feeling better throughout the day. It also leaves me with large chunks of unbroken time before and after my eating window, which I found out to be the most productive and enjoyable. 7. Cycling beats squats for quads. Anytime. I started spinning early this year and my knees keep thanking me for it. Chances are yours would be thankful too. 8. To really improve, you must give yourself permission to experiment (and fail). So this one is also kind of obvious on the face of it, but I doubt most would really be living by it. I came to appreciate it as I started taking bachata dancing classes this summer. While I was making good progress, I could only use moves that I learnt and practiced in the class. Quickly, I would fall into a pattern of always repeating the same sequence of moves that I knew ’worked’. As I looked for ways to improve beyond this status quo, I watched people on the dance floor and realized that what makes some of them stand out is that they dance with their unique style and seem like having fun doing so. It did not take long to realize I have to do more than just keep doing what I learn in classes to become a better dancer. To become better, and eventually maybe great, at something, you have to dare to try things that you have not done before. You have to become playful and see where it takes you. You have to give yourself permission to be terrible (or at least arguably bad) first, only then you can become better. PS: One of my fav essays of all times deals with this topic: Becoming a Magician. 9. Stay till the end of the party. I enjoy a night out, but I am also introverted so most of the time the energy is just too high to make more than a superficial connection while a party goes on. Not to even mention that when I am going out clubbing or dancing, there is usually very little room for a conversation other than shouting at each other about what you are drinking. Staying until the end of a party is a straightforward opportunity to have a relaxed conversation. As a bonus, it removes the annoying guesswork about what time to leave, and frees me from feeling like I have to socialize extensively during it, which in turns allows me to focus more on myself end enjoying the event, 10. To feel rich, decide what you want to spend lavishly on, and save on the rest. This was an important one for me and I am certainly still learning it. I come from a quite modest upbringing and would grow up thinking that the right financial decision is the one that leads to spending lesser amount of money, ideally none if possible. That certainly made me resourceful and was quite good for my personal finances, but also left me missing out on lot of opportunities and spending time instead of money. I started to try to look at money as a tool, and figuring out how to use it better. This one is quite difficult to get right, because spending as little as possible is a straightforward decision to make, and the opposite end spectrum, which is allowing yourself to spend money on everything you desire, is not feasible unless you are financially extremely well of. I shared frustration with this with a friend, and she pointed out to me the concept of money dials, which are “the things that you are willing to spend extravagantly on by cutting back mercilessly on the things you don’t care about.” You probably can’t live in modern spacious apartment in city center, travel out of your country once a month, have a membership for the best gym in town, all that while donating 10% of your income. But you most likely can do one of them, maybe two if you are lucky. The most common money dials are: Convenience, Travel, Health&amp;amp;Fitness, Experiences, Freedom, Relationships, Generosity, Luxury, Social status and Self-improvement. 11. You can maintain only a handful of close connections. As we grow into adulthood, lives tend to fill up with work, ambitions and obligations. The time left for making friends is quite scarce and its something most of us notice. But what fewer of us appreciate is that it also means fewer time to upkeep the close connections we already have. And if we don’t consciously carve out time to refuel these connections evey once so often, they will slowly dry out. The key here really is to decide to spend time on reaching out to old friends, and specially if you are geographically separated. 12. Prioritize recovery. Exercise is important, but if you don’t want to jeopardize your results and energy levels, put recovery at the top of your priority list.</summary></entry></feed>