<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-09T14:27:29+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Martin Holub Blog</title><subtitle>Personal Blog</subtitle><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><entry><title type="html">Solutions for the Dutch Tech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/06/09/SolutionsForTheDutchTech.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solutions for the Dutch Tech" /><published>2024-06-09T09:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T09:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/06/09/SolutionsForTheDutchTech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/06/09/SolutionsForTheDutchTech.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/delaunay_formescirculaires.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt; Circular Forms. Sun, Moon, by Robert Delaunay, 1912-1931. Delaunay’s paintings are materializations of optimism. This attitude probably did not come to him naturally, as he labored on this painting for nearly 20 (!) years. Photo from &lt;a href=&quot; https://g.co/arts/4jLv1wYg4MtvSC2s7&quot;&gt;Google&apos;s Arts &amp;amp; Culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post we looked at the main challenges highlighted in the State of Dutch Tech report issued by teachleap.nl earlier this year. If you have not read the earlier post yet, you can check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/business/startup/2024/05/09/StateOfDutchTech_Problems.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you don’t do that, I applaud you for living by the adage “Rather than trying to change something old, build something new”. You are in the right place and should &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this blog. However, here we will be talking about fiscal policy (brace for it). This is a slow-moving field and the knowledge of how things are now is therefore important. As a brief summary, the challenges were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Startups glow slowly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Access to growth capital is limited.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding the right talent is hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the challenges we also highlighted strengths of the ecosystem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of strong research institutions, with good patent output.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors’ seeing the Netherlands as a strong hub for biotech and green tech ventures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geographically decentralized ecosystem of incubation and accelerator programs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The BeNeLux being the HQ of number of EU-level institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/homepage&quot;&gt;European Medicines Agency&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eif.org/index.htm&quot;&gt;European Investment Fund&lt;/a&gt; in Luxembourg, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will look at how to address these challenges, while acknowledging the existing strengths. But before we do that, let’s give credit where credit is due. Lot of information in this post was put together by teachleap.nl in the State of Dutch Tech report (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;download here&lt;/a&gt;). Chapeau to them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot;/&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;The state of the Dutch tech may not be great, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/&quot;&gt;techleap.nl&lt;/a&gt; is!&lt;/div&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution-1-aint-nothing-big-money-cant-solve&quot;&gt;Solution 1: Ain’t nothing (big) money can’t solve&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dutch startups generally grow slowly. This is a product of a multitude of factors, both cultural and structural. Both are difficult to fix. Here, let’s focus on the more tangible of the two: the structural factor. One obvious way to encourage more growth is by providing adequate levels of funding. The challenge is that driving growth at this stage does require a substantial amount of capital, and the system must find ways to support this by making this capital structurally available. If this sounds like coordination and some amount of politics, then you are listening right (fiscal politics here we come).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/economic-stimulus-comic.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Resources for prosperity are available, but it is a matter of allocating them correctly.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The techleap’s report highlights that larger investment rounds into Dutch startups are likely to include foreign capital (75% at 10-100 M level, and 85% at 100M and beyond). This goes to underscore the importance of international cooperation that could mobilize more growth capital. While I second the need for cooperation on international level, I think that this is potentially too-slow, and in any case a barbwire of conflicts of interests (once EU makes capital available to NL, it cannot refuse to do so for other member states). This is probably also while the most recent example of this, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.invest-nl.nl/actueel/Invest-NL-en-Europees-Investeringsfonds-lanceren-Dutch-Future-Fund-II&quot;&gt;Dutch Future Fund II&lt;/a&gt; by EIF (European Investment Fund) is relatively modest, with 200 M EUR committed from the EIF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems that this leads to secondary effects and mobilization of more capital, it is unclear how important this effect is. First, I did not find any counterfactual evaluations. Wouldn’t this “secondary”-capital have been invested anyway? Second, this capital is made available progressively, and split among multiple VC funds. Consequently, it seems ill-suited to deal with the problem that needs addressing the most, i.e. making large sums structurally available for growth investments. As per usual, it probably started off with everybody being well-intentioned, but politics got the better side of it, reducing the effectiveness of the final implementation.
Let’s now look at what I believe to be at least equally promising ways to get access to this type of capital. A one the techleap’s report only briefly mentions, by recalling that demissionary minister of Economic Affairs and Climate Policy (EZK) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/documenten/kamerstukken/2023/05/26/startups-en-scale-ups-als-motor-voor-transities-en-groei&quot;&gt;highlighted a gap in the existing system&lt;/a&gt;. Namely, that institutional investors (such as pension funds) seem to be interested in investing in startups and scaleups but lack precedence and framework to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-small-detour-on-a-familiar-subject&quot;&gt;A small detour on a familiar subject&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiscal policies, pension funds, and international collaborations may sound all too remote and abstract, so let’s now look at everyone’s favorite subject to complain about, the Dutch housing market crisis. Many expats coming to the Netherlands (me included) will be quite surprised by how “right winged” the situation is when it comes to housing. Historically, this seems to have been treated as people’s problem. There was little regulation on rents, and not enough care given to whether enough, and adequate, housing is being built. The consequences of that are apparent now, with the crisis of the housing market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/woningnood_rtl.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot;/&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;… the rest of the text reads “door vluchteling”. I clipped this out as it is not important in this context. What matters is that the current housing crisis is a result of governmental mismanagement. News item from&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rtl.nl/nieuws/nederland/artikel/5425673/vn-rapporteur-woningnood-slecht-beleid-vluchteling/&quot;&gt;RTL News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A corollary of this issue is that housing is seen as the primary means of investment in the country. I am by no means expert on this, and have much to learn. I do think though, that it is safe to say that real estate investment (at least for one’s primary residence) is the most tax-favorable vehicle there is in the Netherlands. I have a lot of issues with it, but for now let’s keep this to the most pressing one in the context of this article. And that is: it locks up huge amounts of capital. There are 8+ millions of housing units, with an average (and growing) price of 370k EUR [&lt;a href=&quot;https://allecijfers.nl/nederland/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;]. These have aggregate value of 8e6*0.37e6=3e12 EUR. That’s 3 trillion, or 3’000 billion EUR.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If even just 10% of this value was redirected into growth investment, it would allow for 3’000 investment rounds @ 100M EUR. According to the State of the Dutch tech report there are ~1’250 startups that received 0.1-10M worth of funding in the whole county. Releasing 300bn EUR from housing could lift this whole ecosystem to series C+ level &lt;em&gt;2.5 times instantly&lt;/em&gt;. This calculation, of course, is extremely simplistic. The purpose of it here is to illustrate the magnitude of the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems a good idea to look at whether other countries have figured this out at least a bit better. I previously lived in Switzerland, which has a more regulated housing market. There is lower proportion of house ownership (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/en/home/statistics/construction-housing/dwellings/housing-conditions/tenants-owners.html&quot;&gt;35%&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&quot;https://allecijfers.nl/nederland/&quot;&gt;57%&lt;/a&gt; in the Netherlands), with larger role of (non-profit!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lebendige-traditionen.ch/tradition/en/home/traditions/housing-cooperatives.html&quot;&gt;housing corporations&lt;/a&gt;. Even in tenant-occupied housing, the rents are regulated much more tightly than in NL (as written before, I find the Dutch setup much too liberal). Rents are, for example, linked to inflation (so are they in NL, but read on), and can increase only by sub percent values above it. When the inflation is negative (i.e. there is deflation), the rents in fact have to drop! The Swiss government does a much better job at recognizing housing as a right, and something that should not be seen as (significant) investment or source of income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hitting-at-least-two-birds-with-one-stone-incentivize-vc-able-pension-schemes&quot;&gt;Hitting (at least) two birds with one stone: Incentivize VC-able pension schemes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swiss, being relatively less able to save and invest by means of real estate ownership, have perks that make up for it. They benefit from low taxation on stock ownership, with corresponding low capital gains tax on their sale. This is really nice, as it allows one to invest the best way an individual investor can these days – passively. With little work you can reap returns that are above the housing market returns AND, save yourself a lot of hassles with house ownership, AND remain more geographically mobile. This all sounds great, but it does have the disadvantage of you mostly shoving your capital into hands of frequently US-based institutional investors, while the capital could have arguably been used locally to drive competitiveness and growth of your own geographical region. By the way, this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pionline.com/article/20170425/INTERACTIVE/170429926/80-of-equity-market-cap-held-by-institutions&quot;&gt;what pension funds mostly do&lt;/a&gt;, and why it is so important to diversify their investments to something with better secondary effects for local economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swiss have understood this, and implemented an institutionalized system of private pensions plans (PPP) that creates more flexibility in how individual pensions are invested. Dubbed the third pillar, it has two parts. 3a – restricted PPP, and 3b – unrestricted PPP. Both are potential contributors to funding local scale ups, but it is the 3b that is the best cut out for it. These investments lie somewhat between an investment into the stock market and traditional pension funds. They allow individuals to select a risk profile and to some degree allow for channeling pension-directed savings into riskier vehicles such as startup and growth funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make a simple back of the envelope calculation to get a sense for whether this can matter. Assume that half of the Swiss population in their working age (say 25-65) invest in the 3b third pillar, and that they invest 3’000 CHF a year.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Next, assume that they do so for a full 40 years, and that the yearly return on this investment is 4%. For each individual this leads to \(FV = P [((1 + r)^t – 1) / r]\), where P=3’000 r=4%, n=40. Running the numbers, this is 285k CHF.  As there is roughly 4 million people between 25 and 65 in Switzerland (and we assumed half of them invest to pillar 3b), this gives in total 0.285e6 * 2e6 = 6e11, or 600bn CHF. If only 10% of it is allowed to be directed into growth investment in companies, it still would be enough for 600 series C+ with 100 M each. Assuming the Dutch would invest the same way, the amount would be double in the Netherlands (its population being double that of Switzerland).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this has been another simplistic calculation, I hope it illustrates the opportunity that lies in the capital that is directed towards pension savings. This case is especially pronounced for the Netherlands, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/721152/total-pension-assets-of-selected-countries-worldwide/&quot;&gt;a top five/six country worldwide&lt;/a&gt; in terms of total assets in pension funds. Leveraging the existing capital in pension funds, as well offering new ways to save for pension, all offer opportunities to channel substantial capital into driving economic growth. It also has the advantage of incentivizing people to save for retirement. If the Dutch government does not explore this way to structurally increase access to growth capital, it is leaving a large opportunity on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/pensionassetsAUM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Per-country share of assets in the top 300 pension funds globally. Source &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thinkingaheadinstitute.org/content/uploads/2022/09/PI-300-2023-3.pdf&quot;&gt;Thinking Ahead Institute&lt;/a&gt;. The Dutch pension fund capital amounts to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/607698/assets-under-management-by-pension-funds-in-the-netherlands/&quot;&gt;over 3’000 bn EUR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money invested in retirement savings is the most substantial source of capital in this context. There is one more investment vehicle that has been successfully explored (in the UK,) and is currently being implemented in other countries in Europe (Germany, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sifted.eu/articles/france-uk-for-boosting-business-angels&quot;&gt;France&lt;/a&gt;). Most recently, France is implementing policies that allow individuals to gain a tax break of 30%, or even 50%, on pre-seed and seed investments into startups (up to 100 and 150k EUR]. Similar schemes exist for a number of years in the UK, where they contributed &lt;a href=&quot;https://eisa.org.uk/about-eis/facts-and-figures/&quot;&gt;2.1bn GBP of early stage funding in 2022/3&lt;/a&gt;. While this is not evaluated at the counterfactual (i.e. how many of these investors would have invested anyway), it seems to provide a reasonable amount of incentive and a policy other countries should seek to adopt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the pension-redirection system we described above, where diversified investments are made from a large pool of money with long time horizons, here the risk profile is much higher, and shouldered entirely by the individual. This is why it will remain reserved to modest total capital, and interesting only for high net-worth individuals (or gamblers). If implemented in the NL, it would be a move in the right direction, as it would encourage high-worth individuals to explore investments with more positive secondary effects for the economy, rather than passively investing into stocks, or locking up capital in housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution-2-promote-academic-entrepreneurship&quot;&gt;Solution 2: Promote academic entrepreneurship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands has a strong ecosystem of universities and research centers with good academic output. It is in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/scientific-publications-per-million?tab=table&quot;&gt;the top 10&lt;/a&gt; countries worldwide by academic output, and does particularly well in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/nature-index/country-outputs/generate/health-sciences/global&quot;&gt;health sciences&lt;/a&gt;. So far so good. However, the translation of the innovation into value is sluggish. Seven out of every eight patents filed in the Netherlands never turn into a company. The rate is as bad as 1 in 10 for universities and it improves somewhat to 1 in 6 for university medical centers (UMCs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in the country, I see that there is a good number of institutions and organizations that target prospective entrepreneurs and early stage founders. From incubators, to accelerators, to funders. I think there are two reasons why this support network does not translate to (better) results. First, many of the entrepreneurship-encouraging activities are fairly new, and their impact will take more time to materialize. Second, entrepreneurship is not seen as an attractive career choice by the vast majority of academics. This hampers deeptech venture creation. Such a situation is in contrast to the US, where many students join a top-notch scientific lab already with the intention to start a company, and are supported by their PI in doing so.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe is generally pretty heavy on work-life balance, and the Dutch are certainly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecdbetterlifeindex.org/countries/netherlands/&quot;&gt;one of the champions in that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Starting a company has an image of hustling on something that is probably not going to work. Try to motivate yourself to do that while your friends are landing permanent contracts in-between their frequent trips to Intratuin and IKEA to equip their newly bought homes. Handling peer pressure in this context is challenging but for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/business/startup/2024/01/22/PmarcaAdviceForFounders.html&quot;&gt;the most determined founders&lt;/a&gt;.
The culture needs to change. Founding a company should be seen as something fulfilling both professionally and personally, with a potential for large upside on the impact and income level. Perpetuating the image of a lonely founder without work-life balance is not useful. The goal is not to paint a rosy picture, simply a more realistic one. For every founder who hustles with no work balance there will be others who pull it off while keeping functional relationships and high life satisfaction through most of it. It is important to create a more representative and living image of what founding means in any given field, time, and locale. A simple and powerful way to do it is to create more opportunities for interaction between early stage founders and academic trainees. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eth-entrepreneurship_entrepreneurial-backpack-series-activity-7166805463534125057-1LTL?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&quot;&gt;This is happening&lt;/a&gt; in some areas, but needs to become more common. While doing so, it will be important to keep diversity and inclusion in mind, as well as account for survivorship bias by inviting a diverse pool of founders, including those whose ventures failed.  I recently joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nucleate.org/&quot;&gt;Nucleate&lt;/a&gt; where we are helping to create this type of interface. It was one of my main motivations to start a branch in the Netherlands, as I personally felt the lack of these interactions. Another reason was to change the academic experience of PhDs and postdocs, which I turn to next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 4+ years I was at the university as a PhD, the only business I heard of was the one in “business as usual” and “minding your own business”. On the other hand, I was asked to do coursework for 45 Graduate School (GS) credits, amounting to 540 hours of workload. I don’t assume any ill intent, but that does hinder me from calling the courses by their right name: a waste of time. Save a few small exceptions, that’s what the majority of them were.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The only “upside” of such a system was that it allowed me to get some of my work-related activities recognized towards these credits (such as organizing a panel at the iGEM Jamboree in 2023), and that I could scrape some credits by doing MOOCs from other universities. Calling this an upside is an overstatement. I would have done these activities anyway. The net value of the whole GS is in red numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is, there is a framework that has PhDs put in 500+ hours (that is 3 months of full time work!) towards something. Now we just need to make this something useful. There is some good precedence available elsewhere (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/learn/biotechnology/massachusetts-institute-of-technology-the-science-and-business-of-biotechnology&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://med.nyu.edu/research/technology-opportunities-ventures/sites/default/files/biomedical-entrepreneurship-program-fall-course.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and I am personally interested in updating and adapting it to the local ecosystem. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nucleate.org/&quot;&gt;Nucleate&lt;/a&gt; is an organization that has capacity to do this, and we are looking for partners within universities and institutional partners to make this happen. Please get in touch if you would like to learn more or contribute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution-3-grow-attract-and-retain-talent&quot;&gt;Solution 3: Grow, attract and retain talent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands struggles with talent shortages, and it is not doing well in addressing them from neither the &lt;a href=&quot;https://advalvas.vu.nl/en/science-education/netherlands-spends-less-stem-other-countries/&quot;&gt;local&lt;/a&gt;, nor the &lt;a href=&quot;https://expatax.nl/the-30-ruling-in-2024-what-has-changed/&quot;&gt;global&lt;/a&gt; talent pools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/jobvacancyrates.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Job vacancy rate in the EU. The higher the rate the longer it takes to fill a job vacancy. Source &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.euronews.com/business/2023/09/26/working-in-europe-which-countries-have-the-most-job-vacancies-and-what-roles-are-in-high-d&quot;&gt;Euronews &amp;amp; Eurostat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the local level, the country must promote STEM fields as attractive areas of study. The Netherlands sees &lt;strong&gt;only 19% of its university students graduate from STEM&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s only about half that of Germany. It also &lt;a href=&quot;https://advalvas.vu.nl/en/science-education/netherlands-spends-less-stem-other-countries/&quot;&gt;underfunds&lt;/a&gt; this area relative to other countries. Next to universities, the country also must promote these subjects at schools of applied sciences, and foster the creation of more technical apprenticeships. Local and national governments should work with businesses to leverage this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn to the global level now. The Netherlands does courtesy to its name (low-lands) and culture (&lt;em&gt;doe normaal&lt;/em&gt;) – it does not stand as a location for global talent. It’s by all means a fair country, with a good balance across a number of aspects. It is well connected between its individual cities and internationally. It affords a good tradeoff between family life and career opportunities. It is easy to settle in, as everyone speaks good English, and there are a lot of expats already. It has good educational institutions and is very safe. Even the weather is not that bad, and summers are generally quite nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this description is that similar things could be said about a number of other countries, leaving the Netherlands somewhere in the middle of the pack of “good” countries where to live (say in the top 20 or so, depending what factors matter to you). If the Dutch are serious about doing better than this, they must acknowledge that the competition for talent is fierce, and take adequate action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle for talent starts early, and so it is important to enter it early. This is why English taught bachelors are likely net-positive, and something the Dutch would have done better by not doing anything about, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dutchnews.nl/2024/04/universities-to-offer-more-dutch-taught-degree-courses-from-2025/&quot;&gt;instead of scaling them down&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The battle for talent is probably the most rampant at the master level. I have long been a critic of charging some students (much) more for their degree. If you come from non-EU/EFTA, you will pay about 25k EUR per year for your masters in the Netherlands, 10-fold more than students from the EU/EFTA countries! Talent seems to be valued only as long as it has very deep pockets or a pedigree. This obscenity continues on PhD level, where PhDs arriving on foreign scholarships will not see the level of their reimbursement matched up to a university (and country)-wide standard. EPFL, as an example, does &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epfl.ch/education/phd/doctoral-studies-structure/doctoral-students-salary/&quot;&gt;implement this matching&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, many countries either historically had (US, UK, …), or recently decided to create (Germany, Switzerland), opportunities for pursuing doctorate without masters (so called direct doctorate), which continue to be lacking in the Netherlands. Whatever the intent of this messaging is, the results are quite clear. If dealt with the opportunity to do so, students across bachelor, master and PhD level, are likely to pursue their studies and careers elsewhere. Consequently, the country is missing out on some of the best talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle for talent continues after graduation. To attract skilled employees, it is important to offer adequate compensation through salary, and especially in the early-stage, through equity. Aside from directly increasing starter salaries (which is in my opinion badly needed), the Netherlands has historically implemented a 30% ruling that shielded expats from some degree of taxation, effectively bumping up their salaries. Initially available for eight years, it has been cut to five, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://expatax.nl/the-30-ruling-in-2024-what-has-changed/&quot;&gt;most recently scaled down substantially more&lt;/a&gt;. The scaling back also includes removal of partial foreign tax liability, which massively reduces the attractiveness of the country for expats. I, for one, would have probably not come to the Netherlands to do a PhD if these changes happened a couple of years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 30% ruling, which the government would have done the best not to touch (too late!), improving employee compensation through equity is in need of reform. The way stocks are distributed to company employees, and taxed, in the Netherlands, is unattractive. Number of other countries implement ESOPs (employee stock ownership programs) do a much better job in this aspect. The Netherlands must adopt similar policies, otherwise it will continue to be unattractive for those who seek to use their talent where it has the largest leverage - in early stage companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this should have been post about solutions, and I admit to have been complaining a lot (that’s what &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@k.kozmana/ice-cold-slightly-crazy-98ee875f078a&quot;&gt;growing up in communist country does to you&lt;/a&gt;! To end on the correct note, the solutions we discussed in this section are: 1) channel more funding into STEM degrees and increase the number of students therein, 2) increase the number of technical apprenticeships 3) retain English-taught bachelors or even scale them up, 4) abandon high-tranche tuition fees for non-EU/EFTA nationals, 5) match-up PhD scholarships up to a standard level, 6) create options for direct doctorate, 7) increase salaries, 8) retain 30% ruling, and 9) reform ESOP taxation to make equity ownership in early stage companies more attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/tangledsolutions.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Listing the solutions was the easy part, now to implement them …&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen that there are a number of solutions available to address shortcomings in the current tech entrepreneurial landscape in the Netherlands. Few are as simple as not changing the good things, or re-implementing measures that were scaled back. Many, however, do require large scale coordinated political action. I am optimistic about the Dutch political leadership eventually figuring out what the right thing to do is, and doing it. I am however NOT optimistic about how long this is going to take. Consequently, I expect the Netherlands to struggle keeping its position as an attractive destination for expat talent among competition. Netherlands-based individuals should be focusing on the things they can control. Working with universities, researchers and recent graduates to create dialogues around entrepreneurship, building cross-border networks to facilitate exchange of talent and capital, and creating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.octant.bio/blog-posts/open-sourcing-the-octant-apprenticeship&quot;&gt;in-house apprenticeship programs&lt;/a&gt; to foster talent internally are all examples of actions with potential for large positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has been a mouthful! Thanks for reading everyone! If you spot any inaccuracies or would like to engage in a discussion, please write below in the comments. If you would like to read more content like this as it becomes available, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This sounds like a lot, and by most measures it is. But if you want to be reminded that the European economies are small, this is also exactly the current (June ’24) market cap of &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; Microsoft, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; Apple, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; NVIDIA [&lt;a href=&quot;https://companiesmarketcap.com/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;] (Whether this valuation is justified, or better, why it is not, is a subject for a different discussion). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I could not find good data on this, so if somebody has a source that could check this against reality, that would be helpful. As here we are using the example as an inspiration, its correctness is not that important. The point rather being that something like that is possible. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As an example Carolyn Bertozzi mentions this in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bios.community/podcast/47-taking-agency-jejry&quot;&gt;this BIOS podcast interview&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It seems that the Dutch have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2018/02/the-dutch-have-the-best-work-life-balance-here-s-why/&quot;&gt;fallen back in this metric somewhat&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, they continue to be one of the leaders. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have taken courses as arcane as “Voice Training”, courses that assumed project management can be solved by sharing the knowledge on what Trello is (which everyone in the course knew already), or courses that promised to support attendees during career choice but were not than what any generic career blog post summarizes under 5 minutes. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When the president of TU/e was asked about what he thinks will the consequences if limiting English-taught programs be, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/_cBpi4RbmRw?t=248&quot;&gt;this is what he had to say&lt;/a&gt;: “It will be awful for the country, it will be awful for this high-tech region, it will be awful for Europe […] so it will be a disaster. The Dutch cannot afford not having international students.” I guess someone did not get the memo. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="startup" /><category term="business" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html">Circular Forms. Sun, Moon, by Robert Delaunay, 1912-1931. Delaunay’s paintings are materializations of optimism. This attitude probably did not come to him naturally, as he labored on this painting for nearly 20 (!) years. Photo from Google&apos;s Arts &amp;amp; Culture. Introduction In the previous post we looked at the main challenges highlighted in the State of Dutch Tech report issued by teachleap.nl earlier this year. If you have not read the earlier post yet, you can check it out here. If you don’t do that, I applaud you for living by the adage “Rather than trying to change something old, build something new”. You are in the right place and should subscribe to this blog. However, here we will be talking about fiscal policy (brace for it). This is a slow-moving field and the knowledge of how things are now is therefore important. As a brief summary, the challenges were: Startups glow slowly. Access to growth capital is limited. Finding the right talent is hard. Aside from the challenges we also highlighted strengths of the ecosystem: Number of strong research institutions, with good patent output. Investors’ seeing the Netherlands as a strong hub for biotech and green tech ventures. Geographically decentralized ecosystem of incubation and accelerator programs. The BeNeLux being the HQ of number of EU-level institutions (European Medicines Agency in Amsterdam, European Investment Fund in Luxembourg, …) In this post, we will look at how to address these challenges, while acknowledging the existing strengths. But before we do that, let’s give credit where credit is due. Lot of information in this post was put together by teachleap.nl in the State of Dutch Tech report (download here). Chapeau to them! Solution 1: Ain’t nothing (big) money can’t solve Dutch startups generally grow slowly. This is a product of a multitude of factors, both cultural and structural. Both are difficult to fix. Here, let’s focus on the more tangible of the two: the structural factor. One obvious way to encourage more growth is by providing adequate levels of funding. The challenge is that driving growth at this stage does require a substantial amount of capital, and the system must find ways to support this by making this capital structurally available. If this sounds like coordination and some amount of politics, then you are listening right (fiscal politics here we come). Resources for prosperity are available, but it is a matter of allocating them correctly. The techleap’s report highlights that larger investment rounds into Dutch startups are likely to include foreign capital (75% at 10-100 M level, and 85% at 100M and beyond). This goes to underscore the importance of international cooperation that could mobilize more growth capital. While I second the need for cooperation on international level, I think that this is potentially too-slow, and in any case a barbwire of conflicts of interests (once EU makes capital available to NL, it cannot refuse to do so for other member states). This is probably also while the most recent example of this, the Dutch Future Fund II by EIF (European Investment Fund) is relatively modest, with 200 M EUR committed from the EIF. While it seems that this leads to secondary effects and mobilization of more capital, it is unclear how important this effect is. First, I did not find any counterfactual evaluations. Wouldn’t this “secondary”-capital have been invested anyway? Second, this capital is made available progressively, and split among multiple VC funds. Consequently, it seems ill-suited to deal with the problem that needs addressing the most, i.e. making large sums structurally available for growth investments. As per usual, it probably started off with everybody being well-intentioned, but politics got the better side of it, reducing the effectiveness of the final implementation. Let’s now look at what I believe to be at least equally promising ways to get access to this type of capital. A one the techleap’s report only briefly mentions, by recalling that demissionary minister of Economic Affairs and Climate Policy (EZK) highlighted a gap in the existing system. Namely, that institutional investors (such as pension funds) seem to be interested in investing in startups and scaleups but lack precedence and framework to do so. A small detour on a familiar subject Fiscal policies, pension funds, and international collaborations may sound all too remote and abstract, so let’s now look at everyone’s favorite subject to complain about, the Dutch housing market crisis. Many expats coming to the Netherlands (me included) will be quite surprised by how “right winged” the situation is when it comes to housing. Historically, this seems to have been treated as people’s problem. There was little regulation on rents, and not enough care given to whether enough, and adequate, housing is being built. The consequences of that are apparent now, with the crisis of the housing market. A corollary of this issue is that housing is seen as the primary means of investment in the country. I am by no means expert on this, and have much to learn. I do think though, that it is safe to say that real estate investment (at least for one’s primary residence) is the most tax-favorable vehicle there is in the Netherlands. I have a lot of issues with it, but for now let’s keep this to the most pressing one in the context of this article. And that is: it locks up huge amounts of capital. There are 8+ millions of housing units, with an average (and growing) price of 370k EUR [source]. These have aggregate value of 8e6*0.37e6=3e12 EUR. That’s 3 trillion, or 3’000 billion EUR.1 If even just 10% of this value was redirected into growth investment, it would allow for 3’000 investment rounds @ 100M EUR. According to the State of the Dutch tech report there are ~1’250 startups that received 0.1-10M worth of funding in the whole county. Releasing 300bn EUR from housing could lift this whole ecosystem to series C+ level 2.5 times instantly. This calculation, of course, is extremely simplistic. The purpose of it here is to illustrate the magnitude of the opportunity. It seems a good idea to look at whether other countries have figured this out at least a bit better. I previously lived in Switzerland, which has a more regulated housing market. There is lower proportion of house ownership (35% compared to 57% in the Netherlands), with larger role of (non-profit!) housing corporations. Even in tenant-occupied housing, the rents are regulated much more tightly than in NL (as written before, I find the Dutch setup much too liberal). Rents are, for example, linked to inflation (so are they in NL, but read on), and can increase only by sub percent values above it. When the inflation is negative (i.e. there is deflation), the rents in fact have to drop! The Swiss government does a much better job at recognizing housing as a right, and something that should not be seen as (significant) investment or source of income. Hitting (at least) two birds with one stone: Incentivize VC-able pension schemes The Swiss, being relatively less able to save and invest by means of real estate ownership, have perks that make up for it. They benefit from low taxation on stock ownership, with corresponding low capital gains tax on their sale. This is really nice, as it allows one to invest the best way an individual investor can these days – passively. With little work you can reap returns that are above the housing market returns AND, save yourself a lot of hassles with house ownership, AND remain more geographically mobile. This all sounds great, but it does have the disadvantage of you mostly shoving your capital into hands of frequently US-based institutional investors, while the capital could have arguably been used locally to drive competitiveness and growth of your own geographical region. By the way, this is what pension funds mostly do, and why it is so important to diversify their investments to something with better secondary effects for local economies. The Swiss have understood this, and implemented an institutionalized system of private pensions plans (PPP) that creates more flexibility in how individual pensions are invested. Dubbed the third pillar, it has two parts. 3a – restricted PPP, and 3b – unrestricted PPP. Both are potential contributors to funding local scale ups, but it is the 3b that is the best cut out for it. These investments lie somewhat between an investment into the stock market and traditional pension funds. They allow individuals to select a risk profile and to some degree allow for channeling pension-directed savings into riskier vehicles such as startup and growth funding. Let’s make a simple back of the envelope calculation to get a sense for whether this can matter. Assume that half of the Swiss population in their working age (say 25-65) invest in the 3b third pillar, and that they invest 3’000 CHF a year.2 Next, assume that they do so for a full 40 years, and that the yearly return on this investment is 4%. For each individual this leads to \(FV = P [((1 + r)^t – 1) / r]\), where P=3’000 r=4%, n=40. Running the numbers, this is 285k CHF. As there is roughly 4 million people between 25 and 65 in Switzerland (and we assumed half of them invest to pillar 3b), this gives in total 0.285e6 * 2e6 = 6e11, or 600bn CHF. If only 10% of it is allowed to be directed into growth investment in companies, it still would be enough for 600 series C+ with 100 M each. Assuming the Dutch would invest the same way, the amount would be double in the Netherlands (its population being double that of Switzerland). While this has been another simplistic calculation, I hope it illustrates the opportunity that lies in the capital that is directed towards pension savings. This case is especially pronounced for the Netherlands, which is a top five/six country worldwide in terms of total assets in pension funds. Leveraging the existing capital in pension funds, as well offering new ways to save for pension, all offer opportunities to channel substantial capital into driving economic growth. It also has the advantage of incentivizing people to save for retirement. If the Dutch government does not explore this way to structurally increase access to growth capital, it is leaving a large opportunity on the table. Per-country share of assets in the top 300 pension funds globally. Source Thinking Ahead Institute. The Dutch pension fund capital amounts to over 3’000 bn EUR. The money invested in retirement savings is the most substantial source of capital in this context. There is one more investment vehicle that has been successfully explored (in the UK,) and is currently being implemented in other countries in Europe (Germany, and France). Most recently, France is implementing policies that allow individuals to gain a tax break of 30%, or even 50%, on pre-seed and seed investments into startups (up to 100 and 150k EUR]. Similar schemes exist for a number of years in the UK, where they contributed 2.1bn GBP of early stage funding in 2022/3. While this is not evaluated at the counterfactual (i.e. how many of these investors would have invested anyway), it seems to provide a reasonable amount of incentive and a policy other countries should seek to adopt. Compared to the pension-redirection system we described above, where diversified investments are made from a large pool of money with long time horizons, here the risk profile is much higher, and shouldered entirely by the individual. This is why it will remain reserved to modest total capital, and interesting only for high net-worth individuals (or gamblers). If implemented in the NL, it would be a move in the right direction, as it would encourage high-worth individuals to explore investments with more positive secondary effects for the economy, rather than passively investing into stocks, or locking up capital in housing. Solution 2: Promote academic entrepreneurship The Netherlands has a strong ecosystem of universities and research centers with good academic output. It is in the top 10 countries worldwide by academic output, and does particularly well in health sciences. So far so good. However, the translation of the innovation into value is sluggish. Seven out of every eight patents filed in the Netherlands never turn into a company. The rate is as bad as 1 in 10 for universities and it improves somewhat to 1 in 6 for university medical centers (UMCs). Living in the country, I see that there is a good number of institutions and organizations that target prospective entrepreneurs and early stage founders. From incubators, to accelerators, to funders. I think there are two reasons why this support network does not translate to (better) results. First, many of the entrepreneurship-encouraging activities are fairly new, and their impact will take more time to materialize. Second, entrepreneurship is not seen as an attractive career choice by the vast majority of academics. This hampers deeptech venture creation. Such a situation is in contrast to the US, where many students join a top-notch scientific lab already with the intention to start a company, and are supported by their PI in doing so.3 Europe is generally pretty heavy on work-life balance, and the Dutch are certainly one of the champions in that.4 Starting a company has an image of hustling on something that is probably not going to work. Try to motivate yourself to do that while your friends are landing permanent contracts in-between their frequent trips to Intratuin and IKEA to equip their newly bought homes. Handling peer pressure in this context is challenging but for the most determined founders. The culture needs to change. Founding a company should be seen as something fulfilling both professionally and personally, with a potential for large upside on the impact and income level. Perpetuating the image of a lonely founder without work-life balance is not useful. The goal is not to paint a rosy picture, simply a more realistic one. For every founder who hustles with no work balance there will be others who pull it off while keeping functional relationships and high life satisfaction through most of it. It is important to create a more representative and living image of what founding means in any given field, time, and locale. A simple and powerful way to do it is to create more opportunities for interaction between early stage founders and academic trainees. This is happening in some areas, but needs to become more common. While doing so, it will be important to keep diversity and inclusion in mind, as well as account for survivorship bias by inviting a diverse pool of founders, including those whose ventures failed. I recently joined Nucleate where we are helping to create this type of interface. It was one of my main motivations to start a branch in the Netherlands, as I personally felt the lack of these interactions. Another reason was to change the academic experience of PhDs and postdocs, which I turn to next. Throughout the 4+ years I was at the university as a PhD, the only business I heard of was the one in “business as usual” and “minding your own business”. On the other hand, I was asked to do coursework for 45 Graduate School (GS) credits, amounting to 540 hours of workload. I don’t assume any ill intent, but that does hinder me from calling the courses by their right name: a waste of time. Save a few small exceptions, that’s what the majority of them were.5 The only “upside” of such a system was that it allowed me to get some of my work-related activities recognized towards these credits (such as organizing a panel at the iGEM Jamboree in 2023), and that I could scrape some credits by doing MOOCs from other universities. Calling this an upside is an overstatement. I would have done these activities anyway. The net value of the whole GS is in red numbers. The good news is, there is a framework that has PhDs put in 500+ hours (that is 3 months of full time work!) towards something. Now we just need to make this something useful. There is some good precedence available elsewhere (e.g. here, and here, and I am personally interested in updating and adapting it to the local ecosystem. Nucleate is an organization that has capacity to do this, and we are looking for partners within universities and institutional partners to make this happen. Please get in touch if you would like to learn more or contribute! Solution 3: Grow, attract and retain talent The Netherlands struggles with talent shortages, and it is not doing well in addressing them from neither the local, nor the global talent pools. Job vacancy rate in the EU. The higher the rate the longer it takes to fill a job vacancy. Source Euronews &amp;amp; Eurostat. On the local level, the country must promote STEM fields as attractive areas of study. The Netherlands sees only 19% of its university students graduate from STEM. That’s only about half that of Germany. It also underfunds this area relative to other countries. Next to universities, the country also must promote these subjects at schools of applied sciences, and foster the creation of more technical apprenticeships. Local and national governments should work with businesses to leverage this opportunity. Let’s turn to the global level now. The Netherlands does courtesy to its name (low-lands) and culture (doe normaal) – it does not stand as a location for global talent. It’s by all means a fair country, with a good balance across a number of aspects. It is well connected between its individual cities and internationally. It affords a good tradeoff between family life and career opportunities. It is easy to settle in, as everyone speaks good English, and there are a lot of expats already. It has good educational institutions and is very safe. Even the weather is not that bad, and summers are generally quite nice. The problem with this description is that similar things could be said about a number of other countries, leaving the Netherlands somewhere in the middle of the pack of “good” countries where to live (say in the top 20 or so, depending what factors matter to you). If the Dutch are serious about doing better than this, they must acknowledge that the competition for talent is fierce, and take adequate action. The battle for talent starts early, and so it is important to enter it early. This is why English taught bachelors are likely net-positive, and something the Dutch would have done better by not doing anything about, instead of scaling them down).6 The battle for talent is probably the most rampant at the master level. I have long been a critic of charging some students (much) more for their degree. If you come from non-EU/EFTA, you will pay about 25k EUR per year for your masters in the Netherlands, 10-fold more than students from the EU/EFTA countries! Talent seems to be valued only as long as it has very deep pockets or a pedigree. This obscenity continues on PhD level, where PhDs arriving on foreign scholarships will not see the level of their reimbursement matched up to a university (and country)-wide standard. EPFL, as an example, does implement this matching. Finally, many countries either historically had (US, UK, …), or recently decided to create (Germany, Switzerland), opportunities for pursuing doctorate without masters (so called direct doctorate), which continue to be lacking in the Netherlands. Whatever the intent of this messaging is, the results are quite clear. If dealt with the opportunity to do so, students across bachelor, master and PhD level, are likely to pursue their studies and careers elsewhere. Consequently, the country is missing out on some of the best talent. The battle for talent continues after graduation. To attract skilled employees, it is important to offer adequate compensation through salary, and especially in the early-stage, through equity. Aside from directly increasing starter salaries (which is in my opinion badly needed), the Netherlands has historically implemented a 30% ruling that shielded expats from some degree of taxation, effectively bumping up their salaries. Initially available for eight years, it has been cut to five, and most recently scaled down substantially more. The scaling back also includes removal of partial foreign tax liability, which massively reduces the attractiveness of the country for expats. I, for one, would have probably not come to the Netherlands to do a PhD if these changes happened a couple of years earlier. Unlike the 30% ruling, which the government would have done the best not to touch (too late!), improving employee compensation through equity is in need of reform. The way stocks are distributed to company employees, and taxed, in the Netherlands, is unattractive. Number of other countries implement ESOPs (employee stock ownership programs) do a much better job in this aspect. The Netherlands must adopt similar policies, otherwise it will continue to be unattractive for those who seek to use their talent where it has the largest leverage - in early stage companies. Ok, this should have been post about solutions, and I admit to have been complaining a lot (that’s what growing up in communist country does to you! To end on the correct note, the solutions we discussed in this section are: 1) channel more funding into STEM degrees and increase the number of students therein, 2) increase the number of technical apprenticeships 3) retain English-taught bachelors or even scale them up, 4) abandon high-tranche tuition fees for non-EU/EFTA nationals, 5) match-up PhD scholarships up to a standard level, 6) create options for direct doctorate, 7) increase salaries, 8) retain 30% ruling, and 9) reform ESOP taxation to make equity ownership in early stage companies more attractive. Listing the solutions was the easy part, now to implement them … Conclusions We have seen that there are a number of solutions available to address shortcomings in the current tech entrepreneurial landscape in the Netherlands. Few are as simple as not changing the good things, or re-implementing measures that were scaled back. Many, however, do require large scale coordinated political action. I am optimistic about the Dutch political leadership eventually figuring out what the right thing to do is, and doing it. I am however NOT optimistic about how long this is going to take. Consequently, I expect the Netherlands to struggle keeping its position as an attractive destination for expat talent among competition. Netherlands-based individuals should be focusing on the things they can control. Working with universities, researchers and recent graduates to create dialogues around entrepreneurship, building cross-border networks to facilitate exchange of talent and capital, and creating in-house apprenticeship programs to foster talent internally are all examples of actions with potential for large positive impact. This post has been a mouthful! Thanks for reading everyone! If you spot any inaccuracies or would like to engage in a discussion, please write below in the comments. If you would like to read more content like this as it becomes available, subscribe! Footnotes This sounds like a lot, and by most measures it is. But if you want to be reminded that the European economies are small, this is also exactly the current (June ’24) market cap of either Microsoft, or Apple, or NVIDIA [source] (Whether this valuation is justified, or better, why it is not, is a subject for a different discussion). &amp;#8617; I could not find good data on this, so if somebody has a source that could check this against reality, that would be helpful. As here we are using the example as an inspiration, its correctness is not that important. The point rather being that something like that is possible. &amp;#8617; As an example Carolyn Bertozzi mentions this in this BIOS podcast interview. &amp;#8617; It seems that the Dutch have fallen back in this metric somewhat. Nevertheless, they continue to be one of the leaders. &amp;#8617; I have taken courses as arcane as “Voice Training”, courses that assumed project management can be solved by sharing the knowledge on what Trello is (which everyone in the course knew already), or courses that promised to support attendees during career choice but were not than what any generic career blog post summarizes under 5 minutes. &amp;#8617; When the president of TU/e was asked about what he thinks will the consequences if limiting English-taught programs be, this is what he had to say: “It will be awful for the country, it will be awful for this high-tech region, it will be awful for Europe […] so it will be a disaster. The Dutch cannot afford not having international students.” I guess someone did not get the memo. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State of Dutch Tech 2024, Three Problems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/05/09/StateOfDutchTech_Problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State of Dutch Tech 2024, Three Problems" /><published>2024-05-09T09:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T09:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/05/09/StateOfDutchTech_Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/05/09/StateOfDutchTech_Problems.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/theblacksquare.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;The Black Square, by Kazimir Malevich, 1915. One cannot help but wonder, did Kazimir Malevich have a premonition about the state of Dutch tech in 2024? Original photo from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/art/features/kasimir-malevichs-black-square-what-does-it-say-to-you-9608316.html&quot;&gt;independent.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you thinking about starting a company in the Netherlands? Or are you already a founder with the dream to upend industries? Or maybe you are dreaming of a job in a high-growth company while biking along the endless canals on the weekends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all these cases, and probably a number of more, you should check the State of Dutch Tech report by teachleap.nl (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;download here&lt;/a&gt;). In this post, I will highlight three major problems it points to. In an upcoming post I will look at three solutions it suggests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first: I want to give chapeau to &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/who-we-are/&quot;&gt;techleap.nl&lt;/a&gt; (no affiliation). They are doing great work to continuously evaluate and accelerate the tech-ecosystem in the Netherlands. The report is detailed, yet readable. Well done! Now, for the summary, because, as you may have guessed, acceleration is badly needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;The state of the Dutch tech may not be great, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/&quot;&gt;techleap.nl&lt;/a&gt; is!&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-1-dutch-startups-fail-to-grow&quot;&gt;Problem 1: Dutch startups fail to grow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startups are great, but they are not very profitable. It is only as companies grow and expand their market share and customer base that they generate attractive returns for their founders and investors. It is also these companies that create substantial employment and give their employees a chance to acquire skills and experience needed to found another high-growth company in the future. So yes, sure startups are great, but you know what is even better? Startups that grow. Unfortunately, the Dutch startups don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some sobering stats from the report: &lt;strong&gt;more than 70% of all Dutch startups will never exit the seed stage&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;only 19% of them will ever receive more than 10M EUR in funding&lt;/strong&gt;. The Dutch are already &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/patent-applications-per-million&quot;&gt;not a champion in generating patents&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spinout.fyi/blog/data-launch-v2&quot;&gt;turning patents into research-based startups&lt;/a&gt; (spin-offs). Even if formed, these spin-offs don’t grow either. Nearly &lt;strong&gt;50% of Dutch spin-off companies that survive 15 years have less than 10 employees&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;only 18% have above 50&lt;/strong&gt;. After these 15 years, 60% of spin-offs were still privately held. Dreaming of impacting the world with application of your research? Then you may have to wake up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech_noofemployees.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Spin-off companies by age and company status. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;State of Dutch Tech 2024 &lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, chances of you making it big as a founder in the Netherlands are relatively slim. As it turns out, even if you are one of the lucky ones who gets to grow, it will be &lt;strong&gt;slow&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Median time to reach series A in the Netherlands (4 years) is double that of the US&lt;/strong&gt;. The time to reach series C is 8 years, which is 3 and 2 years longer than in the US and EU respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech_fundingrounds.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Median time to reach a given funding round in the Netherlands, US and the EU. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;State of Dutch Tech 2024 &lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-2-big-money-is-hard-to-get-in-nl&quot;&gt;Problem 2: Big money is hard to get (in NL)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not any news that European VC funding is lagging the US one. The EU’s per capita VC investment is one eighth of that in the US and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pitchbook.com/news/articles/singapore-vc-funding-per-capita-2023&quot;&gt;the Netherlands is not an outlier&lt;/a&gt;. It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://stateofeuropeantech.com/reading-tracks/soet-in-5-minutes#C0-0-new-startup-formation&quot;&gt;getting better&lt;/a&gt;, but only very slowly. Additionally, 2023 was not an easy year, with VC funding experiencing a drop of 36% and 38% in the EU and US respectively. Many VCs report LPs delaying or reducing investments. Consequently, the Dutch and European VCs are cautious. That’s exactly the opposite of what Europe needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech_reluctantvc.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;VCs are experiencing difficulties sourcing capital from LPs. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;State of Dutch Tech 2024 &lt;/a&gt; report.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has several consequences. First, scarcity of capital makes it yet harder for companies to scale. Second, it creates more opportunities for foreign, non-European (e.g. US or Chinese), capital to enter the picture. While this is not immediately a bad thing, it does mean that part of the value created by successful companies will be captured outside of Europe, only exacerbating the problem in the future. In fact, between 2019 and 2023, 85% of all growth equity in the Netherlands included a foreign investment already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While big money is never easy to get, it is harder in the Netherlands than some other places in Europe and certainly much harder than it is in the US. &lt;strong&gt;In the Netherlands, only 1.3% companies raised 100+M EUR investments&lt;/strong&gt;, whereas this is 2.8% in Germany, 2.1% in Switzerland and 1.9% in the UK. Maybe the lack of big money in the Netherlands should not be a surprise given that the phrase “going Dutch” has been around since the 17th century?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-3-the-netherlands-is-not-a-top-destination-for-global-talent&quot;&gt;Problem 3: The Netherlands is not a top destination for global talent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has high salaries, the UK has a global metropolis and the comfort of an English-speaking country, Ireland has low taxes, Switzerland has high salaries, low taxes, and the Alps. The Netherlands has … weed? rain? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pwc.nl/en/insights-and-publications/tax-news/income/box-3-compensation-until-2024--new-system-from-2025.html&quot;&gt;tax policies that violate the European Convention on Human Rights&lt;/a&gt;? While I hate to admit it, the Netherlands is simply not a top destination for foreign talent. Don’t get me wrong, it is a fair country, but in comparison to its competition it does not stand out (something the Dutch would probably be happy about).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, the natural conditions are difficult to change. But that only means that the Dutch must work harder on other fronts to become attractive for recruits from abroad. Unfortunately, they have been doing &lt;a href=&quot;https://expatax.nl/the-30-ruling-in-2024-what-has-changed/&quot;&gt;exactly the opposite&lt;/a&gt;. Some would argue that lack of foreign talent can be substituted with the local one. While this is true, it is so only to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/mckinsey-digital/our-insights/reinventing-the-european-economy-from-within&quot;&gt;a rather small extent&lt;/a&gt;. It would also still require stable and high-quality governance. What part about the illegal taxation or inability to stimulate growth funding made you think it would be the case? Indeed, it is not. The Netherlands sees &lt;strong&gt;only 19% of its students graduate from STEM fields&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s only about half (!) that of Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/artdegreecomics.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Maybe an art degree was not a great idea in the end? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.memedroid.com/memes/detail/1520310&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to motivate both local and foreign talent to go work for an early-stage company is to promise a chance of becoming (somewhat) wealthy through equity. Unsurprisingly, the Netherlands does not make this easy either. It implements unfavourable taxation schemes and regulations, lacking behind countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2023/10/24/france-wants-to-boost-angel-investment-by-copying-uks-investment-schemes/&quot;&gt;France&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sifted.eu/articles/germany-startup-esop-rule-changes&quot;&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt;, UK and the US in the attractiveness of stock ownership plans (ranking only 14th out of 24 evaluated countries).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all this together, it is not a surprise that the Netherlands is one of the three countries in Europe where it takes the longest to fill a job vacancy. Coming full circle, this problem becomes yet more pronounced at senior positions that require substantial expertise and adequate compensation, further slowing down company growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/stateofDutchTech_talentchallenges.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Talent and culture challenges among Dutch startups. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techleap.nl/report/state-of-dutch-tech-report-2024/&quot;&gt;State of Dutch Tech 2024 &lt;/a&gt; report. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-the-bad-and-the-ugly-is-there-any-good&quot;&gt;After the bad and the ugly, is there any good?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I painted a dark picture. It is a realistic one and I want you to hang it in your living room. Preferably only symbolically, unless you actually have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiart.org/en/kazimir-malevich/black-square-1915&quot;&gt;The Black Square&lt;/a&gt;. In that case, please consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gofundme.com/f/empower-dutch-leadership-support-our-journey-to-the-2024-al&quot;&gt;buying me a coffee or two&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this tirade, and the reminder that you too missed the chance of becoming fairy-tale wealthy by painting single-coloured squares, we deserve at least some encouragement. Luckily, there are a handful of good aspects that the report brings forward that we can hang onto. In particular if you are in the biotech industry. One, &lt;strong&gt;29%&lt;/strong&gt; of VC funding in the Netherlands goes to health-related startups, &lt;strong&gt;13%&lt;/strong&gt; goes to food. Both are about &lt;strong&gt;double the European average&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;11%&lt;/strong&gt; goes to semiconductor industry, and that’s &lt;strong&gt;5-fold the European average&lt;/strong&gt;. Two, the Dutch health, pharma and biotech sectors collected over 1B EUR funding between 2019 and 2023. Three, &lt;strong&gt;only 1 out of 8 patents filed by Dutch research institutions are turned into startups&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that there is a large untapped potential for research-based venture creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of Dutch tech is, overall, quite gloomy. But given that you are reading this, you are probably an uncorrectable optimist or even a &lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.eth.limo/general/2023/11/27/techno_optimism.html&quot;&gt;techno-optimist&lt;/a&gt;. You may also be a prospective founder. As such, where others see a problem, you see a challenge. And where there is a challenge, there may be a solution. Good for you, because this is exactly the angle we will take in the next article, where we discuss three main recommendations for improvement that the report brings forward. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="startup" /><category term="business" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html">The Black Square, by Kazimir Malevich, 1915. One cannot help but wonder, did Kazimir Malevich have a premonition about the state of Dutch tech in 2024? Original photo from independent.co.uk. Introduction Are you thinking about starting a company in the Netherlands? Or are you already a founder with the dream to upend industries? Or maybe you are dreaming of a job in a high-growth company while biking along the endless canals on the weekends? In all these cases, and probably a number of more, you should check the State of Dutch Tech report by teachleap.nl (download here). In this post, I will highlight three major problems it points to. In an upcoming post I will look at three solutions it suggests. First things first: I want to give chapeau to techleap.nl (no affiliation). They are doing great work to continuously evaluate and accelerate the tech-ecosystem in the Netherlands. The report is detailed, yet readable. Well done! Now, for the summary, because, as you may have guessed, acceleration is badly needed. The state of the Dutch tech may not be great, but techleap.nl is! Problem 1: Dutch startups fail to grow Startups are great, but they are not very profitable. It is only as companies grow and expand their market share and customer base that they generate attractive returns for their founders and investors. It is also these companies that create substantial employment and give their employees a chance to acquire skills and experience needed to found another high-growth company in the future. So yes, sure startups are great, but you know what is even better? Startups that grow. Unfortunately, the Dutch startups don’t. Here are some sobering stats from the report: more than 70% of all Dutch startups will never exit the seed stage, and only 19% of them will ever receive more than 10M EUR in funding. The Dutch are already not a champion in generating patents or turning patents into research-based startups (spin-offs). Even if formed, these spin-offs don’t grow either. Nearly 50% of Dutch spin-off companies that survive 15 years have less than 10 employees and only 18% have above 50. After these 15 years, 60% of spin-offs were still privately held. Dreaming of impacting the world with application of your research? Then you may have to wake up. Spin-off companies by age and company status. Taken from State of Dutch Tech 2024 report. Unfortunately, chances of you making it big as a founder in the Netherlands are relatively slim. As it turns out, even if you are one of the lucky ones who gets to grow, it will be slow. Median time to reach series A in the Netherlands (4 years) is double that of the US. The time to reach series C is 8 years, which is 3 and 2 years longer than in the US and EU respectively. Median time to reach a given funding round in the Netherlands, US and the EU. Taken from State of Dutch Tech 2024 report. Problem 2: Big money is hard to get (in NL) It is not any news that European VC funding is lagging the US one. The EU’s per capita VC investment is one eighth of that in the US and the Netherlands is not an outlier. It is getting better, but only very slowly. Additionally, 2023 was not an easy year, with VC funding experiencing a drop of 36% and 38% in the EU and US respectively. Many VCs report LPs delaying or reducing investments. Consequently, the Dutch and European VCs are cautious. That’s exactly the opposite of what Europe needs. VCs are experiencing difficulties sourcing capital from LPs. Taken from State of Dutch Tech 2024 report. This has several consequences. First, scarcity of capital makes it yet harder for companies to scale. Second, it creates more opportunities for foreign, non-European (e.g. US or Chinese), capital to enter the picture. While this is not immediately a bad thing, it does mean that part of the value created by successful companies will be captured outside of Europe, only exacerbating the problem in the future. In fact, between 2019 and 2023, 85% of all growth equity in the Netherlands included a foreign investment already. While big money is never easy to get, it is harder in the Netherlands than some other places in Europe and certainly much harder than it is in the US. In the Netherlands, only 1.3% companies raised 100+M EUR investments, whereas this is 2.8% in Germany, 2.1% in Switzerland and 1.9% in the UK. Maybe the lack of big money in the Netherlands should not be a surprise given that the phrase “going Dutch” has been around since the 17th century? Problem 3: The Netherlands is not a top destination for global talent The US has high salaries, the UK has a global metropolis and the comfort of an English-speaking country, Ireland has low taxes, Switzerland has high salaries, low taxes, and the Alps. The Netherlands has … weed? rain? tax policies that violate the European Convention on Human Rights? While I hate to admit it, the Netherlands is simply not a top destination for foreign talent. Don’t get me wrong, it is a fair country, but in comparison to its competition it does not stand out (something the Dutch would probably be happy about). Arguably, the natural conditions are difficult to change. But that only means that the Dutch must work harder on other fronts to become attractive for recruits from abroad. Unfortunately, they have been doing exactly the opposite. Some would argue that lack of foreign talent can be substituted with the local one. While this is true, it is so only to a rather small extent. It would also still require stable and high-quality governance. What part about the illegal taxation or inability to stimulate growth funding made you think it would be the case? Indeed, it is not. The Netherlands sees only 19% of its students graduate from STEM fields. That’s only about half (!) that of Germany. Maybe an art degree was not a great idea in the end? Source. Another way to motivate both local and foreign talent to go work for an early-stage company is to promise a chance of becoming (somewhat) wealthy through equity. Unsurprisingly, the Netherlands does not make this easy either. It implements unfavourable taxation schemes and regulations, lacking behind countries like France, Germany, UK and the US in the attractiveness of stock ownership plans (ranking only 14th out of 24 evaluated countries). Taking all this together, it is not a surprise that the Netherlands is one of the three countries in Europe where it takes the longest to fill a job vacancy. Coming full circle, this problem becomes yet more pronounced at senior positions that require substantial expertise and adequate compensation, further slowing down company growth. Talent and culture challenges among Dutch startups. Taken from State of Dutch Tech 2024 report. After the bad and the ugly, is there any good? So far, I painted a dark picture. It is a realistic one and I want you to hang it in your living room. Preferably only symbolically, unless you actually have The Black Square. In that case, please consider buying me a coffee or two. After this tirade, and the reminder that you too missed the chance of becoming fairy-tale wealthy by painting single-coloured squares, we deserve at least some encouragement. Luckily, there are a handful of good aspects that the report brings forward that we can hang onto. In particular if you are in the biotech industry. One, 29% of VC funding in the Netherlands goes to health-related startups, 13% goes to food. Both are about double the European average. 11% goes to semiconductor industry, and that’s 5-fold the European average. Two, the Dutch health, pharma and biotech sectors collected over 1B EUR funding between 2019 and 2023. Three, only 1 out of 8 patents filed by Dutch research institutions are turned into startups. This means that there is a large untapped potential for research-based venture creation. Conclusion The state of Dutch tech is, overall, quite gloomy. But given that you are reading this, you are probably an uncorrectable optimist or even a techno-optimist. You may also be a prospective founder. As such, where others see a problem, you see a challenge. And where there is a challenge, there may be a solution. Good for you, because this is exactly the angle we will take in the next article, where we discuss three main recommendations for improvement that the report brings forward. Stay tuned!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Flattery to Fit - Why You May Have to Rewrite Your Cover Letter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/career/2024/04/14/FlatteryToFit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Flattery to Fit - Why You May Have to Rewrite Your Cover Letter" /><published>2024-04-14T17:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-14T17:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/career/2024/04/14/FlatteryToFit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/career/2024/04/14/FlatteryToFit.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/coverletter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
A photo by &lt;a href=&quot; https://www.pexels.com/photo/job-applicant-passing-her-documents-3760072/&quot;&gt;Andrea Piacquadio&lt;/a&gt; on Pexels.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a cover letter is like cooking for a date who is also a reviewer on the Michelin-star guide. You want to impress them but have no idea how – should you stand out with something creative? Probably not, they have seen it all. Or would they appreciate something authentic? Maybe, but it could turn out to be too simple. Unfortunately, cover letters are the necessary evil of job hunting. There are times in almost everyone’s career when we get to write one (and, sadly, usually many more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you write a good cover letter? There are plenty of resources suggesting what to write about, but that apparently does not stop many people from writing abysmally bad ones. My suggestion here is that you can improve your cover letter by choosing things &lt;strong&gt;that you are &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; going to avoid&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-avoid-in-a-cover-letter&quot;&gt;What to avoid in a cover letter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what should you avoid? &lt;strong&gt;Playing yourself down and showering the company with generic praise.&lt;/strong&gt; That seems straightforward, but is apparently hard to do for quite a number of people. Consider the following evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am doing a PhD in a fairly prestigious group that receives a lot of applications that are geographically well distributed. My PI forwards the full application pack to everyone in the group, and, as a consequence, I got the chance to read some 30+ cover letters over the past few years. Here are some excerpts that I gathered from these letters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As such a reputable lab in the ﬁeld, it would both be a resource and an honour to receive your supervision […]”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I knew your research and wanted to join your group when I was a master student many years ago. [n]ow, I am thrilled to know that a postdoc position […] is available. I choose to contact you without any hesitation. I sincerely want to pursue a professional science-related career in your laboratory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To summarise, working on such an original and innovative project in a multidisciplinary environment would be an opportunity I would wholeheartedly dedicate myself to. Spending the next few years in [your laboratory] would be an honour.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I am sincerely motivated to reach out to you, as I aspire to join your lab. I perceive your research as a pinnacle to strive for […]”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I hope I can have the chance to meet you virtually, in order to show you better my passion and love for science and my motivation to get in touch with your research.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These statements all come from different cover letters, written by both prospective postdocs and graduate students. They all tick boxes for generic compliments and tons of servility. I don’t know about you, but these statements don’t make me want to hire this person – rather they make me pity them. One would almost think that the poor applicant’s life and ability to pay rent is entirely dependent on the generosity and benevolence of the mighty PI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume these statements don’t look that bad when you write them in the context of a motivation letter. However, singled out like this, it becomes quite clear that they are not helping you get a job, unless it’s a job with an egomaniac boss.[^1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-now-know-what-to-avoid-what-are-you-going-to-write-instead&quot;&gt;You now know what to avoid. What are you going to write instead?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what should you do instead? &lt;strong&gt;One&lt;/strong&gt;, drop blank-statement compliments and replace them with specifics about projects the company or group runs. &lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;, scan your cover letter for signs of exaggerated subservience and weed them out. Then, connect one and two by highlighting how your previous achievements and the way you obtained them make you a great candidate for typical projects of this group or company. Remember, you already have a lot of value, and your cover letter is your chance to show that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="career" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">A photo by Andrea Piacquadio on Pexels. Writing a cover letter is like cooking for a date who is also a reviewer on the Michelin-star guide. You want to impress them but have no idea how – should you stand out with something creative? Probably not, they have seen it all. Or would they appreciate something authentic? Maybe, but it could turn out to be too simple. Unfortunately, cover letters are the necessary evil of job hunting. There are times in almost everyone’s career when we get to write one (and, sadly, usually many more). So how do you write a good cover letter? There are plenty of resources suggesting what to write about, but that apparently does not stop many people from writing abysmally bad ones. My suggestion here is that you can improve your cover letter by choosing things that you are absolutely going to avoid. What to avoid in a cover letter So what should you avoid? Playing yourself down and showering the company with generic praise. That seems straightforward, but is apparently hard to do for quite a number of people. Consider the following evidence. I am doing a PhD in a fairly prestigious group that receives a lot of applications that are geographically well distributed. My PI forwards the full application pack to everyone in the group, and, as a consequence, I got the chance to read some 30+ cover letters over the past few years. Here are some excerpts that I gathered from these letters: “As such a reputable lab in the ﬁeld, it would both be a resource and an honour to receive your supervision […]” “I knew your research and wanted to join your group when I was a master student many years ago. [n]ow, I am thrilled to know that a postdoc position […] is available. I choose to contact you without any hesitation. I sincerely want to pursue a professional science-related career in your laboratory.” “To summarise, working on such an original and innovative project in a multidisciplinary environment would be an opportunity I would wholeheartedly dedicate myself to. Spending the next few years in [your laboratory] would be an honour.” “I am sincerely motivated to reach out to you, as I aspire to join your lab. I perceive your research as a pinnacle to strive for […]” “I hope I can have the chance to meet you virtually, in order to show you better my passion and love for science and my motivation to get in touch with your research.” These statements all come from different cover letters, written by both prospective postdocs and graduate students. They all tick boxes for generic compliments and tons of servility. I don’t know about you, but these statements don’t make me want to hire this person – rather they make me pity them. One would almost think that the poor applicant’s life and ability to pay rent is entirely dependent on the generosity and benevolence of the mighty PI. I assume these statements don’t look that bad when you write them in the context of a motivation letter. However, singled out like this, it becomes quite clear that they are not helping you get a job, unless it’s a job with an egomaniac boss.[^1] You now know what to avoid. What are you going to write instead? So, what should you do instead? One, drop blank-statement compliments and replace them with specifics about projects the company or group runs. Two, scan your cover letter for signs of exaggerated subservience and weed them out. Then, connect one and two by highlighting how your previous achievements and the way you obtained them make you a great candidate for typical projects of this group or company. Remember, you already have a lot of value, and your cover letter is your chance to show that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Common Methods for Pre-Revenue Startup Valuation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/04/07/MethodsOfStartupValuation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Common Methods for Pre-Revenue Startup Valuation" /><published>2024-04-07T09:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-07T09:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/04/07/MethodsOfStartupValuation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/04/07/MethodsOfStartupValuation.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/startupvaluation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
A photo by &lt;a href=&quot; https://unsplash.com/@austindistel?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Austin Distel&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pre-revenue start-up valuation needn’t be a mystery!  🚀 💲 Here are the three most common start-up pre-money valuation methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-the-scorecard-aka-bill-payne-method&quot;&gt;💰 The Scorecard (aka Bill Payne) method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starts from average start-up valuation (for comparable stage, industry, size, …), and multiples it by a subjective weighted factor that considers team, timing, size of the opportunity, technology/product (e.g. IP, network effects, …), competitive environment (e.g. barriers to entry), partnerships/sales/rollout, … (and sometimes a bit more)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-example-&quot;&gt;An example 🔎:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pre-revenue startups similar to startup A are valued on average at $1.86M. We subjectively assign the following weights (must sum up to 100%) to the following factors: team (35%), timing &amp;amp; size of the opportunity (25%), technology/product (20%), competitive environment (10%), partnerships (10%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then score the startup on these metrics relative to the industry average:  team (140%), timing &amp;amp; size of the opportunity (150%), technology/product (89%), competitive environment (67%), partnerships (81%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weighting these scores and summing up, we obtain a multiplier for the pre-money valuation relative to industry average: 140%*35% + 150%*25% + 89%*20% + 67%*10% + 81%*10% = 1.191. Finally, the pre-money valuation for this startup is: 1.86*1.191 = $2.215M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weights&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weights * Score&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Team&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.35*1.40=.49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Timing &amp;amp; Opportunity&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.25*1.50=.375&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Technology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.89&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.20*.89=.178&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Competitive Environment&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.67&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.10*.67=.067&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Partnerships&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.81&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.10*.81=.081&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.191&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
An example of startup valuation using the Scorecard method.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-the-vc-method&quot;&gt;💰 The “VC” method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First determines the post-money valuation as terminal value / expected ROI. The pre-money valuation is then post-money valuation - investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-example--1&quot;&gt;An example 🔎:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startup B anticipates exit in 5 years at $60M (based on current market data and future projections). VCs anticipate an ROI of 15x (this is commonly 10-30x, sometimes up to 100x for early stage investments). The post-money valuation is then 60/15 = $4M. Given a sought investment of $1M, the pre-money valuation of this startup is $3M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-the-berkus-method&quot;&gt;💰 The Berkus method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assigns value between 0 and $500k for the following five factors: team, idea, working prototype, board/strategic relationships/partnerships, rollout/sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-example--2&quot;&gt;An example 🔎:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startup C has a very good and fast team ($400k), compelling idea ($300k), working prototype and a demo ($500k), has not established marketing/supplier relationships, but has sound board ($250k), and has not rolled out a product or receive first sale yet ($0). The pre-money valuation of this startup is 0.4 + 0.3 + 0.5 + 0.25 = $1.45M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources-&quot;&gt;Resources 📖:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.venionaire.com/startup-valuation-payne-scorecard-method/&quot;&gt;The Scorecard method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sharpsheets.io/blog/venture-capital-valuation-method/&quot;&gt;The VC method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/humble-ventures/how-investors-value-pre-revenue-startups-part-ii-6bec0307145a&quot;&gt;The Berkus method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="startup" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">A photo by Austin Distel on Unsplash. Pre-revenue start-up valuation needn’t be a mystery! 🚀 💲 Here are the three most common start-up pre-money valuation methods: 💰 The Scorecard (aka Bill Payne) method Starts from average start-up valuation (for comparable stage, industry, size, …), and multiples it by a subjective weighted factor that considers team, timing, size of the opportunity, technology/product (e.g. IP, network effects, …), competitive environment (e.g. barriers to entry), partnerships/sales/rollout, … (and sometimes a bit more) An example 🔎: Pre-revenue startups similar to startup A are valued on average at $1.86M. We subjectively assign the following weights (must sum up to 100%) to the following factors: team (35%), timing &amp;amp; size of the opportunity (25%), technology/product (20%), competitive environment (10%), partnerships (10%). We then score the startup on these metrics relative to the industry average: team (140%), timing &amp;amp; size of the opportunity (150%), technology/product (89%), competitive environment (67%), partnerships (81%). Weighting these scores and summing up, we obtain a multiplier for the pre-money valuation relative to industry average: 140%*35% + 150%*25% + 89%*20% + 67%*10% + 81%*10% = 1.191. Finally, the pre-money valuation for this startup is: 1.86*1.191 = $2.215M.   Weights Score Weights * Score Team .35 1.40 .35*1.40=.49 Timing &amp;amp; Opportunity .25 1.50 .25*1.50=.375 Technology .20 .89 .20*.89=.178 Competitive Environment .10 .67 .10*.67=.067 Partnerships .10 .81 .10*.81=.081 Total 1.0   1.191 An example of startup valuation using the Scorecard method. 💰 The “VC” method First determines the post-money valuation as terminal value / expected ROI. The pre-money valuation is then post-money valuation - investment. An example 🔎: Startup B anticipates exit in 5 years at $60M (based on current market data and future projections). VCs anticipate an ROI of 15x (this is commonly 10-30x, sometimes up to 100x for early stage investments). The post-money valuation is then 60/15 = $4M. Given a sought investment of $1M, the pre-money valuation of this startup is $3M. 💰 The Berkus method Assigns value between 0 and $500k for the following five factors: team, idea, working prototype, board/strategic relationships/partnerships, rollout/sales. An example 🔎: Startup C has a very good and fast team ($400k), compelling idea ($300k), working prototype and a demo ($500k), has not established marketing/supplier relationships, but has sound board ($250k), and has not rolled out a product or receive first sale yet ($0). The pre-money valuation of this startup is 0.4 + 0.3 + 0.5 + 0.25 = $1.45M. Resources 📖: The Scorecard method The VC method The Berkus method</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Write a To-Do List Unless You Write This List First</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/03/03/ToBeList.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Write a To-Do List Unless You Write This List First" /><published>2024-03-03T16:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-03-03T16:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/03/03/ToBeList</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/03/03/ToBeList.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-do-lists-are-great-but-not-sufficient&quot;&gt;To-do lists are great, but not sufficient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a to-do list is a practical and effective way to free mental capacity and avoid forgetting tasks that you may have to execute at work and other domains of your life. To-do lists are great. In fact, and I am very sure I would be incapable of keeping track of all the tasks I may have to do, wasn’t it for keeping a to-do list. I may not have even written this post. To-do lists are probably one of the simplest productivity hacks out there. You should absolutely write them. But you should &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt; write them unless you write a different list first. It’s what I call &lt;strong&gt;to-be&lt;/strong&gt; list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-to-be-list-and-what-is-on-mine&quot;&gt;What is a to-be list, and what is on mine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting sh*t done is cool, but we all know there are more important things out there. Like realizing your full potential and being a kind human being. That’ what the to-be list is there to help you with. Unlike a to-do list, you write it once and then you rarely change it. It should have just a handful of items (say maximum twelve) and they will be deeply personal. The main purpose of a to-be list is to first figure out what kind of person you want to be, and then help you be one.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every to-be list is unique, but for the sake of inspiration, here is what is on mine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emotional generosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infectious enthusiasm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social courage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intellectual curiosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relentless resourcefulness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotional generosity&lt;/strong&gt; is living with your heart open, letting your feelings and emotions be seen, but also creating space to listen and fully apprehend those of others.  &lt;strong&gt;Infectious enthusiasm&lt;/strong&gt; is creating an atmosphere of joy around everything you do and sharing it with others.
&lt;strong&gt;Social courage&lt;/strong&gt; is asking for what you want and speaking up to fight injustice. &lt;strong&gt;Intellectual curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; is about understanding the world around you as much as you can, without making assumptions about it (and other people’s opinions about it). &lt;strong&gt;Relentless resourcefulness&lt;/strong&gt; is being maximally helpful anytime you get chance to – a friend of a friend is looking for new home? You ask around. A friend travels to a city you have been to? You share your favorite places to visit. A colleague is stuck with a work task? You offer to troubleshoot and brainstorm together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;will-you-write-your-to-be-list&quot;&gt;Will you write your to-be list?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t always manage to live up to my to-be list but having one certainly does help me to do it more frequently. In a world where the word ambition has become almost uniquely associated with career, I find it very important to remind myself that ambitions for one’s character are much more important.
If you agree, I encourage you to write a to-be list of your own, maybe taking an inspiration from mine, but more importantly reflecting your own unique experience and character.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If you are exceptionally creative, you could weave your to-be list into a small poem and maybe say it out loud each morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am curious – what would be in your to-be list? And why? Let me know in the comments and thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;screenshot-essay-version&quot;&gt;Screenshot essay version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/240303_ToBeList.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot Essay&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
This essay, in a screenshot format.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As an aside, for the productivity freaks out there, research supports the argument that people who set personal goals see this translate to productivity at work, in at least equal measure as people who just set work-related goals. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Inspiration for items on a to-be list can come from anywhere. I got mine from Fred again .., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/jia_jiang_what_i_learned_from_100_days_of_rejection&quot;&gt;Jia Jiang&lt;/a&gt;, Paul Graham, and few others. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">To-do lists are great, but not sufficient Writing a to-do list is a practical and effective way to free mental capacity and avoid forgetting tasks that you may have to execute at work and other domains of your life. To-do lists are great. In fact, and I am very sure I would be incapable of keeping track of all the tasks I may have to do, wasn’t it for keeping a to-do list. I may not have even written this post. To-do lists are probably one of the simplest productivity hacks out there. You should absolutely write them. But you should NOT write them unless you write a different list first. It’s what I call to-be list. What is a to-be list, and what is on mine Getting sh*t done is cool, but we all know there are more important things out there. Like realizing your full potential and being a kind human being. That’ what the to-be list is there to help you with. Unlike a to-do list, you write it once and then you rarely change it. It should have just a handful of items (say maximum twelve) and they will be deeply personal. The main purpose of a to-be list is to first figure out what kind of person you want to be, and then help you be one.1 Every to-be list is unique, but for the sake of inspiration, here is what is on mine: Emotional generosity Infectious enthusiasm Social courage Intellectual curiosity Relentless resourcefulness Emotional generosity is living with your heart open, letting your feelings and emotions be seen, but also creating space to listen and fully apprehend those of others. Infectious enthusiasm is creating an atmosphere of joy around everything you do and sharing it with others. Social courage is asking for what you want and speaking up to fight injustice. Intellectual curiosity is about understanding the world around you as much as you can, without making assumptions about it (and other people’s opinions about it). Relentless resourcefulness is being maximally helpful anytime you get chance to – a friend of a friend is looking for new home? You ask around. A friend travels to a city you have been to? You share your favorite places to visit. A colleague is stuck with a work task? You offer to troubleshoot and brainstorm together. Will you write your to-be list? I don’t always manage to live up to my to-be list but having one certainly does help me to do it more frequently. In a world where the word ambition has become almost uniquely associated with career, I find it very important to remind myself that ambitions for one’s character are much more important. If you agree, I encourage you to write a to-be list of your own, maybe taking an inspiration from mine, but more importantly reflecting your own unique experience and character.2 If you are exceptionally creative, you could weave your to-be list into a small poem and maybe say it out loud each morning. I am curious – what would be in your to-be list? And why? Let me know in the comments and thanks for reading! Screenshot essay version This essay, in a screenshot format. As an aside, for the productivity freaks out there, research supports the argument that people who set personal goals see this translate to productivity at work, in at least equal measure as people who just set work-related goals. &amp;#8617; Inspiration for items on a to-be list can come from anywhere. I got mine from Fred again .., Jia Jiang, Paul Graham, and few others. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Makes a Great Startup Founder?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/22/PmarcaAdviceForFounders.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Makes a Great Startup Founder?" /><published>2024-01-22T09:41:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T09:41:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/22/PmarcaAdviceForFounders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/22/PmarcaAdviceForFounders.html">&lt;p&gt;In the episode #385 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lex_Fridman&quot;&gt;Lex Fridman’s&lt;/a&gt; podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen&quot;&gt;Marc Andreessen&lt;/a&gt; talks about what makes a great founder and what advice he would give to young people. You can watch the excerpt here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-hxeDjAxvJ8?si=Ium65Pj10vMVCsCk&amp;amp;start=9835&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- https://www.chunkhang.com/blog/responsive-youtube-video-with-jekyll use as include youtube.html id=&apos;....&apos;  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have lot of respect for Marc Andreessen. He is a techno-optimist and visionary as well as very clear and opiniated thinker. No one can predict the future, but he gives it a fair shot for some things, and I will listen when he tries. I suggest checking his &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmarchive.com/&quot;&gt;archival blog&lt;/a&gt; for productivity and startup logistics resources, and some of his podcast appearances to learn more about how he thinks (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://conversationswithtyler.com/episodes/marc-andreessen/&quot;&gt;Conversations with Tyler #152&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Marc Andreessen gives advice for how to identify good founders, or how to become one, it’s good to take a note. Here are the major points he discusses in the excerpt above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;characteristics-of-a-great-founder&quot;&gt;Characteristics of a great founder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation starts quite funny, when being asked what advice he would give to aspiring startup founder, Marc says, that he cannot really give any, because the really great founders don’t listen to advice. That is a catchy way to put it, but it intuitively seems true. Marc argues that founders who need to be guided by hand towards company creation are likely better off doing something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another catchy statement he highlights that there really is not a good way to reference check star-up founders who have not run a company before. The right reference you look for is “I would go work for that person”, but that’s not something the referees would be commonly thinking of saying.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other characteristics he mentions are being smart, energetic, and courageous. Where the last one, he argues, is a choice (more on this below).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-it-like-to-start-a-company&quot;&gt;What is it like to start a company&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entrepreneurial career is often romanticized, pictured almost as a discovery quest of new continent or planet (from there the oft-advertised imagery of spaceships, astronauts, and other explorers). The founder is depicted as someone with clear vision, leading an enthusiastic team towards a shared goal, which is some combination of world being a better place and everyone on the team affording a large house and a sports car (or a high-end caravan and a boat, if that’s your thing) just few years down the line, while enjoying weekly Friday happy hours and yearly company outings. While I think this is helpful to make more people attentive to the possibility of pursuing entrepreneurial career, it is also vital for exactly these people to realize that it’s mostly nothing like that.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc Andreessen comments that the reality for founders is basically people repeatedly saying “no” to you, often followed by some version of “never” and “you are stupid”. “No, I won’t buy your product”, “No, I won’t leave my cushy job in a big company to go work for you”, “No, we won’t run a story about your company on social media”, are just some of the many options of how one can be rejected. Rejection is painful, it does take quite some training to prevent it from having you feel like sh*it for a week after receiving one, and you will never become completely immune to taking it personally.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think you think that accepting one rejection blow after another is something you could deal with &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; – think of doing that, while grinning from cheek to cheek, joyfully welcoming your employees with a smile and chat about their wedding preparation plans, while also sharing enthusiasm and your vision with everyone from the janitor to your prospective funders. How easy does that sound? (Sorry to hear about your own cancelled engagement by the way! It turns out that with 80-hour work weeks there is little time left for great dates!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, starting a company is not a smooth ride, so you may even get some strange sense of gratitude once it goes under, which, &lt;em&gt;what a plot twist turning THIS into a happy ending!&lt;/em&gt;, it most likely will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-should-start-a-company&quot;&gt;Who should start a company&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having read the above, you must be wondering – is a great founder also a sociopath? Well kind of. According to Marc Andreessen, people who start companies should have a irresistible desire to see their solution on the market, a burning feeling that they cannot do otherwise but startup. This will hedge them against the many adversities they are bound to encounter – having their private life as well as their perceived self-worth challenged, they can always console themselves with the reminder that there was no other way (here you go, if your startup fails, you can become a stoic philosopher!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burning desire seems important but will burn really really bright and fast if the tech is not solid. The would-be successful founders must have a great and specific technical product idea. No one should start a company on a vague vision of “transforming XYZ”, ”solving XYZ crisis”, or “making XYZ more sustainable”, no matter how noble or important this might seem. In fact, its probably better to forget about any grand vision until you have a working product that you are selling at a profit. You can get fancy with visions afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great and specific technical product idea is not a holy grail unless it also checks the boxes for the size of the opportunity, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmarchive.com/guide_to_startups_part4.html&quot;&gt;product-market fit&lt;/a&gt; and you are able &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grahamweaver.com/blog/threesurprisinglessons&quot;&gt;to build a great team&lt;/a&gt; around it, but all these topics are beyond the scope of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this leave you excited about entrepreneurship? Congratulations, you seem to be a masochist with large pain tolerance. The world needs you to go out there and get your hands dirty making some great products. Before you do so, you can learn more by reading Marc Andreessen’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmarchive.com/index.html#guide-to-startups&quot;&gt;Guide to Startups&lt;/a&gt;. I will keep blogging on this and related topics using variety of resources, so &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to stay updated and keep learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this leave you thinking entrepreneurship is not for you? Congratulations, you may have saved yourself some grey hair and couple of good friends. Maybe more importantly (because reading this post you may be biased to starting up), it should give you an idea what place you want to be in to be comfortable being serous about staring up,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final Note&lt;/b&gt;: It is not my intention to leave you thinking that starting up means giving up on any personal life. This tone was chosen to accentuate some ideas in relatable way. While it’s certainly possible to weigh heavily on the side of work in exchange for the private, people who are prone to do so will likely do it as employees as well. Building a sustainable business means building an environment people enjoy coming back to, and to become a great leader, you must accept the imperative to make your mental and physical wellbeing a priority. Finally, running a business is empowering and this can have large positive ramifications across all aspects of one’s life.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unless you explicitly ask them for it, of course! (Say individual X starts an enterprise, on scale of 1-10: how likely do you think they are going to be successful? How likely would you be to join their team when offered the opportunity to do so?) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I am of somewhat different opinion and believe it’s more of a habit as much as being energetic is one. More than that, I would also say that most people have large capacity to be both, energetic and courageous, and that making this a habitual state is mainly a subtractive process (of eliminating distractions, limiting beliefs and inner conflicts). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I am NOT speaking from personal experience. I do however have some second-hand experience through friends, and I am attentive to writing from founders that is on the internet. If you disagree and your startup actually does feel like haven on earth, I want to hear from you about what you are doing differently (and whether you are hiring). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s the, in this case mostly unfortunate, condition of human mind, that we will be struck more heavily by negative emotions and events than by the positive ones (that’s why all the news outlets seem like a catastrophe reel). While this was super-helpful to increase chances of survival of our species (finally a miracle you can truly put yourself behind), it is mostly maladaptive in today’s environment. Knowing this is only slightly helpful at moments when you are questioning your value as a human being after being rejected on some microscopically tiny aspect of your existence. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And you really should not say this before having some evidence to attest to it. If you don’t have, it’s still fair you want to try, but I would suggest collecting it with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rejectiontherapy.com/100-days-of-rejection-therapy/&quot;&gt;Rejection Therapy&lt;/a&gt; before starting a company. Stakes are much lower and it’s also much more fun. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="startup" /><category term="education" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">In the episode #385 of Lex Fridman’s podcast, Marc Andreessen talks about what makes a great founder and what advice he would give to young people. You can watch the excerpt here: I have lot of respect for Marc Andreessen. He is a techno-optimist and visionary as well as very clear and opiniated thinker. No one can predict the future, but he gives it a fair shot for some things, and I will listen when he tries. I suggest checking his archival blog for productivity and startup logistics resources, and some of his podcast appearances to learn more about how he thinks (e.g. Conversations with Tyler #152). When Marc Andreessen gives advice for how to identify good founders, or how to become one, it’s good to take a note. Here are the major points he discusses in the excerpt above: Characteristics of a great founder The conversation starts quite funny, when being asked what advice he would give to aspiring startup founder, Marc says, that he cannot really give any, because the really great founders don’t listen to advice. That is a catchy way to put it, but it intuitively seems true. Marc argues that founders who need to be guided by hand towards company creation are likely better off doing something else. In another catchy statement he highlights that there really is not a good way to reference check star-up founders who have not run a company before. The right reference you look for is “I would go work for that person”, but that’s not something the referees would be commonly thinking of saying.1 Other characteristics he mentions are being smart, energetic, and courageous. Where the last one, he argues, is a choice (more on this below).2 What is it like to start a company The entrepreneurial career is often romanticized, pictured almost as a discovery quest of new continent or planet (from there the oft-advertised imagery of spaceships, astronauts, and other explorers). The founder is depicted as someone with clear vision, leading an enthusiastic team towards a shared goal, which is some combination of world being a better place and everyone on the team affording a large house and a sports car (or a high-end caravan and a boat, if that’s your thing) just few years down the line, while enjoying weekly Friday happy hours and yearly company outings. While I think this is helpful to make more people attentive to the possibility of pursuing entrepreneurial career, it is also vital for exactly these people to realize that it’s mostly nothing like that.3 Marc Andreessen comments that the reality for founders is basically people repeatedly saying “no” to you, often followed by some version of “never” and “you are stupid”. “No, I won’t buy your product”, “No, I won’t leave my cushy job in a big company to go work for you”, “No, we won’t run a story about your company on social media”, are just some of the many options of how one can be rejected. Rejection is painful, it does take quite some training to prevent it from having you feel like sh*it for a week after receiving one, and you will never become completely immune to taking it personally.4 If you think you think that accepting one rejection blow after another is something you could deal with 5 – think of doing that, while grinning from cheek to cheek, joyfully welcoming your employees with a smile and chat about their wedding preparation plans, while also sharing enthusiasm and your vision with everyone from the janitor to your prospective funders. How easy does that sound? (Sorry to hear about your own cancelled engagement by the way! It turns out that with 80-hour work weeks there is little time left for great dates!) Clearly, starting a company is not a smooth ride, so you may even get some strange sense of gratitude once it goes under, which, what a plot twist turning THIS into a happy ending!, it most likely will. Who should start a company Having read the above, you must be wondering – is a great founder also a sociopath? Well kind of. According to Marc Andreessen, people who start companies should have a irresistible desire to see their solution on the market, a burning feeling that they cannot do otherwise but startup. This will hedge them against the many adversities they are bound to encounter – having their private life as well as their perceived self-worth challenged, they can always console themselves with the reminder that there was no other way (here you go, if your startup fails, you can become a stoic philosopher!). Burning desire seems important but will burn really really bright and fast if the tech is not solid. The would-be successful founders must have a great and specific technical product idea. No one should start a company on a vague vision of “transforming XYZ”, ”solving XYZ crisis”, or “making XYZ more sustainable”, no matter how noble or important this might seem. In fact, its probably better to forget about any grand vision until you have a working product that you are selling at a profit. You can get fancy with visions afterwards. Great and specific technical product idea is not a holy grail unless it also checks the boxes for the size of the opportunity, the product-market fit and you are able to build a great team around it, but all these topics are beyond the scope of this post. Conclusion Does this leave you excited about entrepreneurship? Congratulations, you seem to be a masochist with large pain tolerance. The world needs you to go out there and get your hands dirty making some great products. Before you do so, you can learn more by reading Marc Andreessen’s Guide to Startups. I will keep blogging on this and related topics using variety of resources, so subscribe to stay updated and keep learning. Does this leave you thinking entrepreneurship is not for you? Congratulations, you may have saved yourself some grey hair and couple of good friends. Maybe more importantly (because reading this post you may be biased to starting up), it should give you an idea what place you want to be in to be comfortable being serous about staring up, Final Note: It is not my intention to leave you thinking that starting up means giving up on any personal life. This tone was chosen to accentuate some ideas in relatable way. While it’s certainly possible to weigh heavily on the side of work in exchange for the private, people who are prone to do so will likely do it as employees as well. Building a sustainable business means building an environment people enjoy coming back to, and to become a great leader, you must accept the imperative to make your mental and physical wellbeing a priority. Finally, running a business is empowering and this can have large positive ramifications across all aspects of one’s life. Footnotes Unless you explicitly ask them for it, of course! (Say individual X starts an enterprise, on scale of 1-10: how likely do you think they are going to be successful? How likely would you be to join their team when offered the opportunity to do so?) &amp;#8617; I am of somewhat different opinion and believe it’s more of a habit as much as being energetic is one. More than that, I would also say that most people have large capacity to be both, energetic and courageous, and that making this a habitual state is mainly a subtractive process (of eliminating distractions, limiting beliefs and inner conflicts). &amp;#8617; I am NOT speaking from personal experience. I do however have some second-hand experience through friends, and I am attentive to writing from founders that is on the internet. If you disagree and your startup actually does feel like haven on earth, I want to hear from you about what you are doing differently (and whether you are hiring). &amp;#8617; It’s the, in this case mostly unfortunate, condition of human mind, that we will be struck more heavily by negative emotions and events than by the positive ones (that’s why all the news outlets seem like a catastrophe reel). While this was super-helpful to increase chances of survival of our species (finally a miracle you can truly put yourself behind), it is mostly maladaptive in today’s environment. Knowing this is only slightly helpful at moments when you are questioning your value as a human being after being rejected on some microscopically tiny aspect of your existence. &amp;#8617; And you really should not say this before having some evidence to attest to it. If you don’t have, it’s still fair you want to try, but I would suggest collecting it with Rejection Therapy before starting a company. Stakes are much lower and it’s also much more fun. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We Lived During a War</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/01/05/WeLivedDuringWar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Lived During a War" /><published>2024-01-05T08:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-05T08:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/01/05/WeLivedDuringWar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2024/01/05/WeLivedDuringWar.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/llmwar.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;llm war prompt&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Curiously, the model can provide an answer for many country pairs. Some are, however, censored out.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several things happened over the course of this Christmas holiday. First, Russia carried out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/russia-launches-massive-air-attack-ukraine-least-10-dead-kyiv-2023-12-29/&quot;&gt;largest air attack on Ukraine since the beginning of their offense&lt;/a&gt;. Second, a man shot fourteen university students dead, wounding 25 and killing himself in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2023_Prague_shooting&quot;&gt;Prague mass school shooting&lt;/a&gt;. Third, I read a poem that tied the events together in an unexpected way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;russia-ukraine-conflict&quot;&gt;Russia-Ukraine conflict&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has been carrying out military offense on Ukraine for nearly two years now, with tens of thousands of causalities, immeasurable amount of human suffering and long lasting environmental and geopolitical consequences. Basic services are failing, and families are torn apart. The future potential of individuals as well as the country is radically diminished. Humans can, in one way or another, cope with just about anything, so life goes on. But those who will go through to see the end of it will emerge with unerasable animosity for the opponent.
I am Czech, and I don’t easily make friends with Russians. Don’t get me wrong, I have several Russian friends, some of them close ones. I have worked with many Russians and will do so in the future. I am willing to give anyone the benefit of doubt. However, anyone who I meet who is Russian will first undergo value-based scrutiny. I grew up in a former communist country, where the possibilities I had and the mindsets of people around me were crippled by the country’s history. I grew up on the backdrop of history of oppression, injustice, and fear. While many Czechoslovaks do carry the guilt of supporting the communist regime, it would have never emerged was it not for the territorial ambitions of the Soviets &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;israel-palestine-conflict&quot;&gt;Israel-Palestine conflict&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am also wary of Israelis. After a Hamas’ terrorist attack in early October 2023, Israel has launched a massive offensive targeting the Gaza Strip &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2023_Israel%E2%80%93Hamas_war&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. It’s disguised as a revenge, but it is more than that. One thing is demanding some just settlement after violent action of Hamas’, the other is jumping at it as a pretext for perpetuating genocide. Over 1’500 Israeli and international soldiers and civilians were killed in the operation so far, while the death count on the Palestinian side surpasses 21’000. 
I am at loss of words to describe either the violence that happens there, or my helplessness over the international lapse to prevent this escalation. A year ago I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://leidenshorts.nl/film/image-of-victory/&quot;&gt;a short movie&lt;/a&gt; that is a great artist expression of criticism for the conflict, and something I come back to frequently to find some framework for coping with current events. The movie begins with a 2004 military offensive in Gaza, where a soldier is injured. The move then goes ahead following his recovery in an Isreali hospital. He is visited by tens of people, including Bar Rafeli and the Israeli defense minister, and touted as a war hero. Subtly, an impression of utter farce and futility surfaces &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;terror-close-to-home&quot;&gt;Terror close to home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two ongoing armed conflicts described above sound dreadful for anyone, soldiers and civilians alike. But it is very difficult for any of us who are not directly affected by the conflict to imagine what it must be like to experience this terror firsthand. 
Just before Christmas, a 24-year old man shot 14 university students dead, injuring 25 before killing himself in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2023_Prague_shooting&quot;&gt;worst mass shooting of the modern Czech history&lt;/a&gt;. Czech Republic is a country of 10 million – that’s not necessarily small. 14 is ballpark one in a million. Yet when terrible things like this happen, you understand how close we actually are. Almost anyone will, directly, or indirectly, know someone who is affected. A friend of a friend died in hospital with bullet hole in their skull and someone I know nearly ended up being at the location of shooting, at the time it happened, was it not for a coincidental plan change. And I don’t even live in the city where it happened, heck, I have been living abroad for seven years by now.
The shooting happened just before Christmas holidays, and I went to its location several days after to light a candle and pay memory to the victims. As I stood there, overlooking the building where it happened and the square it faces, I closed my eyes. As soon as I did that, I could not find the imagery of people running away in panic. The imaginary sounds of shots fired resonating between the buildings on the square sent shivers up my spine. It felt terrible, but all that was just a fraction of how people that were present there when it happened must have felt, and that in itself was at least as bad as what people who live in areas of armed conflict must go through on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silence-is-a-statement&quot;&gt;Silence is a statement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, no one in their sane mind who has both feet on the ground would wish for armed violence to continue for a second longer. And let’s be fair, we don’t. But what has any of us done to express this sentiment? Are we mounting massive protests? Do we send financial support for humanitarian efforts in war struck regions? Do we put fierce and relentless pressure on our governments to do all they can to exert diplomatic and economic pressure on the perpetuators of the conflict? No, for the most part we don’t do any of that. I am myself employed at a major university in the Netherlands. Nowhere on the campus there are any signs of support for either Ukraine or Palestine. In the many months following the beginning of the conflict, no public statements to condemn the violence have been made. I find this extremely frustrating. Are leaders too afraid of being cancelled for taking a political stance? Only recently I realized one sad truth – not making a statement, is a statement of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-poem&quot;&gt;The poem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I told you about three things that happened, and those were two so far. The last one is a poem I read, that ties the two together. I will just leave you here with it to see how it does that for yourself (click &lt;a href=&quot;https://onbeing.org/programs/ilya-kaminsky-we-lived-happily-during-the-war/&quot;&gt;this link if you want to hear it narrated&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/kaminsky_poem.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;poem from kaminsky&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Poem by Ilya Kaminsky from his 2019 collection Deaf Republic. Image taken from &lt;a href=&quot; https://ericweinste.in/&quot;&gt;ericweinste.in&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the very same reasons, I am also more wary of Germans, but to much smaller extent. Knowing many of them well, I know they have done a lot of soul searching and retrospection over the past decades, clearly demonstrating the departure from mindsets that perpetuated the World Wars. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The tension is there to stay. Either party finds themselves to be more in right than the other (see interviews with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ry6kpYFHnxs&amp;amp;ab_channel=CoreyGil-Shuster&quot;&gt;Palestinians&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JhSHTJr8S64&amp;amp;t=199s&amp;amp;ab_channel=CoreyGil-Shuster&quot;&gt;Israeli&lt;/a&gt;), and I am in no way an arbiter of who is more right and who is not when it comes to the territorial conflict. I do however stand behind the statement that Israel is committing ethnic cleansing and that internationally we must require our leaders to call it what it is and to work to stop it as soon as possible. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Curiously, the model can provide an answer for many country pairs. Some are, however, censored out. Several things happened over the course of this Christmas holiday. First, Russia carried out the largest air attack on Ukraine since the beginning of their offense. Second, a man shot fourteen university students dead, wounding 25 and killing himself in Prague mass school shooting. Third, I read a poem that tied the events together in an unexpected way. Russia-Ukraine conflict Russia has been carrying out military offense on Ukraine for nearly two years now, with tens of thousands of causalities, immeasurable amount of human suffering and long lasting environmental and geopolitical consequences. Basic services are failing, and families are torn apart. The future potential of individuals as well as the country is radically diminished. Humans can, in one way or another, cope with just about anything, so life goes on. But those who will go through to see the end of it will emerge with unerasable animosity for the opponent. I am Czech, and I don’t easily make friends with Russians. Don’t get me wrong, I have several Russian friends, some of them close ones. I have worked with many Russians and will do so in the future. I am willing to give anyone the benefit of doubt. However, anyone who I meet who is Russian will first undergo value-based scrutiny. I grew up in a former communist country, where the possibilities I had and the mindsets of people around me were crippled by the country’s history. I grew up on the backdrop of history of oppression, injustice, and fear. While many Czechoslovaks do carry the guilt of supporting the communist regime, it would have never emerged was it not for the territorial ambitions of the Soviets 1. Israel-Palestine conflict Now, I am also wary of Israelis. After a Hamas’ terrorist attack in early October 2023, Israel has launched a massive offensive targeting the Gaza Strip Wikipedia. It’s disguised as a revenge, but it is more than that. One thing is demanding some just settlement after violent action of Hamas’, the other is jumping at it as a pretext for perpetuating genocide. Over 1’500 Israeli and international soldiers and civilians were killed in the operation so far, while the death count on the Palestinian side surpasses 21’000. I am at loss of words to describe either the violence that happens there, or my helplessness over the international lapse to prevent this escalation. A year ago I saw a short movie that is a great artist expression of criticism for the conflict, and something I come back to frequently to find some framework for coping with current events. The movie begins with a 2004 military offensive in Gaza, where a soldier is injured. The move then goes ahead following his recovery in an Isreali hospital. He is visited by tens of people, including Bar Rafeli and the Israeli defense minister, and touted as a war hero. Subtly, an impression of utter farce and futility surfaces 2. Terror close to home The two ongoing armed conflicts described above sound dreadful for anyone, soldiers and civilians alike. But it is very difficult for any of us who are not directly affected by the conflict to imagine what it must be like to experience this terror firsthand. Just before Christmas, a 24-year old man shot 14 university students dead, injuring 25 before killing himself in the worst mass shooting of the modern Czech history. Czech Republic is a country of 10 million – that’s not necessarily small. 14 is ballpark one in a million. Yet when terrible things like this happen, you understand how close we actually are. Almost anyone will, directly, or indirectly, know someone who is affected. A friend of a friend died in hospital with bullet hole in their skull and someone I know nearly ended up being at the location of shooting, at the time it happened, was it not for a coincidental plan change. And I don’t even live in the city where it happened, heck, I have been living abroad for seven years by now. The shooting happened just before Christmas holidays, and I went to its location several days after to light a candle and pay memory to the victims. As I stood there, overlooking the building where it happened and the square it faces, I closed my eyes. As soon as I did that, I could not find the imagery of people running away in panic. The imaginary sounds of shots fired resonating between the buildings on the square sent shivers up my spine. It felt terrible, but all that was just a fraction of how people that were present there when it happened must have felt, and that in itself was at least as bad as what people who live in areas of armed conflict must go through on a regular basis. Silence is a statement Clearly, no one in their sane mind who has both feet on the ground would wish for armed violence to continue for a second longer. And let’s be fair, we don’t. But what has any of us done to express this sentiment? Are we mounting massive protests? Do we send financial support for humanitarian efforts in war struck regions? Do we put fierce and relentless pressure on our governments to do all they can to exert diplomatic and economic pressure on the perpetuators of the conflict? No, for the most part we don’t do any of that. I am myself employed at a major university in the Netherlands. Nowhere on the campus there are any signs of support for either Ukraine or Palestine. In the many months following the beginning of the conflict, no public statements to condemn the violence have been made. I find this extremely frustrating. Are leaders too afraid of being cancelled for taking a political stance? Only recently I realized one sad truth – not making a statement, is a statement of its own. The poem So I told you about three things that happened, and those were two so far. The last one is a poem I read, that ties the two together. I will just leave you here with it to see how it does that for yourself (click this link if you want to hear it narrated): Poem by Ilya Kaminsky from his 2019 collection Deaf Republic. Image taken from ericweinste.in. For the very same reasons, I am also more wary of Germans, but to much smaller extent. Knowing many of them well, I know they have done a lot of soul searching and retrospection over the past decades, clearly demonstrating the departure from mindsets that perpetuated the World Wars. &amp;#8617; The tension is there to stay. Either party finds themselves to be more in right than the other (see interviews with Palestinians and Israeli), and I am in no way an arbiter of who is more right and who is not when it comes to the territorial conflict. I do however stand behind the statement that Israel is committing ethnic cleansing and that internationally we must require our leaders to call it what it is and to work to stop it as soon as possible. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">26 Lessons on How to Run a Business from the Book ‘The Personal MBA’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/05/PersonalMBA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="26 Lessons on How to Run a Business from the Book ‘The Personal MBA’" /><published>2024-01-05T07:16:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-05T07:16:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/05/PersonalMBA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/startup/2024/01/05/PersonalMBA.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/personalmba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;mba&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@bramnaus&quot;&gt;Bram Naus&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us out there in the tech and business world will consider pursuing an MBA at one point. While this can be a rewarding experience, it comes with a hefty price tag and equally significant opportunity cost. There are plenty of reasons for pursuing a full-fledged program (social capital and prestigious stamp are just a few), but for many, a shorter course and real-world practice will do well. I am a big proponent of self-reliance and thus was delighted to learn about the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9512985-the-personal-mba&quot;&gt;The Personal MBA: A World-Class Business Education in a Single Volume&lt;/a&gt;. If you are interested in how businesses work, or even considering pursuing MBA, this book a is a great starting point. Below you will find a selection of my personal major takeaways. If you find these interesting, certainly check the author’s website at &lt;a href=&quot;https://personalmba.com/&quot;&gt;personalmba.com&lt;/a&gt; (it’s also a great source of witty quotes). Without further ado, some things I learnt about running businesses by reading this book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;efficient-processes-are-key-to-sustainable-businesses&quot;&gt;Efficient processes are key to sustainable businesses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Process improvements don’t help the immediate bottom line, but they are essential to long-term business viability. Stray free of the other extreme, overoptimization. Good loose system beats a tight-one. While the former is less efficient, the latter requires numerous exceptions which still won’t prevent it from failing in unexpected ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-companies-are-sexy&quot;&gt;Small companies are sexy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the U. S. Small Business Administration, small businesses represent 99.7 percent of all employer firms in the United States, employ half of all private-sector workers, have generated 64 percent of net new jobs over the past fifteen years, and create more than 50 percent of U.S. nonfarm gross domestic product (GDP).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; You don’t have to create next Amazon or Tesla to have huge positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;businesses-are-not-rocket-science&quot;&gt;Businesses are not rocket science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A business 1) provides something of value, that 2) other people want, 3) at a price they are willing to pay, 4) in a way that satisfies or exceeds their expectations, while 5) generating sufficient revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The milestone between a project and a business is first financially profitable transaction. Keep eye on the prize and get it as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;product-should-satisfy-one-or-more-fundamental-human-drives&quot;&gt;Product should satisfy one or more fundamental human drives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drives are the drive to Acquire, the drive to Bond, the drive to Learn, the drive to Defend, the drive to Feel.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Clearly articulate how your product ties to one or more of these drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluate-market-potential-of-your-idea&quot;&gt;Evaluate market potential of your idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On scale 0 to 10, score the following: 1) How badly do people want or need your product right now? 2) How many people are purchasing things like this already?, 3) What is the highest price consumers would pay for this?, 4) How much will it cost to acquire new customers, 5) How much does it cost to create and deliver your product?, 6) How unique is your offer? 7) How quickly can you start selling something?, 8) How much you have to invest before you can make and sell your product? 9) How easy it is to generate secondary sales from the primary product? (if you sell an enzyme, can you sell reagent kits or experiment kits with it as well?), 10) How much work does your product require to keep delivering value? (in-person training requires a lot, a prerecorded online programme requires none).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;competition-is-a-gift&quot;&gt;Competition is a gift&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When deciding to enter to otherwise equal markets, enter the one with competition, that way you know there are consumers for your offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn how competitors deliver value is to become their customer.
The best way to beat your rivals is to make them irrelevant. Don’t focus on competing, focus on making a killer product. Remember, in words of Paul Graham: &lt;em&gt;“If in doubt, work on the product.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-less-obvious-ways-to-create-economic-value&quot;&gt;Some less obvious ways to create economic value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared resource&lt;/strong&gt; – lab space, a gym, …. Create and manage a durable asset that multiple parties use, and charge for access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An agency&lt;/strong&gt; – literary and real estate agents, … Collect, manage, market and sell an asset or service on other people’s behalf, and collect a fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt; – tickets, … Offer customers the possibility of taking some action in the future, at predefined prices, without obliging them to do so. In other words, charge for providing flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audience aggregation&lt;/strong&gt; – mailing lists, social media, … Create community with certain set of characteristics. Get and keep their attention by providing something they value. Provide access to this community to third parties and charge for the access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more obvious ways are: service, product, subscription, lease, loan, insurance, capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-generating-and-sharing-mock-ups-and-prototypes&quot;&gt;Keep generating and sharing mock-ups and prototypes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are much more likely to get funded if you can show a demo or prototype. Sharing it with customers is the best way how to get feedback. These benefits significantly outweigh the risk of competition jumping on your idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quicker you generate new versions of demo’s and the quicker you collect feedback on them, the faster you will start delivering a product of value. Internal testing counts too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-pre-orders-and-shadow-testing-to-gauge-your-product-market-fit&quot;&gt;Use pre-orders and shadow-testing to gauge your product-market fit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you working on a product and do you want to have reliable data on who is out there to buy it? Create opportunity to preorder or a mock-up website and collect information on people who commit to purchase. Beware: be honest and perfectly transparent about the current readiness of your offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-trade-offs&quot;&gt;Make trade-offs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Product can be convenient or it can be high-end. It can address a pain point immediately, or focus on something more subtle and deliver value over time. Rarely it will be able to do both equally well. You will thus need to make trade-offs, and that’s a good thing. Focus on trade-offs that maximize the strengths of your offering, and satisfy the needs of your customers. To find out the latter: ask them to make explicit A/B trade-offs for key characteristic of your offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once marketing your product, verbalize your offering’s major strength in a hook. Good hooks are one-liners such as &lt;em&gt;“1000 songs in your pocket”&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;“The 20-Minute Body”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-true-marketing-value-of-social-media&quot;&gt;The true marketing value of social media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered why the ads you are getting on Instagram are so interesting? That’s because they are tailored to yours truly. To use marketing budget effectively, target groups of prospects who are likely to be interested in your product already. This extends beyond social media: always choose smaller targeted campaign over a general one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;permission-to-follow-up-is-the-second-best-thing-after-a-direct-sale&quot;&gt;Permission to follow-up is the second-best thing after a direct sale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your marketing campaign should have clear call to action. The primary objective is a sale. The second-best option is a follow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquiring new prospects requires effort. It’s much easier to reach out to a contact who demonstrated interest earlier. Do so periodically, and absolutely do include former customers when doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asking for permission to follow up, be super clear what customers should expect when they sign up (a weekly newsletter with one new productivity trick each week, etc …), and let customers explicitly state their interest in future purchase on sign-up (a pre-commitment strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-tips-for-effective-selling&quot;&gt;Some tips for effective selling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to your customer, and understand what are their pain points and needs. Then demonstrate how your product addresses them (if it does). Point to competition if it does not. (Check &lt;a href=&quot;https://nabeelqu.co/post-selling&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for a good primer on sales.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your prospect imagine what a life with your product would be like. You can do this with demos, testers, or testimonials and other stories. The most effective testimonials describe customer satisfaction despite original scepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;offer-genuine-free-value&quot;&gt;Offer genuine free value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is great way how to ask for permission to follow up, collect feedback, and allow your customer to image what a life with your product would be like. It also creates a reciprocal relationship, making your prospects more likely to buy from you in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selling-begins-when-prospects-say-no&quot;&gt;Selling begins when prospects say no&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling is the process identifying and eliminating customers’ barriers to purchase. “It’s too expensive?” Focus on value your offering delivers. “It is not exactly what I am looking for?” Share testimonials and case studies. “It can wait?” Educate on the counterfactuals.
To reduce frequency of no, offer risk reversal strategy (e.g. free returns).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-just-meet-your-customers-expectations-exceed-them&quot;&gt;Don’t just meet your customer’s expectations, exceed them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The perception of quality is performance minus expectations. Create performance that exceeds expectations by offering an unexpected benefit with your offer (a freebie, earlier delivery than advertised, …).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;treat-your-value-delivery-process-as-an-experiment&quot;&gt;Treat your value delivery process as an experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The higher your throughput, the more customers you can serve. To increase your throughput focus on streamlining your value delivery process and eliminating any unnecessary steps. To be able to do this, you should deliberately outline your whole value stream, and measure how changes to its parts affect your throughput.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-focus-on-maximizing-short-term-profit&quot;&gt;Don’t focus on maximizing (short term) profit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You, of course, must generate profit. But you will achieve better results by focusing on serving as many customers as possible while capturing modest value. While this reduces short term results, it will make your business much better situated for the long-term (that’s why Apple is not selling a $100’000 iPhone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should reinvest most of revenue that your business generates into its growth for the same reason. It will compound your profits and after several years you will be in much better position than would have been the case otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;before-seeking-funding-decide-on-what-enterprise-you-want-to-build&quot;&gt;Before seeking funding decide on what enterprise you want to build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unicorn that races to IPO and leaves you wealthy at the exit? You will very likely need lot of external capital. A self-sufficient business that has you free to make your own decisions? Avoid external dilutive financing as much as possible. This will also make it easier to reinvest your profits (see above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do accept funding, use it solely to acquire things that will grow your revenue and that you could not afford otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-emotions-around-entrepreneurship&quot;&gt;Understand your emotions around entrepreneurship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fears and anxieties stop us from doing things we wish to do. These mental patterns were designed to protect us from objectively bad things, such as being expelled from community or being eaten by predator. The world has dramatically changed since. Risks we are facing when following our (healthy and socially acceptable) dreams and passions are disproportionately smaller, yet they trigger the same levels of fear and arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verbalize these fears by sharing them out loud with someone or writing them down. Imagine yourself pursing your goals and make mental note of what inner conflicts this triggers. Deconstruct these conflicts by asking yourself how significant they are in the real world. There is a good chance that doing so will leave you both more relaxed and motivated for pursuing your goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-a-personal-rd-budget&quot;&gt;Have a personal R&amp;amp;D budget&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the hustle and bustle of building and growing a business, you will have to keep in mind to put your wellbeing first. Assuming that is taken care of, you will also need to stay on top of the game in your field and as a manager. While you will learn a lot by doing, you can accelerate your growth by creating a personal R&amp;amp;D budget and spending it on anything that makes you more knowledgeable or productive. This includes classes, coaching, books, equipment and conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-teams-small-and-elite&quot;&gt;Keep teams small and elite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep teams small. Studies have shown that the most effective group size is somewhere between three and eight people.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Keep teams in this size to reduce communication overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep teams elite. In words of Paul English: &lt;em&gt;“Any company can have only ten best people.”&lt;/em&gt; Focus on making this ten better than your competitors, and then capitalize on individuals’ strengths. You will beat your competition irrespective of their total size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;five-tips-for-effective-real-world-management&quot;&gt;Five tips for effective real-world management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recruit only as many people as you need to deliver in high quality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a clear vision and ambitious plan for achieving it. Revise the plan as you go.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Treat people with respect and show appreciation for their effort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide your team with the best tools and don’t fraction their time with unnecessary meetings or distractions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure your performance and keep experimenting with process improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;any-repeated-task-can-benefit-from-automation&quot;&gt;Any repeated task can benefit from automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create checklists and SOPs to help both new and old employees to carry out tasks with more efficiency and less errors. Listen to your employees on what SOPs are needed. Steer clear of documents where effort to create and maintain them outweighs value they deliver. While automated systems reduce idiosyncratic errors, they can introduce systemic ones. Keep a finger on your processes’ pulse with unbiased and continuous sampling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-stress-tests&quot;&gt;Run stress tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internally simulate what happens if you get 10x your daily visitor count, number of orders per week, a major recall, a major supplier goes out of business, etc…. Find ways how your value delivery chain fails in internal experiments, and safeguard against future real world crisis. You will learn that you should, as much as possible, avoid having a single point of failure (having one customer much larger than rest, single supplier of critical ingredient, etc …).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-fun&quot;&gt;Have fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you read the above points, you probably noticed that they have you understanding yourself as a person, getting rid of self-defeating beliefs, carrying out experiments, working with bright and inspiring colleagues, all the while following your passion and making a positive change in the world. That’s a great career! So don’t forget to have fun and enjoy the ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;www.sba.gov/advo/stats/sbfaq.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1878833.Driven &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67825.Peopleware &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="startup" /><category term="education" /><category term="business" /><summary type="html">Photo by Bram Naus on Unsplash. Many of us out there in the tech and business world will consider pursuing an MBA at one point. While this can be a rewarding experience, it comes with a hefty price tag and equally significant opportunity cost. There are plenty of reasons for pursuing a full-fledged program (social capital and prestigious stamp are just a few), but for many, a shorter course and real-world practice will do well. I am a big proponent of self-reliance and thus was delighted to learn about the book The Personal MBA: A World-Class Business Education in a Single Volume. If you are interested in how businesses work, or even considering pursuing MBA, this book a is a great starting point. Below you will find a selection of my personal major takeaways. If you find these interesting, certainly check the author’s website at personalmba.com (it’s also a great source of witty quotes). Without further ado, some things I learnt about running businesses by reading this book: Efficient processes are key to sustainable businesses Process improvements don’t help the immediate bottom line, but they are essential to long-term business viability. Stray free of the other extreme, overoptimization. Good loose system beats a tight-one. While the former is less efficient, the latter requires numerous exceptions which still won’t prevent it from failing in unexpected ways. Small companies are sexy According to the U. S. Small Business Administration, small businesses represent 99.7 percent of all employer firms in the United States, employ half of all private-sector workers, have generated 64 percent of net new jobs over the past fifteen years, and create more than 50 percent of U.S. nonfarm gross domestic product (GDP).1 You don’t have to create next Amazon or Tesla to have huge positive impact. Businesses are not rocket science A business 1) provides something of value, that 2) other people want, 3) at a price they are willing to pay, 4) in a way that satisfies or exceeds their expectations, while 5) generating sufficient revenue. The milestone between a project and a business is first financially profitable transaction. Keep eye on the prize and get it as soon as possible. Product should satisfy one or more fundamental human drives The drives are the drive to Acquire, the drive to Bond, the drive to Learn, the drive to Defend, the drive to Feel.2 Clearly articulate how your product ties to one or more of these drives. Evaluate market potential of your idea On scale 0 to 10, score the following: 1) How badly do people want or need your product right now? 2) How many people are purchasing things like this already?, 3) What is the highest price consumers would pay for this?, 4) How much will it cost to acquire new customers, 5) How much does it cost to create and deliver your product?, 6) How unique is your offer? 7) How quickly can you start selling something?, 8) How much you have to invest before you can make and sell your product? 9) How easy it is to generate secondary sales from the primary product? (if you sell an enzyme, can you sell reagent kits or experiment kits with it as well?), 10) How much work does your product require to keep delivering value? (in-person training requires a lot, a prerecorded online programme requires none). Competition is a gift When deciding to enter to otherwise equal markets, enter the one with competition, that way you know there are consumers for your offering. The best way to learn how competitors deliver value is to become their customer. The best way to beat your rivals is to make them irrelevant. Don’t focus on competing, focus on making a killer product. Remember, in words of Paul Graham: “If in doubt, work on the product.” Some less obvious ways to create economic value Shared resource – lab space, a gym, …. Create and manage a durable asset that multiple parties use, and charge for access. An agency – literary and real estate agents, … Collect, manage, market and sell an asset or service on other people’s behalf, and collect a fee. Option – tickets, … Offer customers the possibility of taking some action in the future, at predefined prices, without obliging them to do so. In other words, charge for providing flexibility. Audience aggregation – mailing lists, social media, … Create community with certain set of characteristics. Get and keep their attention by providing something they value. Provide access to this community to third parties and charge for the access. The more obvious ways are: service, product, subscription, lease, loan, insurance, capital. Keep generating and sharing mock-ups and prototypes You are much more likely to get funded if you can show a demo or prototype. Sharing it with customers is the best way how to get feedback. These benefits significantly outweigh the risk of competition jumping on your idea. The quicker you generate new versions of demo’s and the quicker you collect feedback on them, the faster you will start delivering a product of value. Internal testing counts too! Use pre-orders and shadow-testing to gauge your product-market fit Are you working on a product and do you want to have reliable data on who is out there to buy it? Create opportunity to preorder or a mock-up website and collect information on people who commit to purchase. Beware: be honest and perfectly transparent about the current readiness of your offering. Make trade-offs Product can be convenient or it can be high-end. It can address a pain point immediately, or focus on something more subtle and deliver value over time. Rarely it will be able to do both equally well. You will thus need to make trade-offs, and that’s a good thing. Focus on trade-offs that maximize the strengths of your offering, and satisfy the needs of your customers. To find out the latter: ask them to make explicit A/B trade-offs for key characteristic of your offering. Once marketing your product, verbalize your offering’s major strength in a hook. Good hooks are one-liners such as “1000 songs in your pocket”, or “The 20-Minute Body”. The true marketing value of social media Ever wondered why the ads you are getting on Instagram are so interesting? That’s because they are tailored to yours truly. To use marketing budget effectively, target groups of prospects who are likely to be interested in your product already. This extends beyond social media: always choose smaller targeted campaign over a general one. Permission to follow-up is the second-best thing after a direct sale Your marketing campaign should have clear call to action. The primary objective is a sale. The second-best option is a follow up. Acquiring new prospects requires effort. It’s much easier to reach out to a contact who demonstrated interest earlier. Do so periodically, and absolutely do include former customers when doing so. When asking for permission to follow up, be super clear what customers should expect when they sign up (a weekly newsletter with one new productivity trick each week, etc …), and let customers explicitly state their interest in future purchase on sign-up (a pre-commitment strategy). Some tips for effective selling Listen to your customer, and understand what are their pain points and needs. Then demonstrate how your product addresses them (if it does). Point to competition if it does not. (Check this post for a good primer on sales.) Let your prospect imagine what a life with your product would be like. You can do this with demos, testers, or testimonials and other stories. The most effective testimonials describe customer satisfaction despite original scepticism. Offer genuine free value This is great way how to ask for permission to follow up, collect feedback, and allow your customer to image what a life with your product would be like. It also creates a reciprocal relationship, making your prospects more likely to buy from you in the future. Selling begins when prospects say no Selling is the process identifying and eliminating customers’ barriers to purchase. “It’s too expensive?” Focus on value your offering delivers. “It is not exactly what I am looking for?” Share testimonials and case studies. “It can wait?” Educate on the counterfactuals. To reduce frequency of no, offer risk reversal strategy (e.g. free returns). Don’t just meet your customer’s expectations, exceed them The perception of quality is performance minus expectations. Create performance that exceeds expectations by offering an unexpected benefit with your offer (a freebie, earlier delivery than advertised, …). Treat your value delivery process as an experiment The higher your throughput, the more customers you can serve. To increase your throughput focus on streamlining your value delivery process and eliminating any unnecessary steps. To be able to do this, you should deliberately outline your whole value stream, and measure how changes to its parts affect your throughput. Don’t focus on maximizing (short term) profit You, of course, must generate profit. But you will achieve better results by focusing on serving as many customers as possible while capturing modest value. While this reduces short term results, it will make your business much better situated for the long-term (that’s why Apple is not selling a $100’000 iPhone). You should reinvest most of revenue that your business generates into its growth for the same reason. It will compound your profits and after several years you will be in much better position than would have been the case otherwise. Before seeking funding decide on what enterprise you want to build An unicorn that races to IPO and leaves you wealthy at the exit? You will very likely need lot of external capital. A self-sufficient business that has you free to make your own decisions? Avoid external dilutive financing as much as possible. This will also make it easier to reinvest your profits (see above). If you do accept funding, use it solely to acquire things that will grow your revenue and that you could not afford otherwise. Understand your emotions around entrepreneurship Fears and anxieties stop us from doing things we wish to do. These mental patterns were designed to protect us from objectively bad things, such as being expelled from community or being eaten by predator. The world has dramatically changed since. Risks we are facing when following our (healthy and socially acceptable) dreams and passions are disproportionately smaller, yet they trigger the same levels of fear and arousal. Verbalize these fears by sharing them out loud with someone or writing them down. Imagine yourself pursing your goals and make mental note of what inner conflicts this triggers. Deconstruct these conflicts by asking yourself how significant they are in the real world. There is a good chance that doing so will leave you both more relaxed and motivated for pursuing your goals. Have a personal R&amp;amp;D budget In all the hustle and bustle of building and growing a business, you will have to keep in mind to put your wellbeing first. Assuming that is taken care of, you will also need to stay on top of the game in your field and as a manager. While you will learn a lot by doing, you can accelerate your growth by creating a personal R&amp;amp;D budget and spending it on anything that makes you more knowledgeable or productive. This includes classes, coaching, books, equipment and conferences. Keep teams small and elite Keep teams small. Studies have shown that the most effective group size is somewhere between three and eight people.3 Keep teams in this size to reduce communication overhead. Keep teams elite. In words of Paul English: “Any company can have only ten best people.” Focus on making this ten better than your competitors, and then capitalize on individuals’ strengths. You will beat your competition irrespective of their total size. Five tips for effective real-world management Recruit only as many people as you need to deliver in high quality. Have a clear vision and ambitious plan for achieving it. Revise the plan as you go. Treat people with respect and show appreciation for their effort. Provide your team with the best tools and don’t fraction their time with unnecessary meetings or distractions. Measure your performance and keep experimenting with process improvements. Any repeated task can benefit from automation Create checklists and SOPs to help both new and old employees to carry out tasks with more efficiency and less errors. Listen to your employees on what SOPs are needed. Steer clear of documents where effort to create and maintain them outweighs value they deliver. While automated systems reduce idiosyncratic errors, they can introduce systemic ones. Keep a finger on your processes’ pulse with unbiased and continuous sampling. Run stress tests Internally simulate what happens if you get 10x your daily visitor count, number of orders per week, a major recall, a major supplier goes out of business, etc…. Find ways how your value delivery chain fails in internal experiments, and safeguard against future real world crisis. You will learn that you should, as much as possible, avoid having a single point of failure (having one customer much larger than rest, single supplier of critical ingredient, etc …). Have fun As you read the above points, you probably noticed that they have you understanding yourself as a person, getting rid of self-defeating beliefs, carrying out experiments, working with bright and inspiring colleagues, all the while following your passion and making a positive change in the world. That’s a great career! So don’t forget to have fun and enjoy the ride. Footnotes www.sba.gov/advo/stats/sbfaq.pdf &amp;#8617; https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1878833.Driven &amp;#8617; https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67825.Peopleware &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter to 10 Years Younger Self</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/12/28/Letter10YoungerSelf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to 10 Years Younger Self" /><published>2023-12-28T08:13:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T08:13:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/12/28/Letter10YoungerSelf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/12/28/Letter10YoungerSelf.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/letter10years.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;letetr&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@alvaroserrano&quot;&gt;Alvaro Serrano&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, hi there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is me, I mean you, but from the future. I have been out and about collecting some experience in the past few years and now I am coming around to share it with you such as you don’t have to spend so much time wondering in the dark in the coming decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I even start, you have just turned 20 and started a university, moved cities started meeting lot of new people. It’s great. Or is it? I know how you are feeling, you don’t like the degree major and are thinking of switching programs. Well my advice is, do it and don’t look back. There is so much to do, so why dwell on things you are not really excited about, with people that are not really your bunch? I know you will argument about “loosing” a year, but don’t worry! If you are putting yourself in a place of higher satisfaction and curiosity, you can hardly call that a loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- This will be a common pattern: If you sense something is not quite right, if your body does not align with what your mind wants it to do, don’t downplay the corporal feeling. It is at least as important of a voice as that of your mind! --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be conscious about maintaining long-standing friendships. It’s great to meet new people especially if you either align with them very well or if they are very different from you. But in most cases, they are just as good as anyone else. Meeting them can become somewhat overwhelming and you can quickly loose touch with friends from your early phases of life. Well, that’s good for some, because trust me, some people you used to hang out with, were really not aiming upwards, but fair number is just all-right or even great, and they deserve much better than to be mostly buried under constant income of new acquaintances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memories and experiences are investments and travelling is one of the best way to collect them, so travel as much as you can afford. Saving money is good, but make travelling something you indulge on for the coming decade. I know, it seems difficult as the budget is tight but almost always there will be a room in it to travel. As soon as you are earning substantially more than to break even, just make it a rule to spend X% of it on exploring the world, and when I say world, I mean going outside of Europe. And yes, that means: take all the vacation you can! Nature beats cities but do get a mix of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In coming years, there will be several times when you are faced with having to decide which position or project to choose in your studies or for work. The best advice I can give: focus first on working with people you want to be around with, focus second on the environment, and only after project. The way of progress in any science project is uncertain and the outcomes are by far not predictable. You may think one approach is going to work only to try it dozen of times to no avail and having to divert. While you can learn a lot hustling and getting deep into the subject matter, you will learn much more from the people around you. A supervisor who truly cares about your success and is willing to work with you as you develop to define what it means at given time is worth their worth in gold. You will think it’s a weakness, before you find out it’s a strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second best advice I can give: Allow the decision to sink into your body, and decide which way to turn based on how you feel! If you experience fear or anxiety it is likely still a good idea to go ahead. If you experience sadness, that’s how you now it’s a bad idea! Don’t let your mind tell you otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow yourself to be loved. Whatever barriers you have built as protection that may have been necessary as you were growing up (and they, you can cut yourself some slack here, were) are not needed anymore. You will slowly deconstruct them over the decade, but you will keep tripping over them for a while. Instead of slowly chipping on them, seek to put yourself in positions where a bomb could explode in their vicinity (yes that means dare to be seen and to become vulnerable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok so far this was a lot of “do that” “don’t do that” type of talk, but you should not get overly stressed about. You are actually doing lot of things right already and this advice is mainly to help you move along this path bit faster. Over the decade you will develop strong connection with your feelings and emotions, and you will find ways how to listen to them and share them with others. You will actually become pretty good in the latter and it will allow you to connect quite profoundly with people who are open to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will also build a good connection with your own body. You will understand when and why it rejoices and when and why it hurts. You will learn to negotiate with it and care for it. You will learn to listen to it to get measure of your overall wellbeing. You will build a sustainable and varied fitness routine that will also aid your productivity. You will learn how to strain it to become stronger over time, without pushing it to overdrive or towards injury. Some of it you will learn alone, and some of it you will learn with others, and as you learn about others’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will learn to find satisfaction in doing hard things. You will work hard and you will do well thanks to it. You will make substantial contributions to other people’s work and make new contributions of your own. Numerous doors will open and you will build strong and supportive professional network. It won’t be always easy. It will take you a while to build a meaningful relationship with productivity – to perceive it not as an overly demanding boss and kind of an obsessive compulsion, but something you actually enjoy not only for the fruits of it, but also for the process. But you will get there, mostly, and that’s all you can ask for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh btw, yes you are allergic to histamine. And yes, do throw more parties!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What would you tell 10 year younger self? Drop me a hint in the comments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Photo by Alvaro Serrano on Unsplash. Hey, hi there, This is me, I mean you, but from the future. I have been out and about collecting some experience in the past few years and now I am coming around to share it with you such as you don’t have to spend so much time wondering in the dark in the coming decade. Where do I even start, you have just turned 20 and started a university, moved cities started meeting lot of new people. It’s great. Or is it? I know how you are feeling, you don’t like the degree major and are thinking of switching programs. Well my advice is, do it and don’t look back. There is so much to do, so why dwell on things you are not really excited about, with people that are not really your bunch? I know you will argument about “loosing” a year, but don’t worry! If you are putting yourself in a place of higher satisfaction and curiosity, you can hardly call that a loss. Be conscious about maintaining long-standing friendships. It’s great to meet new people especially if you either align with them very well or if they are very different from you. But in most cases, they are just as good as anyone else. Meeting them can become somewhat overwhelming and you can quickly loose touch with friends from your early phases of life. Well, that’s good for some, because trust me, some people you used to hang out with, were really not aiming upwards, but fair number is just all-right or even great, and they deserve much better than to be mostly buried under constant income of new acquaintances. Memories and experiences are investments and travelling is one of the best way to collect them, so travel as much as you can afford. Saving money is good, but make travelling something you indulge on for the coming decade. I know, it seems difficult as the budget is tight but almost always there will be a room in it to travel. As soon as you are earning substantially more than to break even, just make it a rule to spend X% of it on exploring the world, and when I say world, I mean going outside of Europe. And yes, that means: take all the vacation you can! Nature beats cities but do get a mix of both. In coming years, there will be several times when you are faced with having to decide which position or project to choose in your studies or for work. The best advice I can give: focus first on working with people you want to be around with, focus second on the environment, and only after project. The way of progress in any science project is uncertain and the outcomes are by far not predictable. You may think one approach is going to work only to try it dozen of times to no avail and having to divert. While you can learn a lot hustling and getting deep into the subject matter, you will learn much more from the people around you. A supervisor who truly cares about your success and is willing to work with you as you develop to define what it means at given time is worth their worth in gold. You will think it’s a weakness, before you find out it’s a strength. The second best advice I can give: Allow the decision to sink into your body, and decide which way to turn based on how you feel! If you experience fear or anxiety it is likely still a good idea to go ahead. If you experience sadness, that’s how you now it’s a bad idea! Don’t let your mind tell you otherwise. Allow yourself to be loved. Whatever barriers you have built as protection that may have been necessary as you were growing up (and they, you can cut yourself some slack here, were) are not needed anymore. You will slowly deconstruct them over the decade, but you will keep tripping over them for a while. Instead of slowly chipping on them, seek to put yourself in positions where a bomb could explode in their vicinity (yes that means dare to be seen and to become vulnerable). Ok so far this was a lot of “do that” “don’t do that” type of talk, but you should not get overly stressed about. You are actually doing lot of things right already and this advice is mainly to help you move along this path bit faster. Over the decade you will develop strong connection with your feelings and emotions, and you will find ways how to listen to them and share them with others. You will actually become pretty good in the latter and it will allow you to connect quite profoundly with people who are open to do the same. You will also build a good connection with your own body. You will understand when and why it rejoices and when and why it hurts. You will learn to negotiate with it and care for it. You will learn to listen to it to get measure of your overall wellbeing. You will build a sustainable and varied fitness routine that will also aid your productivity. You will learn how to strain it to become stronger over time, without pushing it to overdrive or towards injury. Some of it you will learn alone, and some of it you will learn with others, and as you learn about others’. You will learn to find satisfaction in doing hard things. You will work hard and you will do well thanks to it. You will make substantial contributions to other people’s work and make new contributions of your own. Numerous doors will open and you will build strong and supportive professional network. It won’t be always easy. It will take you a while to build a meaningful relationship with productivity – to perceive it not as an overly demanding boss and kind of an obsessive compulsion, but something you actually enjoy not only for the fruits of it, but also for the process. But you will get there, mostly, and that’s all you can ask for. Oh btw, yes you are allergic to histamine. And yes, do throw more parties! What would you tell 10 year younger self? Drop me a hint in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Essays That Challenged My Thinking This Year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Essays That Challenged My Thinking This Year" /><published>2023-12-22T17:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-22T17:53:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/literature/2023/12/22/FiveEssays.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/booksessays.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;essays&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@impatrickt&quot;&gt;Patrick Tomasso&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was the year when I started reading lot of essays. An essay is somewhat neglected writing form - it’s basically thinking laid bare, with an attempt to figure something out. The word essay itself comes from the French &lt;em&gt;essayer&lt;/em&gt; which means &lt;em&gt;to try&lt;/em&gt;. Now unless you are a philosophy geek, that does not sound terribly interesting. But wait, good essay happens to have one more important feature – it comes up with something surprising. Consequently, it is a (relatively) short form that reveals new ways to understand the world around you. Being a short form, it not only means you don’t have to deal with a whole book (and there is lot of them that waste 300+ pages to get one page worth of a point across), but also that authors who do not write books still can get a shot at expressing their thoughts through essays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read some twenty to thirty essays wide range of topics. Bellow I present the five that either felt the most relatable or challenged my exiting mental models the most. Dealing with topics as diverse as economic inequality, impostor syndrome, and transformational festivals, chances are you will love reading them too. So, without further ado, here are the five essays, with a favorite quote from each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-beyond-belief-erik-davis-2006&quot;&gt;5. Beyond Belief (Erik Davis, 2006)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably don’t have to remind you, we live in a consumerist society. That’s good and bad, but one aspect I became particularly frustrated about is that it puts us in a passive position where entertainment is being catered to us. Seems to not to be a problem, as our phones, computers, TVs and movie theaters are full with it, right? Well not quite, because I think it has important implications - disempowering most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that most of us would be much happier in society where everybody plays and active and recognizable role in entertaining the rest. This is something that probably worked quite naturally when communities consisted of 50 people seated around one campfire. &lt;a href=&quot;https://burningman.org/&quot;&gt;Burning Man&lt;/a&gt;, a countercultural transformational festival held annually in Black Rock Desert (Nevada, US), is an attempt at more participatory society, and much more than that. Any attempt to describe it will probably fall short, but Erik Davis at least does it with extreme literally skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“At its best, Burning Man twists authenticity and irony into a Möbius strip that never lets you know what side you’re on but always keeps you going. […] The specifically religious elements of the Burn are important not in themselves, but in relation to one another and to the less ethereal aspects of the festival: the carnality, the trash, the desert dust. This wider field of relations is not holistic but multiple: a promiscuous carnival of souls, a metaphysical flea-market, a demolition derby of reality constructs colliding in a parched void.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://techgnosis.com/beyond-belief-cults-of-burning-man/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-learning-the-elite-class-aella-2022&quot;&gt;4. Learning the Elite Class (Aella, 2022)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is ambitious will inevitably find themselves surrounded by smart people, more often than one would like this may end up in experiences of imposter syndrome. Written as a story of fetish-researcher at posh party &lt;em&gt;Learning the Elite Class&lt;/em&gt; is probably its best description I read this year (and maybe thus far).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The next person I talk to is a startup founder; she’s working on some company that aims to help crypto companies deal with the legal system. I don’t understand most of what she says, but it still feels familiar - I got into crypto early and was around the edges of the formation of the cryptosphere, and the basic culture isn’t arcane to me. I have vague background intuitions around what sorts of things are scams and aren’t, the ways crypto carries risk, the way the public views it. When she uses words like “community” in relation to crypto, it touches lightly into a web of other concepts, and I feel I understand the nuance and implications of it.  She tells me she’s doing a fundraising round and it’s looking promising; her team is building an app that’s going into beta next week and she is flying to a conference tomorrow morning and she was in calls all day earlier fixing an emergency with bank payments not going through to one of her contractors. Her life seems intense to me, and I don’t understand how she’s here at this party looking lively.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aella.substack.com/p/learning-the-elite-class&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-how-to-do-great-work-paul-graham-2023&quot;&gt;3. How to Do Great Work (Paul Graham, 2023)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham is a computer scientist, entrepreneur, and investor. He is not only a coder who made seminal contributions to the programming language Lisp, but perhaps more notably, he is one of the four founders of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ycombinator.com/&quot;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;. Y Combinator is probably the world most renown start up accelerator. It funded over 4’000 startups that now have combined valuation of 600 Billion USD. Companies that started through it include Airbnb, Codeacademy, Coinbase, Disqus, Dropbox, Reddit, Scribd, Stripe, and Twitch. In this essay, he distils advice on how to get great stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Take as much risk as you can afford.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/greatwork.html&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-becoming-a-magician-autotranslucencecom-2018&quot;&gt;2. Becoming a Magician (autotranslucence.com, 2018)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An essay on why going 10x improvements can be much better idea than 2x, at least where you really care. Illustrated on World Bodypainting Competition. Recommended for magicians, body-painters, and anyone who is less cerebral than Paul Graham (which is probably 99% of population).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t necessarily need to make nonlinear jumps in all aspects of our lives, particularly if (according to your values) making such a jump would require a sacrifice you don’t endorse. But for the things you care about most, or are causing you the most suffering, there is probably a nonlinear strategy that you will miss if you pay too close attention to the linear strategy you current have or that people recommend.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://autotranslucence.com/2018/03/30/becoming-a-magician/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-in-praise-of-idleness-bertrand-russell-1932&quot;&gt;1. In Praise of Idleness (Bertrand Russell, 1932)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bertrand Russell was a British mathematician and philosopher. He made seminal contributions to the field of logic, influencing the development of programming languages and design of computer systems. That it is more than almost anyone would attempt before claiming their right for peaceful retirement, but Bertrand Russel did not stop there, by far. Out of many other achievements, he is also the awardee oof 1950 Nobel Prize in Literature “in recognition of his varied and significant writings in which he champions humanitarian ideals and freedom of thought”. This is what his essay “In Praise of Idleness” is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In Praise of Idleness” is a literary gem - skillfully penned, it is an argument to stop glorifying work, and value leisure more. Reading it makes one wonder how did we make so little progress on it since he wrote it (and if he is self-reflecting, as his numerous achievements likely required that he tolled for most of his adult life, putting leisure into background).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for the others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://harpers.org/archive/1932/10/in-praise-of-idleness/&quot;&gt;Link to the essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find essays an intriguing writing form, I would highly suggest to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://readsomethingwonderful.com/&quot;&gt;readsomethingwonderful.com&lt;/a&gt; website. It does an amazing job in aggregating lot of great essay writing (but is somewhat computer science centric).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you read any of these essays? What have you thought about them? Or is there an essay you love and that is not on this list? Let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="literature" /><category term="essay" /><category term="literature" /><summary type="html">Photo by Patrick Tomasso on Unsplash. This year was the year when I started reading lot of essays. An essay is somewhat neglected writing form - it’s basically thinking laid bare, with an attempt to figure something out. The word essay itself comes from the French essayer which means to try. Now unless you are a philosophy geek, that does not sound terribly interesting. But wait, good essay happens to have one more important feature – it comes up with something surprising. Consequently, it is a (relatively) short form that reveals new ways to understand the world around you. Being a short form, it not only means you don’t have to deal with a whole book (and there is lot of them that waste 300+ pages to get one page worth of a point across), but also that authors who do not write books still can get a shot at expressing their thoughts through essays. I read some twenty to thirty essays wide range of topics. Bellow I present the five that either felt the most relatable or challenged my exiting mental models the most. Dealing with topics as diverse as economic inequality, impostor syndrome, and transformational festivals, chances are you will love reading them too. So, without further ado, here are the five essays, with a favorite quote from each: 5. Beyond Belief (Erik Davis, 2006) I probably don’t have to remind you, we live in a consumerist society. That’s good and bad, but one aspect I became particularly frustrated about is that it puts us in a passive position where entertainment is being catered to us. Seems to not to be a problem, as our phones, computers, TVs and movie theaters are full with it, right? Well not quite, because I think it has important implications - disempowering most of us. I am convinced that most of us would be much happier in society where everybody plays and active and recognizable role in entertaining the rest. This is something that probably worked quite naturally when communities consisted of 50 people seated around one campfire. Burning Man, a countercultural transformational festival held annually in Black Rock Desert (Nevada, US), is an attempt at more participatory society, and much more than that. Any attempt to describe it will probably fall short, but Erik Davis at least does it with extreme literally skill. “At its best, Burning Man twists authenticity and irony into a Möbius strip that never lets you know what side you’re on but always keeps you going. […] The specifically religious elements of the Burn are important not in themselves, but in relation to one another and to the less ethereal aspects of the festival: the carnality, the trash, the desert dust. This wider field of relations is not holistic but multiple: a promiscuous carnival of souls, a metaphysical flea-market, a demolition derby of reality constructs colliding in a parched void.” Link to the essay 4. Learning the Elite Class (Aella, 2022) Anyone who is ambitious will inevitably find themselves surrounded by smart people, more often than one would like this may end up in experiences of imposter syndrome. Written as a story of fetish-researcher at posh party Learning the Elite Class is probably its best description I read this year (and maybe thus far). “The next person I talk to is a startup founder; she’s working on some company that aims to help crypto companies deal with the legal system. I don’t understand most of what she says, but it still feels familiar - I got into crypto early and was around the edges of the formation of the cryptosphere, and the basic culture isn’t arcane to me. I have vague background intuitions around what sorts of things are scams and aren’t, the ways crypto carries risk, the way the public views it. When she uses words like “community” in relation to crypto, it touches lightly into a web of other concepts, and I feel I understand the nuance and implications of it. She tells me she’s doing a fundraising round and it’s looking promising; her team is building an app that’s going into beta next week and she is flying to a conference tomorrow morning and she was in calls all day earlier fixing an emergency with bank payments not going through to one of her contractors. Her life seems intense to me, and I don’t understand how she’s here at this party looking lively.” Link to the essay 3. How to Do Great Work (Paul Graham, 2023) Paul Graham is a computer scientist, entrepreneur, and investor. He is not only a coder who made seminal contributions to the programming language Lisp, but perhaps more notably, he is one of the four founders of Y Combinator. Y Combinator is probably the world most renown start up accelerator. It funded over 4’000 startups that now have combined valuation of 600 Billion USD. Companies that started through it include Airbnb, Codeacademy, Coinbase, Disqus, Dropbox, Reddit, Scribd, Stripe, and Twitch. In this essay, he distils advice on how to get great stuff done. “Take as much risk as you can afford.” Link to the essay 2. Becoming a Magician (autotranslucence.com, 2018) An essay on why going 10x improvements can be much better idea than 2x, at least where you really care. Illustrated on World Bodypainting Competition. Recommended for magicians, body-painters, and anyone who is less cerebral than Paul Graham (which is probably 99% of population). “We don’t necessarily need to make nonlinear jumps in all aspects of our lives, particularly if (according to your values) making such a jump would require a sacrifice you don’t endorse. But for the things you care about most, or are causing you the most suffering, there is probably a nonlinear strategy that you will miss if you pay too close attention to the linear strategy you current have or that people recommend.” Link to the essay 1. In Praise of Idleness (Bertrand Russell, 1932) Bertrand Russell was a British mathematician and philosopher. He made seminal contributions to the field of logic, influencing the development of programming languages and design of computer systems. That it is more than almost anyone would attempt before claiming their right for peaceful retirement, but Bertrand Russel did not stop there, by far. Out of many other achievements, he is also the awardee oof 1950 Nobel Prize in Literature “in recognition of his varied and significant writings in which he champions humanitarian ideals and freedom of thought”. This is what his essay “In Praise of Idleness” is about. “In Praise of Idleness” is a literary gem - skillfully penned, it is an argument to stop glorifying work, and value leisure more. Reading it makes one wonder how did we make so little progress on it since he wrote it (and if he is self-reflecting, as his numerous achievements likely required that he tolled for most of his adult life, putting leisure into background). “Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for the others.” Link to the essay If you find essays an intriguing writing form, I would highly suggest to check out the readsomethingwonderful.com website. It does an amazing job in aggregating lot of great essay writing (but is somewhat computer science centric). Have you read any of these essays? What have you thought about them? Or is there an essay you love and that is not on this list? Let me know in the comments!</summary></entry></feed>