<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-06T09:49:06+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Martin Holub Blog</title><subtitle>Personal Blog</subtitle><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><entry><title type="html">Prioritizing the Right Type of Rest May Be the Best Biohack. Here Is Why.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prioritizing the Right Type of Rest May Be the Best Biohack. Here Is Why." /><published>2023-12-06T08:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-06T08:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2023/12/06/DeepRest.html">&lt;p&gt;Kate woke up early, knowing she had a packed day ahead of her. She went through her morning routine assuredly and quickly. As usual, she brewed her favorite ginger-mint tea, this time with an extra drop of honey as if it could give her the extra energy, she felt she lacked after a poor night’s sleep. While waiting for the tea to cool down a bit, she quickly typed few supportive messages to her college best friend … her mother has recently gotten quite ill and the friend struggles to cope. Pity they cannot meet up she thought, by now they became geographically too separated. Before brushing her teeth, she put on music in the bathroom, her favorite singer just put out a new album and it’s really good. On her way out she passes by the bedroom to kiss her lover goodbye, and out she goes. No breakfast, that she will have to grab on her way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/trainwoman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Photo by Jeffrey Czum on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/time-lapse-photography-of-person-standing-near-train-2120010/&quot;&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things go well for her at the office. The presentation she was nervous about runs well and she receives positive feedback from her supervisors, so the extra hours she has been putting in apparently have paid off. Some more meetings, a bit of editing work on a report she is finishing, a coffee break with coworkers. On the way home she stops by her favorite yoga studio as a small reward for the day. Finally, home, hungry as she had just a sandwich for lunch. The fridge is quite empty, and by now she is not in the mood for doing groceries, so it will be dinner delivery, maybe tacos? She finishes them while lounging on the sofa, rewatching one of her favorite shows while also texting her mum about the day she had, and looking up tickets for a concert that is coming up in her favorite club next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;busy-ness-has-become-the-default-condition&quot;&gt;Busy-ness has become the default condition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like an average day, doesn’t it? It even sounds quite nice. In many ways probably akin to your average day. If someone asked Kate, how is she doing, how likely do you think her answer would include the word ‘busy’ in it? Probably quite likely, and not dissimilar to how would you have replied. 
‘How are you’ is a standard question we get, but how about the following ones: Do you think Kate likes being busy? Do you think ‘busyness’ works for her? Do you think she is getting enough rest and in the right form? These are quite simple questions, and the answers to them are not that difficult to guess, but strangely enough, we rarely raise them with our friends, or ourselves for that matter. So, in this post I want to ask them: &lt;strong&gt;Do you like being busy? Are you getting an adequate amount of rest?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has become the semi-default that we stopped questioning. Most of us lead busy lives. Maybe it’s the price we must pay to be financially comfortable? And why not actually? Many of us (including me) like it (maybe bit too much). But the moment you really let the question of whether you like being busy or not sink in, something changes. Because the chances are, you don’t. And even if you do like it, not all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;not-all-rest-is-made-equal&quot;&gt;Not all rest is made equal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of us will probably be able to say that they are getting some rest during an average week, few will have a sense of whether it is enough or not. I certainly did not, until recently when I was prompted to think about times when I felt really relaxed. The middle-of-vacation falling asleep on a beach type of relaxed. Or when you have done a good yoga session and just sink down to savasana that you don’t want to end. You probably can think of similar experiences when obligations temporarily vanished from your horizon and your body melted as well. So sure, I have memories of feeling super relaxed, but when was the last time I got a chance to feel like it? It must be a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, &lt;strong&gt;most of us are not getting enough rest&lt;/strong&gt;. Partially because we don’t get enough time in our busy lives for it, but &lt;strong&gt;mainly because we are not prioritizing the right type of rest&lt;/strong&gt;. In her recent book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/60750102-the-stress-prescription&quot;&gt;The Stress Prescription&lt;/a&gt;, Elissa Epel defines four different mind states as they relate to stress, red mind (acute stress), yellow (baseline cognitive load), green mind (rest), blue mind (deep rest). We spend most of our days in the &lt;strong&gt;yellow zone&lt;/strong&gt;. Not only at work, but also most of the time around it, when our mind is processing obligations, making plans, engaging in socially, or just plain scrolling or browsing on our devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rest_stress_illustration.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Stress and rest scale illustration.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;strong&gt;red zone&lt;/strong&gt; looks down-right undesirable, it actually is a place we should &lt;strong&gt;actively seek out&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s healthy to engage in activities that get you there for a limited period of time, provided they are self-inflicted (HIIT, cold and heat exposure, hyperventilation, …) as these &lt;strong&gt;mount up your general stress resilience&lt;/strong&gt; on a long run. 
&lt;strong&gt;Green mind&lt;/strong&gt; is what we commonly associate with rest. It’s a pleasant state of relaxation when we are fully engaged in leisure activities. It’s a state when you are just being, not being asked to do something. This is facilitated by &lt;strong&gt;observation and engagement in a single task&lt;/strong&gt; (so no multitasking). Think of being in nature or watching a performance. Watching a show on your TV at home would fit here as well, as long as you are fully immersed and don’t have your attention to repeatedly drift to your phone, the fridge, or some responsibilities coming up (which is unlikely - it’s easier to reach this state of mind in a theater or cinema, as your mind associates these places with the single task of observing art). Engaging in sports is an area that is ambiguous. At times you will be in the yellow or even red zones, at brief times in the green one. If you feel you are fully engaged (i.e. in a state of ‘flow’) you are probably in the green zone. It’s also something that has large learned factor to it – if you have been performing this sport or playing this game for some time already, such that you feel some sense of mastery doing it, the time you spend it the green zone will likely be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how about the &lt;strong&gt;blue zone&lt;/strong&gt;? It turns out that one is both &lt;strong&gt;vital for restoration, and barely visited by most during wake time&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s a state of rest that occurs when we are in a quiet and safe environment, typically physically secluded, focusing on just one thing (e.g. our breath) or having attention openly drifting. This type of rest occurs during a deep sleep (and that also why it’s important to get enough sleep!) and during mind mind-body practices such as meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-enough-deep-rest-is-vital-for-health-and-wellbeing&quot;&gt;Getting enough deep rest is vital for health and wellbeing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I learnt about this, I tried looking at my daily activities through the red-yellow-green-blue lens and realized that I am by far not prioritizing rest the way I thought I am, or nearly as much. Chances are you will feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should you care? Is this anyhow a big deal? Well it kind of is. Researchers have looked at various ways people achieve deep rest (i.e., blue state of mind). In one study, they had people meditate for 20 minutes daily, and meet with a coach weekly. This not only left the people feeling better, but &lt;strong&gt;resulted in positive gene expression changes related to energy metabolism, insulin secretion, telomere maintenance, and inflammation&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0062817&quot;&gt;Bhasin et al., 2013&lt;/a&gt;). In another study, people were invited to join 6-day long meditation retreat and, again, left not only feeling better but also reporting similar health benefits on the gene expression level. This effect applied even to a control group, that just spent 6-day of free time, without meditation (something the researchers called the ‘vacation effect’), and was further strengthen in those who meditated and were accustomed to the meditation practice (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/tp2016164&quot;&gt;Epel et al., 2016&lt;/a&gt;). As it turns out, &lt;strong&gt;restorative rest is a powerful modulator of our health and biology&lt;/strong&gt;. Evidence suggests that &lt;strong&gt;not leaving time and space for it can lead to disease and faster the progression of aging&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on the face of it we do have enough time for leisure, and many would use it to also engage in it, we rarely see it as an opportunity to get deeply immersed in something. In fact, lot of things we would do in our leisure time, such as engaging in sports, catching up with friends, browsing the internet, are just the yellow time creeping in into our green and blue zones. Don’t get me wrong, these are important and fun, but we should not allow them to take up all our leisure time. We &lt;strong&gt;must protect our time and capacity to engage if fully restorative rest&lt;/strong&gt;, to enter, and stay in, the green and blue states of mind. In terms of &lt;strong&gt;return on investment, it may be one of the best things to do for our health and wellbeing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more thorough write-up on deep rest, check the article &lt;em&gt;Deep Rest: An Integrative Model of How Contemplative Practices Combat Stress and Enhance the Body’s Restorative Capacity&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://psyarxiv.com/bkg3j/download?format=pdf&quot;&gt;psyarxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="health" /><category term="health" /><category term="science" /><category term="mind" /><summary type="html">Kate woke up early, knowing she had a packed day ahead of her. She went through her morning routine assuredly and quickly. As usual, she brewed her favorite ginger-mint tea, this time with an extra drop of honey as if it could give her the extra energy, she felt she lacked after a poor night’s sleep. While waiting for the tea to cool down a bit, she quickly typed few supportive messages to her college best friend … her mother has recently gotten quite ill and the friend struggles to cope. Pity they cannot meet up she thought, by now they became geographically too separated. Before brushing her teeth, she put on music in the bathroom, her favorite singer just put out a new album and it’s really good. On her way out she passes by the bedroom to kiss her lover goodbye, and out she goes. No breakfast, that she will have to grab on her way. Photo by Jeffrey Czum on Pexels. Things go well for her at the office. The presentation she was nervous about runs well and she receives positive feedback from her supervisors, so the extra hours she has been putting in apparently have paid off. Some more meetings, a bit of editing work on a report she is finishing, a coffee break with coworkers. On the way home she stops by her favorite yoga studio as a small reward for the day. Finally, home, hungry as she had just a sandwich for lunch. The fridge is quite empty, and by now she is not in the mood for doing groceries, so it will be dinner delivery, maybe tacos? She finishes them while lounging on the sofa, rewatching one of her favorite shows while also texting her mum about the day she had, and looking up tickets for a concert that is coming up in her favorite club next month. Busy-ness has become the default condition This looks like an average day, doesn’t it? It even sounds quite nice. In many ways probably akin to your average day. If someone asked Kate, how is she doing, how likely do you think her answer would include the word ‘busy’ in it? Probably quite likely, and not dissimilar to how would you have replied. ‘How are you’ is a standard question we get, but how about the following ones: Do you think Kate likes being busy? Do you think ‘busyness’ works for her? Do you think she is getting enough rest and in the right form? These are quite simple questions, and the answers to them are not that difficult to guess, but strangely enough, we rarely raise them with our friends, or ourselves for that matter. So, in this post I want to ask them: Do you like being busy? Are you getting an adequate amount of rest? It has become the semi-default that we stopped questioning. Most of us lead busy lives. Maybe it’s the price we must pay to be financially comfortable? And why not actually? Many of us (including me) like it (maybe bit too much). But the moment you really let the question of whether you like being busy or not sink in, something changes. Because the chances are, you don’t. And even if you do like it, not all the time. Not all rest is made equal While most of us will probably be able to say that they are getting some rest during an average week, few will have a sense of whether it is enough or not. I certainly did not, until recently when I was prompted to think about times when I felt really relaxed. The middle-of-vacation falling asleep on a beach type of relaxed. Or when you have done a good yoga session and just sink down to savasana that you don’t want to end. You probably can think of similar experiences when obligations temporarily vanished from your horizon and your body melted as well. So sure, I have memories of feeling super relaxed, but when was the last time I got a chance to feel like it? It must be a while. As it turns out, most of us are not getting enough rest. Partially because we don’t get enough time in our busy lives for it, but mainly because we are not prioritizing the right type of rest. In her recent book, The Stress Prescription, Elissa Epel defines four different mind states as they relate to stress, red mind (acute stress), yellow (baseline cognitive load), green mind (rest), blue mind (deep rest). We spend most of our days in the yellow zone. Not only at work, but also most of the time around it, when our mind is processing obligations, making plans, engaging in socially, or just plain scrolling or browsing on our devices. Stress and rest scale illustration. While the red zone looks down-right undesirable, it actually is a place we should actively seek out. It’s healthy to engage in activities that get you there for a limited period of time, provided they are self-inflicted (HIIT, cold and heat exposure, hyperventilation, …) as these mount up your general stress resilience on a long run. Green mind is what we commonly associate with rest. It’s a pleasant state of relaxation when we are fully engaged in leisure activities. It’s a state when you are just being, not being asked to do something. This is facilitated by observation and engagement in a single task (so no multitasking). Think of being in nature or watching a performance. Watching a show on your TV at home would fit here as well, as long as you are fully immersed and don’t have your attention to repeatedly drift to your phone, the fridge, or some responsibilities coming up (which is unlikely - it’s easier to reach this state of mind in a theater or cinema, as your mind associates these places with the single task of observing art). Engaging in sports is an area that is ambiguous. At times you will be in the yellow or even red zones, at brief times in the green one. If you feel you are fully engaged (i.e. in a state of ‘flow’) you are probably in the green zone. It’s also something that has large learned factor to it – if you have been performing this sport or playing this game for some time already, such that you feel some sense of mastery doing it, the time you spend it the green zone will likely be higher. And how about the blue zone? It turns out that one is both vital for restoration, and barely visited by most during wake time. It’s a state of rest that occurs when we are in a quiet and safe environment, typically physically secluded, focusing on just one thing (e.g. our breath) or having attention openly drifting. This type of rest occurs during a deep sleep (and that also why it’s important to get enough sleep!) and during mind mind-body practices such as meditation. Getting enough deep rest is vital for health and wellbeing After I learnt about this, I tried looking at my daily activities through the red-yellow-green-blue lens and realized that I am by far not prioritizing rest the way I thought I am, or nearly as much. Chances are you will feel the same. Should you care? Is this anyhow a big deal? Well it kind of is. Researchers have looked at various ways people achieve deep rest (i.e., blue state of mind). In one study, they had people meditate for 20 minutes daily, and meet with a coach weekly. This not only left the people feeling better, but resulted in positive gene expression changes related to energy metabolism, insulin secretion, telomere maintenance, and inflammation (Bhasin et al., 2013). In another study, people were invited to join 6-day long meditation retreat and, again, left not only feeling better but also reporting similar health benefits on the gene expression level. This effect applied even to a control group, that just spent 6-day of free time, without meditation (something the researchers called the ‘vacation effect’), and was further strengthen in those who meditated and were accustomed to the meditation practice (Epel et al., 2016). As it turns out, restorative rest is a powerful modulator of our health and biology. Evidence suggests that not leaving time and space for it can lead to disease and faster the progression of aging. While on the face of it we do have enough time for leisure, and many would use it to also engage in it, we rarely see it as an opportunity to get deeply immersed in something. In fact, lot of things we would do in our leisure time, such as engaging in sports, catching up with friends, browsing the internet, are just the yellow time creeping in into our green and blue zones. Don’t get me wrong, these are important and fun, but we should not allow them to take up all our leisure time. We must protect our time and capacity to engage if fully restorative rest, to enter, and stay in, the green and blue states of mind. In terms of return on investment, it may be one of the best things to do for our health and wellbeing. References For more thorough write-up on deep rest, check the article Deep Rest: An Integrative Model of How Contemplative Practices Combat Stress and Enhance the Body’s Restorative Capacity on psyarxiv.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Clean Indoor Air Manifesto</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clean Indoor Air Manifesto" /><published>2023-12-02T11:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-02T11:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/12/02/IndoorAirManifesto.html">&lt;p&gt;Humans spend 90% or more of their time indoors. 90%, that’s more than some species of whale spend underwater. Spending most time indoors means breathing mainly indoor air, and it thus goes that its quality has important impact on our health. Most of us care about what we eat and drink, yet we rarely question the quality of air we breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While standards exist for quality of indoor air, they are mostly limited to concentrations of pollutants and temperature. There are limited and rare regulations for concentration of CO2 (levels of which are even more rarely measured) and virtually no regulations on concentrations of airborne pathogens. That’s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;indoor-co2-and-aerosols&quot;&gt;Indoor CO2 and aerosols&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CO2 levels affect our immediate cognitive ability. In areas with low CO2, cognitive test scores have been reported &lt;a href=&quot;https://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/doi/10.1289/ehp.1510037&quot;&gt;61% higher than in areas with relatively high CO2&lt;/a&gt;. Mind you, this study designated ‘high CO2’ as a level just half of what has &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/ina.12403&quot;&gt;another study&lt;/a&gt; found to be a common level in classrooms!
Poor air quality not only makes us dumb, it also makes us sick. Indoor airborne transmission is the major route of spread for the most common viruses such as influenza, and now SARS-CoV-2 as well. And not only directly from someone coughing at us, but also from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.abd9149&quot;&gt;breathing indoor air&lt;/a&gt; where they remain suspended in the air for extended amount of time as aerosols. &lt;a href=&quot;https://raeng.org.uk/media/fupdixju/nera-social-cost-benefit-analysis.pdf&quot;&gt;One study estimated&lt;/a&gt; that half of all infections happen in just 5% of all indoor areas, high occupancy public buildings such as airports, schools, gyms, exhibition halls, theaters, music venues, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ventilation-is-helpful-but-not-sufficient&quot;&gt;Ventilation is helpful, but not sufficient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot, and should not, opt out of indoors. This is most of where we work, socialize, meet our needs, and enjoy conveniences. We, therefore, must ventilate and sterilize the indoor air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Ventilate?’, you say, ‘aren’t we doing it already?’ We are, but very very poorly. The high occupancy areas described above tend to have ventilation with air exchange per hour (ACH, a common way how to quantify the rate of ventilation in an indoor environment) of 1 or 2. At this rate, it will take hours before airborne contaminant concentration is reduced by 99.9%. That’s incredibly slow. For comparison, at ACH 6 it is still pretty slow and will take over an hour for the same reduction. As another point of reference, pharmaceutical manufacturing spaces, where environmental quality is very important for the manufacturing process, often require &lt;strong&gt;several hundreds (!) of ACH&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, we have a long way to go before significantly improving the quality of our indoor environments. Technologically, we are not even quite there yet. While ventilation with very high ACH is possible, it needs to be designed for at construction (something that is not possible in existing buildings), requires high energy input and frequent maintenance, and may actually not be pleasant for building occupants (e.g., due to noise and air streams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;far-uvc-inactivates-airborne-pathogens&quot;&gt;Far-UVC inactivates airborne pathogens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an early-stage alternative that holds a lot of promise: far UVC. Far UVC, is light at the high energy spectrum. With wavelength of ~220 nm it does not penetrate human skin or retina, but being UV it does kill microorganisms including viruses, bacteria and fungi. Early scientific studies showed that it can efficiently sterilize indoor air and surfaces (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-67211-2&quot;&gt;Buonanno, 2020&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-022-08462-z&quot;&gt;Eadie, 2022&lt;/a&gt;). It can deliver &lt;strong&gt;50-100-fold improvement over current ventilation systems&lt;/strong&gt; in terms of relative air exchange (ACHe) and could also be mounted in already existing buildings. Bringing manufacturing costs down, as well as carrying out epidemiological studies needs to be done before large scale deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plants-have-many-qualities-but-air-purification-is-not-one-of-them-yet&quot;&gt;Plants have many qualities, but air-purification is not one of them (yet)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UVC seems great, but you must be wondering how about good old plants – aren’t they also cleaning the air? Can’t we just have more plants everywhere? I would love that as well, so I looked into it. It turns out that the only thing plants can do reasonably well is regulating indoor humidity. When it comes to CO2 removal, &lt;strong&gt;plants sequester only negligible amount of the indoor CO2&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-08-088504-9.00325-1&quot;&gt;Llewellyn and Dixon, 2011&lt;/a&gt;). This is because they need just a tiny amount of it for photosynthesis. Moreover, &lt;strong&gt;some potted plant systems are even net positive CO2 emitters&lt;/strong&gt; due to the composition of substrate in the pot (!). Finally, even if plants would photosynthesize like crazy, they would still only deal with CO2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not ready to give up on plants. Being a synthetic biologist, I am aware that there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erz029&quot;&gt;efforts to engineer plants for higher CO2 sequestration rates&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, their &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tibtech.2018.10.008&quot;&gt;microbial symbions can be engineered to do the same&lt;/a&gt;. There are also &lt;a href=&quot;https://neoplants.com/&quot;&gt;startups that engineer plants to remove pollutants from the indoor air&lt;/a&gt;. I remain a plant-optimist. When coupled together with building design that brings in more light and improves passive indoor ventilation, I believe plants will have a small but important role to play in improving the quality of indoor air in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;become-an-indoor-clean-air-activist&quot;&gt;Become an indoor clean air activist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can you do while waiting for UVC to hit the mass market and synthetic biologists to engineer more plants? You can certainly use the information you saw here to remind yourself to &lt;strong&gt;ventilate your indoor spaces frequently&lt;/strong&gt;. I would also &lt;strong&gt;get a CO2 meter and measure the ambient concentration in spaces where you spend the most time&lt;/strong&gt; (at home in your living room and bedroom, at the office). When &lt;strong&gt;you walk into a crowded space&lt;/strong&gt;, be proactive and &lt;strong&gt;ask for it to be better ventilated&lt;/strong&gt; if you can. If you are maybe feeling slightly sick, like your immunity may not be in the best shape that day, &lt;strong&gt;consider skipping that party or concert that you know will be crowded and poorly ventilated&lt;/strong&gt; – the chances that you catch an airborne virus are quite high, and that may not be worth it. If you are an employer, &lt;strong&gt;ask your employees about the indoor environment and whether they recall getting sick while at the office&lt;/strong&gt;, especially if you implement some changes (occupancy, ventilation, …) or move offices. &lt;strong&gt;Show your love for local businesses that make the effort to create a nice indoor environment&lt;/strong&gt;. If you consistently notice the place has fresh air, is well ventilated, is not overbooked, and maybe even uses UVC (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wgbh.org/news/local/2022-07-06/with-ultraviolet-protection-one-boston-cabaret-may-be-safer-from-covid-19-than-almost-anywhere&quot;&gt;this bar in Boston&lt;/a&gt;) – thank the owners and spread the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take a while but together, we will make indoor spaces healthier environments for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/indoor-air-quality/&quot;&gt;a great article&lt;/a&gt; by Juan Cambeiro and Brian Potter over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/&quot;&gt;Institute for Progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="health" /><category term="biosecurity" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html">Humans spend 90% or more of their time indoors. 90%, that’s more than some species of whale spend underwater. Spending most time indoors means breathing mainly indoor air, and it thus goes that its quality has important impact on our health. Most of us care about what we eat and drink, yet we rarely question the quality of air we breathe. While standards exist for quality of indoor air, they are mostly limited to concentrations of pollutants and temperature. There are limited and rare regulations for concentration of CO2 (levels of which are even more rarely measured) and virtually no regulations on concentrations of airborne pathogens. That’s not enough. Indoor CO2 and aerosols CO2 levels affect our immediate cognitive ability. In areas with low CO2, cognitive test scores have been reported 61% higher than in areas with relatively high CO2. Mind you, this study designated ‘high CO2’ as a level just half of what has another study found to be a common level in classrooms! Poor air quality not only makes us dumb, it also makes us sick. Indoor airborne transmission is the major route of spread for the most common viruses such as influenza, and now SARS-CoV-2 as well. And not only directly from someone coughing at us, but also from breathing indoor air where they remain suspended in the air for extended amount of time as aerosols. One study estimated that half of all infections happen in just 5% of all indoor areas, high occupancy public buildings such as airports, schools, gyms, exhibition halls, theaters, music venues, etc. Ventilation is helpful, but not sufficient We cannot, and should not, opt out of indoors. This is most of where we work, socialize, meet our needs, and enjoy conveniences. We, therefore, must ventilate and sterilize the indoor air. ‘Ventilate?’, you say, ‘aren’t we doing it already?’ We are, but very very poorly. The high occupancy areas described above tend to have ventilation with air exchange per hour (ACH, a common way how to quantify the rate of ventilation in an indoor environment) of 1 or 2. At this rate, it will take hours before airborne contaminant concentration is reduced by 99.9%. That’s incredibly slow. For comparison, at ACH 6 it is still pretty slow and will take over an hour for the same reduction. As another point of reference, pharmaceutical manufacturing spaces, where environmental quality is very important for the manufacturing process, often require several hundreds (!) of ACH. Clearly, we have a long way to go before significantly improving the quality of our indoor environments. Technologically, we are not even quite there yet. While ventilation with very high ACH is possible, it needs to be designed for at construction (something that is not possible in existing buildings), requires high energy input and frequent maintenance, and may actually not be pleasant for building occupants (e.g., due to noise and air streams). Far-UVC inactivates airborne pathogens There is an early-stage alternative that holds a lot of promise: far UVC. Far UVC, is light at the high energy spectrum. With wavelength of ~220 nm it does not penetrate human skin or retina, but being UV it does kill microorganisms including viruses, bacteria and fungi. Early scientific studies showed that it can efficiently sterilize indoor air and surfaces (Buonanno, 2020 and Eadie, 2022). It can deliver 50-100-fold improvement over current ventilation systems in terms of relative air exchange (ACHe) and could also be mounted in already existing buildings. Bringing manufacturing costs down, as well as carrying out epidemiological studies needs to be done before large scale deployment. Plants have many qualities, but air-purification is not one of them (yet) UVC seems great, but you must be wondering how about good old plants – aren’t they also cleaning the air? Can’t we just have more plants everywhere? I would love that as well, so I looked into it. It turns out that the only thing plants can do reasonably well is regulating indoor humidity. When it comes to CO2 removal, plants sequester only negligible amount of the indoor CO2 (Llewellyn and Dixon, 2011). This is because they need just a tiny amount of it for photosynthesis. Moreover, some potted plant systems are even net positive CO2 emitters due to the composition of substrate in the pot (!). Finally, even if plants would photosynthesize like crazy, they would still only deal with CO2. I am not ready to give up on plants. Being a synthetic biologist, I am aware that there are efforts to engineer plants for higher CO2 sequestration rates. Similarly, their microbial symbions can be engineered to do the same. There are also startups that engineer plants to remove pollutants from the indoor air. I remain a plant-optimist. When coupled together with building design that brings in more light and improves passive indoor ventilation, I believe plants will have a small but important role to play in improving the quality of indoor air in the future. Become an indoor clean air activist So what can you do while waiting for UVC to hit the mass market and synthetic biologists to engineer more plants? You can certainly use the information you saw here to remind yourself to ventilate your indoor spaces frequently. I would also get a CO2 meter and measure the ambient concentration in spaces where you spend the most time (at home in your living room and bedroom, at the office). When you walk into a crowded space, be proactive and ask for it to be better ventilated if you can. If you are maybe feeling slightly sick, like your immunity may not be in the best shape that day, consider skipping that party or concert that you know will be crowded and poorly ventilated – the chances that you catch an airborne virus are quite high, and that may not be worth it. If you are an employer, ask your employees about the indoor environment and whether they recall getting sick while at the office, especially if you implement some changes (occupancy, ventilation, …) or move offices. Show your love for local businesses that make the effort to create a nice indoor environment. If you consistently notice the place has fresh air, is well ventilated, is not overbooked, and maybe even uses UVC (such as this bar in Boston) – thank the owners and spread the word. It will take a while but together, we will make indoor spaces healthier environments for everyone. This post was inspired by a great article by Juan Cambeiro and Brian Potter over at Institute for Progress.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Holiday Season, I Choose To Be Grateful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Holiday Season, I Choose To Be Grateful" /><published>2023-11-26T12:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-26T12:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2023/11/26/23GratitudeSeason.html">&lt;p&gt;The holiday season is coming, and the cultural message is that we need to host amazing dinner parties and buy expensive and well-thought-out gifts. While that certainly won’t hurt, it takes the attention away from why we are doing this in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this holiday season, I am deciding to focus on something that actually matters to me, namely on expressing gratitude and appreciation to people that touched my life this year. I am going to make this really easy. Imagine an advent calendar (a sort of bonbonniere where children and adults alike eat one piece of chocolate for each day in December before Christmas Eve), but in inverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/adventcalendar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
A photo of an advent calendar by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@miracleday?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&quot;&gt;Elena Mozhvilo&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each day in December, I will spend five to ten minutes thinking about an experience that happened this year, that someone enabled and/or touched my life during. I will then &lt;strong&gt;write down a thank-you note&lt;/strong&gt; where I specifically describe &lt;strong&gt;how this person affected me at that moment and in the time that followed, what I learnt from them and the experience, how I remember their efforts and why I am grateful.&lt;/strong&gt; I will &lt;strong&gt;write this by hand, using complete sentences&lt;/strong&gt;. If I still have their contact, I will &lt;strong&gt;share this note with them*, either direclty as handwriting, the photo therof, or as a typed message&lt;/strong&gt;. Finally, I will crumple up the note and put it in a glass jar. At the end of the month, the jar will contain some twenty to thirty gratitude notes. I guess you could call it the emotional equivalent of a piggy bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, this sounds like a good idea. For sure it’s a nice gift to give to someone and the other person will appreciate it. As I am writing this down, I am already super excited about reconnecting with my friends and others and sharing how they impacted my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it goes quite a bit further, it is also a fantastic gift for oneself. There is lot of scientific literature to attest that gratitude practice is an extremely effective way to improve one’s mental and physical health. It encourages the savoring of positive life experiences and strengthens socials bonds. There is host of physiological benefits that have been reported in literature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-reported physical health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engagement in healthy and prosocial activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Willingness to ask for help and advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More feelings of happiness, pride, and hope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater feeling of social connection, strengthening of intimate bonds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduction in risk for depression, anxiety, and substance abuse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved biomarker profile for cardiovascular disease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvement of sleep and energy levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress and illness resilience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holiday season, I choose to be grateful. Will you join me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-resources&quot;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.va.gov/WHOLEHEALTHLIBRARY/tools/creating-gratitude-practice.asp&quot;&gt;Creating a Gratitude Practice&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This document contains further rationale for estabilishing a gratitude practice, as well as more detailed instructions on how to implement it. It has multiple references for the health benefits described above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ZizdB0TgAVM?si=Lms7EVbikBXPU1PH&amp;amp;t=1922&quot;&gt;Dr. Laurie Santos on the importance of gratitude&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This part of Laurie Santos’s talk highlights the importance of gratitude practice, and how sharing it with others is beneficial for both the one sharing, as well as the one receving it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="mental-health" /><category term="mental-health" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">The holiday season is coming, and the cultural message is that we need to host amazing dinner parties and buy expensive and well-thought-out gifts. While that certainly won’t hurt, it takes the attention away from why we are doing this in the first place. For this holiday season, I am deciding to focus on something that actually matters to me, namely on expressing gratitude and appreciation to people that touched my life this year. I am going to make this really easy. Imagine an advent calendar (a sort of bonbonniere where children and adults alike eat one piece of chocolate for each day in December before Christmas Eve), but in inverse. A photo of an advent calendar by Elena Mozhvilo on Unsplash. Each day in December, I will spend five to ten minutes thinking about an experience that happened this year, that someone enabled and/or touched my life during. I will then write down a thank-you note where I specifically describe how this person affected me at that moment and in the time that followed, what I learnt from them and the experience, how I remember their efforts and why I am grateful. I will write this by hand, using complete sentences. If I still have their contact, I will share this note with them*, either direclty as handwriting, the photo therof, or as a typed message. Finally, I will crumple up the note and put it in a glass jar. At the end of the month, the jar will contain some twenty to thirty gratitude notes. I guess you could call it the emotional equivalent of a piggy bank. Intuitively, this sounds like a good idea. For sure it’s a nice gift to give to someone and the other person will appreciate it. As I am writing this down, I am already super excited about reconnecting with my friends and others and sharing how they impacted my life. But it goes quite a bit further, it is also a fantastic gift for oneself. There is lot of scientific literature to attest that gratitude practice is an extremely effective way to improve one’s mental and physical health. It encourages the savoring of positive life experiences and strengthens socials bonds. There is host of physiological benefits that have been reported in literature: Self-reported physical health Engagement in healthy and prosocial activities Willingness to ask for help and advice More feelings of happiness, pride, and hope Greater feeling of social connection, strengthening of intimate bonds Reduction in risk for depression, anxiety, and substance abuse Improved biomarker profile for cardiovascular disease Improvement of sleep and energy levels Stress and illness resilience This holiday season, I choose to be grateful. Will you join me? Further Resources Creating a Gratitude Practice This document contains further rationale for estabilishing a gratitude practice, as well as more detailed instructions on how to implement it. It has multiple references for the health benefits described above. Dr. Laurie Santos on the importance of gratitude This part of Laurie Santos’s talk highlights the importance of gratitude practice, and how sharing it with others is beneficial for both the one sharing, as well as the one receving it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World on Scientific Canvas - Three Plots to Make You Think</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World on Scientific Canvas - Three Plots to Make You Think" /><published>2023-11-02T19:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T19:56:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/11/02/3Plots.html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first post in a new series where I highlight plots that I came across in scientific literature that will be interesting for a broad audience. Today I look at why poor stay poor (economic inequality), why you should move to Italy but not Singapore (labor productivity), and why buying processed foods costs you more than you think (microbiome diversity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot-1-economic-connectedness-is-by-far-the-most-impactful-way-to-increase-economic-mobility-in-the-us&quot;&gt;Plot 1. Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility (in the US)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/social_capital_i_EC.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility. Figure from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04996-4.pdf&quot;&gt;Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot comes from the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04996-4.pdf&quot;&gt;Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility&lt;/a&gt; which, already from the title, is absolutely a stunning read. The researchers looked at what are drivers of upward economic mobility (in the US!) and concluded that one that matters by far the most is the relative share of high socioeconomic status (SES) friends, a quantity they termed economic connectedness. They find that if low-income children had the same type of friends as high-income children do, they would earn 20% more on average in adulthood! So what does this mean? You, dear reader, are probably relatively wealthy or have a good chance of being so in the future so if you care about economic inequality (and you should, because in the long run it hurst everybody!) go ahead and make friends with everyone, especially with people of relatively low SES!
Equally stunningly, many places which you would have thought are great destinations to elevate one’s or one’s family SES (e.g., Bay Area) are performing very poorly on economic connectedness, and consequently you would be better off moving to plenty of other places, many of which are much cheaper to live in. If you did not think segregation or gentrification is a problem, now you know it is. You can find the map of economic connectedness in the US here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.socialcapital.org/&quot;&gt;socialcapital.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot-2-the-harder-you-work-the-poorer-you-get-geographically-speaking&quot;&gt;Plot 2. The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking). Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would probably think that considering a country’s GDP is relevant when trying to find out where to relocate to, but that number tells you very little about how hard attaining that level of income may be. It turns out that labor productivity, how many hours you have to work to earn a certain wage, is more informative. The plot I chose shows that if you live in Singapore, you will have about double the annual income of someone living in Italy, but you will pay for this by working over 600 hours per year more on average. That’s over 75 8-hour working days a year! You can make many more comparisons yourself if you head over to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/productivity-vs-annual-hours-worked&quot;&gt;interactive plot at ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;. 
There is more insight that can be gleaned from the plot. One is, for example, that while we have done away with slavery as conventionally defined, its modern-day equivalent is rampant. The GDP of Bangladesh is 8% that of the Netherlands, while people in Bangladesh work nearly 1’000 hours per year more to earn it. That’s over 120 8-hour days a year! And that says nothing about the conditions this work is done in! This becomes even more obscene of one makes the comparison with Luxembourg, Switzerland, or Norway. 
If you consider the trend on the plot, you will quickly see that in countries with more productive workers, people tend to work less. That by extension leads to another insight: Don’t be afraid AI will take our jobs! Look forward to it instead! It is the most effective tool for increasing labor productivity we have nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot3-the-western-diet-makes-up-in-calories-for-what-it-lacks-in-diversity&quot;&gt;Plot3. The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/westernizedMicrobiome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity. Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.10.029&quot;&gt;US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome&lt;/a&gt; showing participants BMI and dietary patterns at the beginning end and of study. Faith’s phylogenetic distance (PD) quantifies diversity (in this case in participants’ diets)
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.10.029&quot;&gt;US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome&lt;/a&gt;) looked at Thai immigrants to the US over tens of years (including first and second gen immigrants) and compared their dietary patterns and some biomarkers to the control of US population. It found out that the immigrant microbiome gradually becomes US-like which also means it loses much of the original bacterial strains that can digest plant fiber. This appears to be a product of dietary changes. The US diet is markedly less diverse than the original Thai one and the immigrants gradually gravitate towards. The western diet is higher in fat and sugar and relatively lower in protein. Not surprisingly this leads to BMI increase, as well as increase of prevalence of obesity among immigrants over the years they reside in the US. The immediate takeaway here is, if you move to the US or live there already, do watch your diet (eating &lt;a href=&quot;/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html&quot;&gt;plant-based&lt;/a&gt; would help)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-remarks&quot;&gt;Final remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok those were three of the many figures I looked at recently that made me stop and think! I hope you have gotten something useful from them as well. All three plots come from papers or resources that are freely accessible so go ahead and dig deeper into the studies if you find them interesting! Thanks for reading everyone 😊&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="scicomm" /><summary type="html">This is the first post in a new series where I highlight plots that I came across in scientific literature that will be interesting for a broad audience. Today I look at why poor stay poor (economic inequality), why you should move to Italy but not Singapore (labor productivity), and why buying processed foods costs you more than you think (microbiome diversity). Plot 1. Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility (in the US) Economic connectedness is by far the most impactful way to increase economic mobility. Figure from Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility This plot comes from the paper Social capital I: measurement and associations with economic mobility which, already from the title, is absolutely a stunning read. The researchers looked at what are drivers of upward economic mobility (in the US!) and concluded that one that matters by far the most is the relative share of high socioeconomic status (SES) friends, a quantity they termed economic connectedness. They find that if low-income children had the same type of friends as high-income children do, they would earn 20% more on average in adulthood! So what does this mean? You, dear reader, are probably relatively wealthy or have a good chance of being so in the future so if you care about economic inequality (and you should, because in the long run it hurst everybody!) go ahead and make friends with everyone, especially with people of relatively low SES! Equally stunningly, many places which you would have thought are great destinations to elevate one’s or one’s family SES (e.g., Bay Area) are performing very poorly on economic connectedness, and consequently you would be better off moving to plenty of other places, many of which are much cheaper to live in. If you did not think segregation or gentrification is a problem, now you know it is. You can find the map of economic connectedness in the US here: socialcapital.org. Plot 2. The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking) The harder you work the poorer you get (geographically speaking). Figure adapted from ourworldindata.org You would probably think that considering a country’s GDP is relevant when trying to find out where to relocate to, but that number tells you very little about how hard attaining that level of income may be. It turns out that labor productivity, how many hours you have to work to earn a certain wage, is more informative. The plot I chose shows that if you live in Singapore, you will have about double the annual income of someone living in Italy, but you will pay for this by working over 600 hours per year more on average. That’s over 75 8-hour working days a year! You can make many more comparisons yourself if you head over to the interactive plot at ourworldindata.org. There is more insight that can be gleaned from the plot. One is, for example, that while we have done away with slavery as conventionally defined, its modern-day equivalent is rampant. The GDP of Bangladesh is 8% that of the Netherlands, while people in Bangladesh work nearly 1’000 hours per year more to earn it. That’s over 120 8-hour days a year! And that says nothing about the conditions this work is done in! This becomes even more obscene of one makes the comparison with Luxembourg, Switzerland, or Norway. If you consider the trend on the plot, you will quickly see that in countries with more productive workers, people tend to work less. That by extension leads to another insight: Don’t be afraid AI will take our jobs! Look forward to it instead! It is the most effective tool for increasing labor productivity we have nowadays. Plot3. The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity The western diet makes up in calories for what it lacks in diversity. Figure adapted from US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome showing participants BMI and dietary patterns at the beginning end and of study. Faith’s phylogenetic distance (PD) quantifies diversity (in this case in participants’ diets) This study (US Immigration Westernizes the Human Gut Microbiome) looked at Thai immigrants to the US over tens of years (including first and second gen immigrants) and compared their dietary patterns and some biomarkers to the control of US population. It found out that the immigrant microbiome gradually becomes US-like which also means it loses much of the original bacterial strains that can digest plant fiber. This appears to be a product of dietary changes. The US diet is markedly less diverse than the original Thai one and the immigrants gradually gravitate towards. The western diet is higher in fat and sugar and relatively lower in protein. Not surprisingly this leads to BMI increase, as well as increase of prevalence of obesity among immigrants over the years they reside in the US. The immediate takeaway here is, if you move to the US or live there already, do watch your diet (eating plant-based would help)! Final remarks Ok those were three of the many figures I looked at recently that made me stop and think! I hope you have gotten something useful from them as well. All three plots come from papers or resources that are freely accessible so go ahead and dig deeper into the studies if you find them interesting! Thanks for reading everyone 😊</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive Into Plant-Based Diets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive Into Plant-Based Diets" /><published>2023-10-18T19:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T19:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2023/10/18/PlantBased.html">&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets have become increasingly popular in recent years, with many people choosing to adopt them for health, environmental, or ethical reasons. In this article, I will explore the origins of plant-based diets, their current state, health benefits, potential side effects, and their suitability for athletes. I will also discuss how plant-based diets can help with weight loss and their impact on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origins-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Origins of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets have been around for thousands of years. Much of their history arose in 1500 – 500 BCE on the Indian subcontinent. Also, the ancient Greeks, including athletes, were known to consume plant-based diets, with records dating as far back as 6th century BCE. Aside from that, the early hominids from roughly 2 million years ago were primarily vegan, with opportunistic omnivorous behavior.
Today, while plant-based diets are becoming more popular, relatively modest proportion of 5-10% of people worldwide are eating them. There is a spectrum of plant-based diets, ranging from pescatarian to lacto(-ovo-)vegetarian to vegan. No diet is perfect for everyone, and it’s critical that you consider what foods are available to you, what foods are your staples, and what you can do without, when determining which diet to follow (i.e. the structure of your diet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/michelin_diet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://guide.michelin.com/us/en/article/wellness/a-guide-to-the-vegetarian-spectrum&quot;&gt;guide.michelin.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/diettypes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.precisionnutrition.com/plant-based-nutrition&quot;&gt;precisionnutrition.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health-benefits-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Health Benefits of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main motivations to opt for a plant-based diet is that they have been linked to a variety of health benefits. For example, plant-based were reported to reduce the risk of ischemic disease by 25% and even lower the overall risk of cancer by approximately 10% for some types (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2016.1138447&quot;&gt;Dinu, Abbate, Gensini, Casini, &amp;amp; Sofi, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). There is also strong evidence that they reduce the risk of diabetes by 28% (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9060603&quot;&gt;Lee &amp;amp; Park, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Let’s note in passing that 10% of the worldwide population has diabetes(&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/diabetes-prevalence?tab=table&quot;&gt;ourwoldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;), which is a tremendous socioeconomic cost, so anything that can help alleviate that should be seriously considered. 
While the above benefits are very concrete, the studies could not control for the confounding fact that people who decide to adopt-plant based diet tend to lead healthier lifestyles (fewer smokers, less overweight, more frequent exercise, less alcohol, …). It remains disputable whether there is any inherent benefit to eating plant-based per-se, and if there is one, it will most probably be small. It’s more likely that the true benefits of plant-based diet come from increasing our awareness about what we eat, supporting adoption of healthy lifestyle patterns and facilitating adherence. This includes removing processed meat, which is known to increase the risk of cardiovascular disease, stroke, colon, and rectal cancers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1161/circulationaha.109.924977&quot;&gt;Micha, Wallace, &amp;amp; Mozaffarian, 2010&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1161/circheartfailure.113.000921&quot;&gt;Kaluza, Akesson, &amp;amp; Wolk, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, there is strong evidence that high temperature cooking (such as pan frying, charring, barbecuing) leads to formation of carcinogenic compounds and that amounts of these are particularly elevated in red meats (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/01635580802710741&quot;&gt;Zheng &amp;amp; Lee, 2009&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2011.2287&quot;&gt;Pan et al., 2012&lt;/a&gt;). Plant-based diets avoid consuming meats prepared in this way as they avoid meat in the first place (duh :)).
While the health benefits of plant-based diets may be indirect, this in my opinion does not subtract from their attractiveness for reaching certain health goals. However, even a plant diet can be an unhealthy one. It’s critical to eat whole and healthy foods, irrespective of diet’s structure. That means avoiding processed and high-added sugar foods and consuming equilibrated profile of macro and micronutrients. Such a diet would also lead to higher fiber intake which is implicated in the reduction of risk for colon and rectal cancers. There is nothing wrong with fat either, it’s unprocessed sources such as nuts and seeds tend to be high in fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K) and the healthy mono/poly-unsaturated fatty acids. Consuming an unhealthy plant-based diet is associated with poor health outcomes, even worse than control (so people who keep eating whatever they ate, including processed meat, and not adjusting their lifestyle) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1002039&quot;&gt;Satija et al., 2016&lt;/a&gt;). 
Finally, the above highlights the importance of lifestyle when it comes to health outcomes. To optimize health outcomes, it’s vital to look beyond diet and consider your sleep, exercise, alcohol intake, smoking, and mental fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-weight-loss&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for Weight Loss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets are generally effective for weight loss. However, research shows that other diets can be equally effective, irrespective of their structure (i.e. if they are plant-based or not) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.297.9.969&quot;&gt;Gardner et al., 2007&lt;/a&gt;). In the end, it turns out, the rule of weight loss is quite simple (that is, for most healthy individuals): On day one, consume fewer calories than you burn, on all consequent days, repeat. The advantage of plant-based diets is that they facilitate this, as plant-based, unprocessed (!), foods tend to be less calorie dense. Vegan diets are in this sense even more effective than other plant-based diets. Finally, being a (lacto/ovo-) vegetarian or vegan, is for many a part of their identity, and stops being a decision they would have to face every time when deciding what to eat, which greatly helps with adherence (an idea popularize by James Clear in his book Atomic Habits).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-side-effects-of-plant-based-diets&quot;&gt;Potential Side Effects of Plant-Based Diets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many will be held back from adopting or trying plant-based diets due to concerns about their side effects. Let’s look at how much these are substantiated. It’s true of any diet, that by omission of certain foods, it may be harder to reach macro and micronutrient goals.
This is not an exception for any plant-based diet. On large sample level, these tend to lead to nutritional deficiencies. For example, up to 86.5% of vegetarians do not have adequate levels of vitamin B12 (largest of the B-complex vitamins containing cobalt in its structure essential in multitude of processes in our bodies) in their blood (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/ejcn.2014.46&quot;&gt;Pawlak, Lester, &amp;amp; Babatunde, 2014&lt;/a&gt;), and iron deficiency can be seen in up to 79% of females and up to 29% of males who adopt plant-based diets (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1177/1559827616682933&quot;&gt;Pawlak, Berger, &amp;amp; Hines, 2016&lt;/a&gt;). This is not because plant-based diets contain less iron, but because it comes in forms and combinations that make it less bioavailable. Plant-based diets are also deficient in choline (an essential nutrient and a source of methyl groups needed for many steps in our metabolism and required for synthesis of neurotransmitter acetylcholine), but there is insufficient research to show if this has any negative health implications.
Next, plant-based diets are generally deficient in omega-3 fatty acids. While some plants are good sources of the short-chain form, the long-form is found mainly in fish. Our body can to some degree convert the short-chain into long-chain fatty acids but does so only with 2-5% efficiency. 
Plant-based diets are also generally higher in carbohydrates, lower in fat, and lower in protein. A person following a plant-based diet eats on average 20-30% less protein than an omnivore. This is generally not a problem but may become a concern for someone with a very active lifestyle (see below).
There is evidence to suggest that individuals who follow a plant-based diet, especially those who follow a vegan-diet, are exposed to more phytoestrogens (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2016.10.018&quot;&gt;Tordjman et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;), which are plant derived hormone-like molecules that activate the estrogen receptor. While this has been associated with lower testosterone levels in males, more recent research shows lack of correlation and additionally suggests that estrogens have positive effects in treatment and prevention in rage of indications including skin aging, osteoporosis, cancer, cardiovascular, neurodegenerative, immune, and metabolic diseases. Additionally, estrogens have been reported to help alleviate menopausal symptoms in women (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2014.07.057&quot;&gt;Sirotkin &amp;amp; Harrath, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Overall, there seems to be little to no negative effect associated with elevated phytoestrogen exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-athletes&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for Athletes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plant-based diets are compatible with active lifestyle and can be even preferable for endurance athletes such as runners and cyclists. The elevated carbohydrate consumption provided by plant-based diets translates to an increase in the amount of stored muscle glycogen. Glycogen fuels muscle contractions during intense or prolonged exercise and its increased storage helps with endurance. The general lower calorie intake of plant-based diets can also help maintain weight in certain categories and overall optimize lean muscle mass. However, a chronic insufficient calorie intake is one of major risk factors for injury and illness among athletes. 
Besides general calories insufficiency, plant-based diets tend to lead to micronutrient deficiencies, as highlighted earlier, and these can negatively impact athlete’s health and performance. Furthermore, athletes who follow a plant-based diet consume about 70% of the protein that their omnivorous counterparts consume (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu6031318&quot;&gt;Clarys et al., 2014&lt;/a&gt;), which may not be sufficient depending on one’s exercise regime and fitness goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;importance-of-tracking-supplementation-and-fortification&quot;&gt;Importance of Tracking, Supplementation and Fortification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever diet you adopt, or even if you are an omnivore, there is a chance that your micro and macronutrient intake may result in some insufficiencies in the long run. If you opt for a plant-based diet, you have good chances of having to deal with B12, choline, iron and omega-3 deficiencies. It’s equally important that your calorie and macronutrient intake matches your exercise regimen and fitness goals. 
To keep the micronutrient levels in check, I would highly recommend getting your blood work done on a regular basis. It’s the best way to see how the diet patterns that you adopt translate to micronutrient levels, and it can help identify problems in their infancy or prevent them becoming problems in the first place. It is probably clear by now that for anyone following a plant-based diet consistently, it’s extremely likely that they will have to rely on supplementation and/or fortification for some, or all, of the micronutrients listed above. There is absolutely nothing wrong with that. If you are plant-based, please don’t insist on eating 100% naturally! Get some high-quality supplements, even if it were just for prevention, and your body will thank you for that. Do some research on which supplements to choose – lately there are plenty of them on the market and many come wide widely varying micronutrient levels or levels that are well beyond what you would need. 
Similarly, and in particular if you live an active lifestyle, you should get a good sense of the amount of calories and macronutrients you are digesting, and whether this matches your expenditure and goals. There are tools that can be used to calculate how many calories do you burn at your maintenance, given your exercise patterns. Look online for TDEE, total daily energy expenditure, calculator and use a few of them and take an average for more robust estimate. If you have somewhat smart bodyweight scale, it can give you pretty good estimate as well.
Next, it’s mandatory to track the calories and specific foods that you are eating consistently, at least for some limited period. It’s not that long ago that I tried it for the first time, and I was very surprised with the result. I was on average eating about 30% less calories than I thought! Doing this will also help you understand whether you are meeting your macronutrient needs. Besides these ‘smart’ calculators, it is important to check in with your energy levels. If you feel low, make sure you are getting adequate sleep. If that is in check, look at decreasing intensity or frequency of your exercise (more rest) or increasing calorie input. Finally, if you are very active and plant-based, there is a chance you may be running too low on protein intake and then you would either want to adjust your diet or look for some high-quality vegetarian or vegan protein powder (again, nothing wrong with that!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plant-based-diets-for-the-environment&quot;&gt;Plant-Based Diets for the Environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people opt for plant-based diet to limit their environmental impact. All evidence suggests that this is a step in the right direction, yet the situation is certainly not black and white. How much of a positive impact on the environment will you have, if any, will depend on the individual products you consume on regular basis. Did you, for example, know that some types of cheese will have double to triple the emission footprint of chicken meat? Or that coffee and chocolate have similar emission footprints as some types of beef? (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/carbon-footprint-food-methane&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;). 
Furthermore, choices other than dietary ones can have a larger impact on the environment. Opting to live without a car, skipping one long-haul flight per year or moving over to renewable sources of energy can have double to triple the positive impact of going plant-based. Better home insulation, using more public transport or opting to live without a pet all have comparable effects to becoming plant-based (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab8589&quot;&gt;Ivanova et al., 2020&lt;/a&gt;). And of course, not all plant-based diets are made equal, vegan diet is about twice as effective as general plant-based diet in this regard. Somewhat unpopular, having one less child seems by far the most effective climate impact mitigation strategy (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aa7541&quot;&gt;Wines &amp;amp; Nicholas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). However, I personally choose not to weigh the environmental concerns in this aspect too heavily, as there are tons of problems associated with the aging of society as well (hope to write on that in the future!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/food_emissions.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/carbon-footprint-food-methane&quot;&gt;ourworldindata.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/carbon_footprint.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-52719662&quot;&gt;bbc.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever diet you adopt, make sure it works for you: Does it make you feel good? Can you stick to it? Can you afford it? Doesn’t it feel overly restrictive?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diet is a step in the right direction when aiming to improve health outcomes, but it won’t be (nearly as) effective if not accompanied by other lifestyle choices such as exercise, cigarette, and alcohol use, as well as mental health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even a plant-based diet can be an unhealthy one. Make sure to prioritize whole, unprocessed foods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maybe the largest benefit of plant-based diets is that they avoid some foods that are known to be causing disease, and that they facilitate adherence by becoming part of one’s identity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your blood work done with some periodicity and track what you eat (at least for an initial period). Supplement accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant based diets can be safely followed by athletes and are even advantageous for some forms of exercise. Supplementation is very likely to be helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant-based diets are only one the ways how to mitigate once environmental impact, and they are not the most effective ones. If the environment and health of our planet matters to you, please don’t stop here!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading everyone! Do you have any questions or thoughts spurred by the article? Did I forget to mention something obvious? I will be happy if you let me know in the comments section below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post is based on an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasm.org/continuing-education/free-nasm-courses&quot;&gt;online course by the National Academy of Sports Medicine&lt;/a&gt; that is on sale as part of their promo for the vegetarian awarness month (Oct’23). I can only suggest taking it if you are interested in the topic!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="diet" /><category term="environment" /><category term="fitness" /><category term="sport" /><summary type="html">Plant-based diets have become increasingly popular in recent years, with many people choosing to adopt them for health, environmental, or ethical reasons. In this article, I will explore the origins of plant-based diets, their current state, health benefits, potential side effects, and their suitability for athletes. I will also discuss how plant-based diets can help with weight loss and their impact on the environment. Origins of Plant-Based Diets Plant-based diets have been around for thousands of years. Much of their history arose in 1500 – 500 BCE on the Indian subcontinent. Also, the ancient Greeks, including athletes, were known to consume plant-based diets, with records dating as far back as 6th century BCE. Aside from that, the early hominids from roughly 2 million years ago were primarily vegan, with opportunistic omnivorous behavior. Today, while plant-based diets are becoming more popular, relatively modest proportion of 5-10% of people worldwide are eating them. There is a spectrum of plant-based diets, ranging from pescatarian to lacto(-ovo-)vegetarian to vegan. No diet is perfect for everyone, and it’s critical that you consider what foods are available to you, what foods are your staples, and what you can do without, when determining which diet to follow (i.e. the structure of your diet). From guide.michelin.com From precisionnutrition.com Health Benefits of Plant-Based Diets One of the main motivations to opt for a plant-based diet is that they have been linked to a variety of health benefits. For example, plant-based were reported to reduce the risk of ischemic disease by 25% and even lower the overall risk of cancer by approximately 10% for some types (Dinu, Abbate, Gensini, Casini, &amp;amp; Sofi, 2017). There is also strong evidence that they reduce the risk of diabetes by 28% (Lee &amp;amp; Park, 2017). Let’s note in passing that 10% of the worldwide population has diabetes(ourwoldindata.org), which is a tremendous socioeconomic cost, so anything that can help alleviate that should be seriously considered. While the above benefits are very concrete, the studies could not control for the confounding fact that people who decide to adopt-plant based diet tend to lead healthier lifestyles (fewer smokers, less overweight, more frequent exercise, less alcohol, …). It remains disputable whether there is any inherent benefit to eating plant-based per-se, and if there is one, it will most probably be small. It’s more likely that the true benefits of plant-based diet come from increasing our awareness about what we eat, supporting adoption of healthy lifestyle patterns and facilitating adherence. This includes removing processed meat, which is known to increase the risk of cardiovascular disease, stroke, colon, and rectal cancers (Micha, Wallace, &amp;amp; Mozaffarian, 2010; Kaluza, Akesson, &amp;amp; Wolk, 2014). Furthermore, there is strong evidence that high temperature cooking (such as pan frying, charring, barbecuing) leads to formation of carcinogenic compounds and that amounts of these are particularly elevated in red meats (Zheng &amp;amp; Lee, 2009; Pan et al., 2012). Plant-based diets avoid consuming meats prepared in this way as they avoid meat in the first place (duh :)). While the health benefits of plant-based diets may be indirect, this in my opinion does not subtract from their attractiveness for reaching certain health goals. However, even a plant diet can be an unhealthy one. It’s critical to eat whole and healthy foods, irrespective of diet’s structure. That means avoiding processed and high-added sugar foods and consuming equilibrated profile of macro and micronutrients. Such a diet would also lead to higher fiber intake which is implicated in the reduction of risk for colon and rectal cancers. There is nothing wrong with fat either, it’s unprocessed sources such as nuts and seeds tend to be high in fat-soluble vitamins (A, D, E, K) and the healthy mono/poly-unsaturated fatty acids. Consuming an unhealthy plant-based diet is associated with poor health outcomes, even worse than control (so people who keep eating whatever they ate, including processed meat, and not adjusting their lifestyle) (Satija et al., 2016). Finally, the above highlights the importance of lifestyle when it comes to health outcomes. To optimize health outcomes, it’s vital to look beyond diet and consider your sleep, exercise, alcohol intake, smoking, and mental fitness. Plant-Based Diets for Weight Loss Plant-based diets are generally effective for weight loss. However, research shows that other diets can be equally effective, irrespective of their structure (i.e. if they are plant-based or not) (Gardner et al., 2007). In the end, it turns out, the rule of weight loss is quite simple (that is, for most healthy individuals): On day one, consume fewer calories than you burn, on all consequent days, repeat. The advantage of plant-based diets is that they facilitate this, as plant-based, unprocessed (!), foods tend to be less calorie dense. Vegan diets are in this sense even more effective than other plant-based diets. Finally, being a (lacto/ovo-) vegetarian or vegan, is for many a part of their identity, and stops being a decision they would have to face every time when deciding what to eat, which greatly helps with adherence (an idea popularize by James Clear in his book Atomic Habits). Potential Side Effects of Plant-Based Diets Many will be held back from adopting or trying plant-based diets due to concerns about their side effects. Let’s look at how much these are substantiated. It’s true of any diet, that by omission of certain foods, it may be harder to reach macro and micronutrient goals. This is not an exception for any plant-based diet. On large sample level, these tend to lead to nutritional deficiencies. For example, up to 86.5% of vegetarians do not have adequate levels of vitamin B12 (largest of the B-complex vitamins containing cobalt in its structure essential in multitude of processes in our bodies) in their blood (Pawlak, Lester, &amp;amp; Babatunde, 2014), and iron deficiency can be seen in up to 79% of females and up to 29% of males who adopt plant-based diets (Pawlak, Berger, &amp;amp; Hines, 2016). This is not because plant-based diets contain less iron, but because it comes in forms and combinations that make it less bioavailable. Plant-based diets are also deficient in choline (an essential nutrient and a source of methyl groups needed for many steps in our metabolism and required for synthesis of neurotransmitter acetylcholine), but there is insufficient research to show if this has any negative health implications. Next, plant-based diets are generally deficient in omega-3 fatty acids. While some plants are good sources of the short-chain form, the long-form is found mainly in fish. Our body can to some degree convert the short-chain into long-chain fatty acids but does so only with 2-5% efficiency. Plant-based diets are also generally higher in carbohydrates, lower in fat, and lower in protein. A person following a plant-based diet eats on average 20-30% less protein than an omnivore. This is generally not a problem but may become a concern for someone with a very active lifestyle (see below). There is evidence to suggest that individuals who follow a plant-based diet, especially those who follow a vegan-diet, are exposed to more phytoestrogens (Tordjman et al. 2016), which are plant derived hormone-like molecules that activate the estrogen receptor. While this has been associated with lower testosterone levels in males, more recent research shows lack of correlation and additionally suggests that estrogens have positive effects in treatment and prevention in rage of indications including skin aging, osteoporosis, cancer, cardiovascular, neurodegenerative, immune, and metabolic diseases. Additionally, estrogens have been reported to help alleviate menopausal symptoms in women (Sirotkin &amp;amp; Harrath, 2014). Overall, there seems to be little to no negative effect associated with elevated phytoestrogen exposure. Plant-Based Diets for Athletes Plant-based diets are compatible with active lifestyle and can be even preferable for endurance athletes such as runners and cyclists. The elevated carbohydrate consumption provided by plant-based diets translates to an increase in the amount of stored muscle glycogen. Glycogen fuels muscle contractions during intense or prolonged exercise and its increased storage helps with endurance. The general lower calorie intake of plant-based diets can also help maintain weight in certain categories and overall optimize lean muscle mass. However, a chronic insufficient calorie intake is one of major risk factors for injury and illness among athletes. Besides general calories insufficiency, plant-based diets tend to lead to micronutrient deficiencies, as highlighted earlier, and these can negatively impact athlete’s health and performance. Furthermore, athletes who follow a plant-based diet consume about 70% of the protein that their omnivorous counterparts consume (Clarys et al., 2014), which may not be sufficient depending on one’s exercise regime and fitness goals. Importance of Tracking, Supplementation and Fortification Whatever diet you adopt, or even if you are an omnivore, there is a chance that your micro and macronutrient intake may result in some insufficiencies in the long run. If you opt for a plant-based diet, you have good chances of having to deal with B12, choline, iron and omega-3 deficiencies. It’s equally important that your calorie and macronutrient intake matches your exercise regimen and fitness goals. To keep the micronutrient levels in check, I would highly recommend getting your blood work done on a regular basis. It’s the best way to see how the diet patterns that you adopt translate to micronutrient levels, and it can help identify problems in their infancy or prevent them becoming problems in the first place. It is probably clear by now that for anyone following a plant-based diet consistently, it’s extremely likely that they will have to rely on supplementation and/or fortification for some, or all, of the micronutrients listed above. There is absolutely nothing wrong with that. If you are plant-based, please don’t insist on eating 100% naturally! Get some high-quality supplements, even if it were just for prevention, and your body will thank you for that. Do some research on which supplements to choose – lately there are plenty of them on the market and many come wide widely varying micronutrient levels or levels that are well beyond what you would need. Similarly, and in particular if you live an active lifestyle, you should get a good sense of the amount of calories and macronutrients you are digesting, and whether this matches your expenditure and goals. There are tools that can be used to calculate how many calories do you burn at your maintenance, given your exercise patterns. Look online for TDEE, total daily energy expenditure, calculator and use a few of them and take an average for more robust estimate. If you have somewhat smart bodyweight scale, it can give you pretty good estimate as well. Next, it’s mandatory to track the calories and specific foods that you are eating consistently, at least for some limited period. It’s not that long ago that I tried it for the first time, and I was very surprised with the result. I was on average eating about 30% less calories than I thought! Doing this will also help you understand whether you are meeting your macronutrient needs. Besides these ‘smart’ calculators, it is important to check in with your energy levels. If you feel low, make sure you are getting adequate sleep. If that is in check, look at decreasing intensity or frequency of your exercise (more rest) or increasing calorie input. Finally, if you are very active and plant-based, there is a chance you may be running too low on protein intake and then you would either want to adjust your diet or look for some high-quality vegetarian or vegan protein powder (again, nothing wrong with that!) Plant-Based Diets for the Environment Many people opt for plant-based diet to limit their environmental impact. All evidence suggests that this is a step in the right direction, yet the situation is certainly not black and white. How much of a positive impact on the environment will you have, if any, will depend on the individual products you consume on regular basis. Did you, for example, know that some types of cheese will have double to triple the emission footprint of chicken meat? Or that coffee and chocolate have similar emission footprints as some types of beef? (ourworldindata.org). Furthermore, choices other than dietary ones can have a larger impact on the environment. Opting to live without a car, skipping one long-haul flight per year or moving over to renewable sources of energy can have double to triple the positive impact of going plant-based. Better home insulation, using more public transport or opting to live without a pet all have comparable effects to becoming plant-based (Ivanova et al., 2020). And of course, not all plant-based diets are made equal, vegan diet is about twice as effective as general plant-based diet in this regard. Somewhat unpopular, having one less child seems by far the most effective climate impact mitigation strategy (Wines &amp;amp; Nicholas, 2017). However, I personally choose not to weigh the environmental concerns in this aspect too heavily, as there are tons of problems associated with the aging of society as well (hope to write on that in the future!). From ourworldindata.org From bbc.com Conclusions Whatever diet you adopt, make sure it works for you: Does it make you feel good? Can you stick to it? Can you afford it? Doesn’t it feel overly restrictive? Diet is a step in the right direction when aiming to improve health outcomes, but it won’t be (nearly as) effective if not accompanied by other lifestyle choices such as exercise, cigarette, and alcohol use, as well as mental health. Even a plant-based diet can be an unhealthy one. Make sure to prioritize whole, unprocessed foods. Maybe the largest benefit of plant-based diets is that they avoid some foods that are known to be causing disease, and that they facilitate adherence by becoming part of one’s identity. Get your blood work done with some periodicity and track what you eat (at least for an initial period). Supplement accordingly. Plant based diets can be safely followed by athletes and are even advantageous for some forms of exercise. Supplementation is very likely to be helpful. Plant-based diets are only one the ways how to mitigate once environmental impact, and they are not the most effective ones. If the environment and health of our planet matters to you, please don’t stop here! Thanks for reading everyone! Do you have any questions or thoughts spurred by the article? Did I forget to mention something obvious? I will be happy if you let me know in the comments section below! The post is based on an online course by the National Academy of Sports Medicine that is on sale as part of their promo for the vegetarian awarness month (Oct’23). I can only suggest taking it if you are interested in the topic!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 ADE Festival Personal Highligths</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 ADE Festival Personal Highligths" /><published>2023-10-16T15:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-16T15:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/event/2023/10/16/ADE2023.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-19th&quot;&gt;Thursday 19th&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pieter-de-graaf--live-at-planetarium-artis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/pieter-de-graaf-live-at-planetarium-artis/279312/&quot;&gt;Pieter de Graaf | Live at Planetarium Artis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artis Planetarium, 20:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-dance-is-to-be-free&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/to-dance-is-to-be-free/279313/&quot;&gt;To Dance is to be Free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stadsarchief Amsterdam, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;live-from-earth&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/live-from-earth/279314/&quot;&gt;Live From Earth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lofi, 22:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awakenings-ade-2023-adam-beyer-presents-drumcode&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/awakenings-ade-2023-adam-beyer-presents-drumcode/279315/&quot;&gt;Awakenings ADE 2023: Adam Beyer Presents Drumcode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gashouder, 22:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kntxt-turbo-club&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/kntxt-turbo-club/279316/&quot;&gt;KNTXT Turbo Club&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Theater Amsterdam, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friday-20th&quot;&gt;Friday 20th&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ineffekt---ar-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/ineffekt-ar-experience/279317/&quot;&gt;Ineffekt - AR experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black Gold Amsterdam, 17:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;538-dj-hotel-showcase-hardwell&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/538-dj-hotel-showcase-hardwell/279318/&quot;&gt;538 DJ Hotel showcase: Hardwell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Social Hub Amsterdam City, 20:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alle&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/alle/279319/&quot;&gt;ALLE$&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sexyland World, 21:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saturday-21st&quot;&gt;Saturday 21st&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;11-1-club-couture-with-sven-marquardt&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/11-1-club-couture-with-sven-marquardt/279320/&quot;&gt;11 +1: Club Couture with Sven Marquardt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fosbury &amp;amp; Sons, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-ecstatic-morning-rave&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/free-ecstatic-morning-rave/279321/&quot;&gt;Free Ecstatic Morning Rave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vondelkerk, 10:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-deep-club-at-the-bassment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/the-deep-club-at-the-bas-sment/279322/&quot;&gt;The Deep club at the Bas[s]ment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Bas[s]ment, 19:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cinematique-label-showcase&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/cinematique-label-showcase/279323/&quot;&gt;Cinematique Label Showcase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JD Williams Whisky Bar, 21:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kollektiv-turmstrasse-pres-unity-of-opposites&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/kollektiv-turmstrasse-pres-unity-of-opposites/279324/&quot;&gt;Kollektiv Turmstrasse pres. Unity of Opposites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noordwaards, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;het-weekend&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/het-weekend/279325/&quot;&gt;Het Weekend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;De School, 23:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sunday-22nd&quot;&gt;Sunday 22nd&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ade-hangover---free-entrance&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/ade-hangover-free-entrance/279326/&quot;&gt;ADE Hangover - Free entrance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NDSM, 12:00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intercell-x-i-hate-models-invites&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/2023/intercell-x-i-hate-models-invites/279327/&quot;&gt;Intercell x I Hate Models Invites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warehouse Elementenstraat, 23:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The schedule is subject to change. Please check the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdam-dance-event.nl/en/program/&quot;&gt;ADE website&lt;/a&gt; for the latest updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="event" /><category term="event" /><summary type="html">Thursday 19th Pieter de Graaf | Live at Planetarium Artis Artis Planetarium, 20:30 To Dance is to be Free Stadsarchief Amsterdam, 10:00 Live From Earth Lofi, 22:00 Awakenings ADE 2023: Adam Beyer Presents Drumcode Gashouder, 22:00 KNTXT Turbo Club Theater Amsterdam, 23:00 Friday 20th Ineffekt - AR experience Black Gold Amsterdam, 17:00 538 DJ Hotel showcase: Hardwell The Social Hub Amsterdam City, 20:00 ALLE$ Sexyland World, 21:30 Saturday 21st 11 +1: Club Couture with Sven Marquardt Fosbury &amp;amp; Sons, 10:00 Free Ecstatic Morning Rave Vondelkerk, 10:00 The Deep club at the Bas[s]ment The Bas[s]ment, 19:00 Cinematique Label Showcase JD Williams Whisky Bar, 21:00 Kollektiv Turmstrasse pres. Unity of Opposites Noordwaards, 23:00 Het Weekend De School, 23:00 Sunday 22nd ADE Hangover - Free entrance NDSM, 12:00 Intercell x I Hate Models Invites Warehouse Elementenstraat, 23:30 Note: The schedule is subject to change. Please check the official ADE website for the latest updates.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">12 Lessons I Learnt In the Past 12 Months</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="12 Lessons I Learnt In the Past 12 Months" /><published>2023-10-01T15:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T15:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2023/10/01/12Lessons2023.html">&lt;p&gt;I celebrated my birthday past weekend and wanted to use this moment to reflect on how the year has been. Here is a list of twelve lessons the year taught me. Admittedly, I am not the best student so I have to keep relearning them as I go, therfore writing them down. Couple of them should be useful for you as well! If a particrular one resonates, I would be happy to hear about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-you-dont-have-to-own-a-home&quot;&gt;1. You don’t have to own a home.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would feel inferior to my peers who bought their own homes, and when asked, try to fathom a plan for doing so, going to happen soon, thanks for asking.
Most of us were led to believe that owning a home is a no-brainer that anyone who is serious about their personal finances must aspire to, and ideally achieve as soon as possible. I certainly thought so until very recently and struggled a lot with the fact that as an expat that moves countries about every three years, I am shooting myself in the foot as this makes me virtually unable to own a property anywhere. My opinion changed recently, and I came to think that NOT owning a home may be a smarter financial decision for lot of people, including me, given the current prices and the career mobility this lends me. I will write a whole post on this so stay tuned. For now, I am not thinking of buying a home and I am at peace with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/housingmarket.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-dont-spend-energy-on-someone-who-does-not-give-it-back&quot;&gt;2. Don’t spend energy on someone who does not give it back.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an obvious one but took me way too long to learn. Identify the people in your life who reciprocate when you spend time and energy and go on a positive spiral with them. Distance yourself from the rest and don’t look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-good-things-come-to-those-who-dont-wait-but-many-good-things-take-a-long-time&quot;&gt;3. Good things come to those who don’t wait (but many good things take a long time).&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are doubting whether you should do something, you are probably better of just doing it and learning from the outcome. I found out that acting on the first impulse is an effective strategy for someone who tends to overanalyze like me, because often I would just end up regretting not doing it.
That said, some of the really good things require sustained effort and making progress towards them is an absolute cornerstone for my happiness. The way I try to make sure I get to eat the cake and keep it to is to reserve regular time slots for sustained distraction free work.
If still in doubts, it is useful to think of your life in stages of exploring and exploiting. In the exploring stage, you would say yes to most things. In the exploiting stage, you would say yes only to very few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-results-compound&quot;&gt;4. Results compound.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know interest compounds and mostly tend to act on this knowledge. And I would also agree with anyone who claims that the same must apply to effort. Yet, until recently I would hope for anything I do to feel somehow special, noteworthy, or pleasurable. If I would not achieve results within the tiniest time, I would feel like I must have done something wrong. Only this year I came to fully apprehend that the fact that something feels boring may be a sign I am doing the right thing. This came with the experience that I can spend every day of a week doing things that feel amazing, but still end up feeling empty at the end if it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-the-more-you-can-work-from-home-the-better&quot;&gt;5. The more you can work from home the better.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/wfh_dog.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies that require you to show up four days per week to the office? Seriously? I run experiments in the lab and for the time being there is not an alternative to showing up in person, but for many other things I am at least as efficient working from home. For some things, such as conceptualization and reading, I am much more efficient if I avoid the office, which is always full of distractions.
Earlier in my career I would equate the time in the office with the amount of work I am doing. Lately I see them as mostly detached and prefer to go to work in person only if I really must be there. As a byproduct, I am more rigorous about scheduling meetings in times that work for my energy levels, and more consistent with when and how often I work out and get to work on my side projects (such as writing this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-you-can-eat-perfectly-well-in-just-6-to-8-hour-window-every-day&quot;&gt;6. You can eat perfectly well in just 6 to 8-hour window every day.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would grow up thinking I need to eat every 2-3 hours, 5-6 times a day. I don’t want to make the argument that there is no rationale for this, but I am convinced most of the conditioning is driven by the desire of different food companies to market as many different products as possible to you. Lately I have been limiting my food intake to about 8-hour window without any apparent drop in energy or fitness levels. On the contrary, I notice that it makes me more conscious about what I eat, and that translates to me feeling better throughout the day. It also leaves me with large chunks of unbroken time before and after my eating window, which I found out to be the most productive and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-cycling-beats-squats-for-quads&quot;&gt;7. Cycling beats squats for quads.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anytime. I started spinning early this year and my knees keep thanking me for it. Chances are yours would be thankful too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-to-really-improve-you-must-give-yourself-permission-to-experiment-and-fail&quot;&gt;8. To really improve, you must give yourself permission to experiment (and fail).&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/swing-dance.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this one is also kind of obvious on the face of it, but I doubt most would really be living by it. I came to appreciate it as I started taking bachata dancing classes this summer. While I was making good progress, I could only use moves that I learnt and practiced in the class. Quickly, I would fall into a pattern of always repeating the same sequence of moves that I knew ’worked’.
As I looked for ways to improve beyond this status quo, I watched people on the dance floor and realized that what makes some of them stand out is that they dance with their unique style and seem like having fun doing so. It did not take long to realize I have to do more than just keep doing what I learn in classes to become a better dancer. 
To become better, and eventually maybe great, at something, you have to dare to try things that you have not done before. You have to become playful and see where it takes you. You have to give yourself permission to be terrible (or at least arguably bad) first, only then you can become better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: One of my fav essays of all times deals with this topic: &lt;a href=&quot;https://autotranslucence.com/2018/03/30/becoming-a-magician/&quot;&gt;Becoming a Magician&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-stay-till-the-end-of-the-party&quot;&gt;9. Stay till the end of the party.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/afterparty.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy a night out, but I am also introverted so most of the time the energy is just too high to make more than a superficial connection while a party goes on. Not to even mention that when I am going out clubbing or dancing, there is usually very little room for a conversation other than shouting at each other about what you are drinking.
Staying until the end of a party is a straightforward opportunity to have a relaxed conversation. As a bonus, it removes the annoying guesswork about what time to leave, and frees me from feeling like I have to socialize extensively during it, which in turns allows me to focus more on myself end enjoying the event,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-to-feel-rich-decide-what-you-want-to-spend-lavishly-on-and-save-on-the-rest&quot;&gt;10. To feel rich, decide what you want to spend lavishly on, and save on the rest.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an important one for me and I am certainly still learning it. I come from a quite modest upbringing and would grow up thinking that the right financial decision is the one that leads to spending lesser amount of money, ideally none if possible. That certainly made me resourceful and was quite good for my personal finances, but also left me missing out on lot of opportunities and spending time instead of money. I started to try to look at money as a tool, and figuring out how to use it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is quite difficult to get right, because spending as little as possible is a straightforward decision to make, and the opposite end spectrum, which is allowing yourself to spend money on everything you desire, is not feasible unless you are financially extremely well of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared frustration with this with a friend, and she pointed out to me the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/money-dials/&quot;&gt;money dials&lt;/a&gt;, which are “the things that you are willing to spend extravagantly on by cutting back mercilessly on the things you don’t care about.” You probably can’t live in modern spacious apartment in city center, travel out of your country once a month, have a membership for the best gym in town, all that while donating 10% of your income. But you most likely can do one of them, maybe two if you are lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common money dials are: Convenience, Travel, Health&amp;amp;Fitness, Experiences, Freedom, Relationships, Generosity, Luxury, Social status and Self-improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-you-can-maintain-only-a-handful-of-close-connections&quot;&gt;11. You can maintain only a handful of close connections.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we grow into adulthood, lives tend to fill up with work, ambitions and obligations. The time left for making friends is quite scarce and its something most of us notice. But what fewer of us appreciate is that it also means fewer time to upkeep the close connections we already have. And if we don’t consciously carve out time to refuel these connections evey once so often, they will slowly dry out.
The key here really is to decide to spend time on reaching out to old friends, and specially if you are geographically separated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-prioritize-recovery&quot;&gt;12. Prioritize recovery.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise is important, but if you don’t want to jeopardize your results and energy levels, put recovery at the top of your priority list.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">I celebrated my birthday past weekend and wanted to use this moment to reflect on how the year has been. Here is a list of twelve lessons the year taught me. Admittedly, I am not the best student so I have to keep relearning them as I go, therfore writing them down. Couple of them should be useful for you as well! If a particrular one resonates, I would be happy to hear about it! 1. You don’t have to own a home. I would feel inferior to my peers who bought their own homes, and when asked, try to fathom a plan for doing so, going to happen soon, thanks for asking. Most of us were led to believe that owning a home is a no-brainer that anyone who is serious about their personal finances must aspire to, and ideally achieve as soon as possible. I certainly thought so until very recently and struggled a lot with the fact that as an expat that moves countries about every three years, I am shooting myself in the foot as this makes me virtually unable to own a property anywhere. My opinion changed recently, and I came to think that NOT owning a home may be a smarter financial decision for lot of people, including me, given the current prices and the career mobility this lends me. I will write a whole post on this so stay tuned. For now, I am not thinking of buying a home and I am at peace with it. 2. Don’t spend energy on someone who does not give it back. This is an obvious one but took me way too long to learn. Identify the people in your life who reciprocate when you spend time and energy and go on a positive spiral with them. Distance yourself from the rest and don’t look back. 3. Good things come to those who don’t wait (but many good things take a long time). If you are doubting whether you should do something, you are probably better of just doing it and learning from the outcome. I found out that acting on the first impulse is an effective strategy for someone who tends to overanalyze like me, because often I would just end up regretting not doing it. That said, some of the really good things require sustained effort and making progress towards them is an absolute cornerstone for my happiness. The way I try to make sure I get to eat the cake and keep it to is to reserve regular time slots for sustained distraction free work. If still in doubts, it is useful to think of your life in stages of exploring and exploiting. In the exploring stage, you would say yes to most things. In the exploiting stage, you would say yes only to very few things. 4. Results compound. I know interest compounds and mostly tend to act on this knowledge. And I would also agree with anyone who claims that the same must apply to effort. Yet, until recently I would hope for anything I do to feel somehow special, noteworthy, or pleasurable. If I would not achieve results within the tiniest time, I would feel like I must have done something wrong. Only this year I came to fully apprehend that the fact that something feels boring may be a sign I am doing the right thing. This came with the experience that I can spend every day of a week doing things that feel amazing, but still end up feeling empty at the end if it. 5. The more you can work from home the better. Companies that require you to show up four days per week to the office? Seriously? I run experiments in the lab and for the time being there is not an alternative to showing up in person, but for many other things I am at least as efficient working from home. For some things, such as conceptualization and reading, I am much more efficient if I avoid the office, which is always full of distractions. Earlier in my career I would equate the time in the office with the amount of work I am doing. Lately I see them as mostly detached and prefer to go to work in person only if I really must be there. As a byproduct, I am more rigorous about scheduling meetings in times that work for my energy levels, and more consistent with when and how often I work out and get to work on my side projects (such as writing this). 6. You can eat perfectly well in just 6 to 8-hour window every day. I would grow up thinking I need to eat every 2-3 hours, 5-6 times a day. I don’t want to make the argument that there is no rationale for this, but I am convinced most of the conditioning is driven by the desire of different food companies to market as many different products as possible to you. Lately I have been limiting my food intake to about 8-hour window without any apparent drop in energy or fitness levels. On the contrary, I notice that it makes me more conscious about what I eat, and that translates to me feeling better throughout the day. It also leaves me with large chunks of unbroken time before and after my eating window, which I found out to be the most productive and enjoyable. 7. Cycling beats squats for quads. Anytime. I started spinning early this year and my knees keep thanking me for it. Chances are yours would be thankful too. 8. To really improve, you must give yourself permission to experiment (and fail). So this one is also kind of obvious on the face of it, but I doubt most would really be living by it. I came to appreciate it as I started taking bachata dancing classes this summer. While I was making good progress, I could only use moves that I learnt and practiced in the class. Quickly, I would fall into a pattern of always repeating the same sequence of moves that I knew ’worked’. As I looked for ways to improve beyond this status quo, I watched people on the dance floor and realized that what makes some of them stand out is that they dance with their unique style and seem like having fun doing so. It did not take long to realize I have to do more than just keep doing what I learn in classes to become a better dancer. To become better, and eventually maybe great, at something, you have to dare to try things that you have not done before. You have to become playful and see where it takes you. You have to give yourself permission to be terrible (or at least arguably bad) first, only then you can become better. PS: One of my fav essays of all times deals with this topic: Becoming a Magician. 9. Stay till the end of the party. I enjoy a night out, but I am also introverted so most of the time the energy is just too high to make more than a superficial connection while a party goes on. Not to even mention that when I am going out clubbing or dancing, there is usually very little room for a conversation other than shouting at each other about what you are drinking. Staying until the end of a party is a straightforward opportunity to have a relaxed conversation. As a bonus, it removes the annoying guesswork about what time to leave, and frees me from feeling like I have to socialize extensively during it, which in turns allows me to focus more on myself end enjoying the event, 10. To feel rich, decide what you want to spend lavishly on, and save on the rest. This was an important one for me and I am certainly still learning it. I come from a quite modest upbringing and would grow up thinking that the right financial decision is the one that leads to spending lesser amount of money, ideally none if possible. That certainly made me resourceful and was quite good for my personal finances, but also left me missing out on lot of opportunities and spending time instead of money. I started to try to look at money as a tool, and figuring out how to use it better. This one is quite difficult to get right, because spending as little as possible is a straightforward decision to make, and the opposite end spectrum, which is allowing yourself to spend money on everything you desire, is not feasible unless you are financially extremely well of. I shared frustration with this with a friend, and she pointed out to me the concept of money dials, which are “the things that you are willing to spend extravagantly on by cutting back mercilessly on the things you don’t care about.” You probably can’t live in modern spacious apartment in city center, travel out of your country once a month, have a membership for the best gym in town, all that while donating 10% of your income. But you most likely can do one of them, maybe two if you are lucky. The most common money dials are: Convenience, Travel, Health&amp;amp;Fitness, Experiences, Freedom, Relationships, Generosity, Luxury, Social status and Self-improvement. 11. You can maintain only a handful of close connections. As we grow into adulthood, lives tend to fill up with work, ambitions and obligations. The time left for making friends is quite scarce and its something most of us notice. But what fewer of us appreciate is that it also means fewer time to upkeep the close connections we already have. And if we don’t consciously carve out time to refuel these connections evey once so often, they will slowly dry out. The key here really is to decide to spend time on reaching out to old friends, and specially if you are geographically separated. 12. Prioritize recovery. Exercise is important, but if you don’t want to jeopardize your results and energy levels, put recovery at the top of your priority list.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collaborative Platforms for Synthetic Biology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/06/03/OECDCollaborativePlatforms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collaborative Platforms for Synthetic Biology" /><published>2022-06-03T15:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-03T15:56:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/06/03/OECDCollaborativePlatforms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/06/03/OECDCollaborativePlatforms.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/biofoundry1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Biofoundry&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/biofoundry2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Biofoundry&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/biofoundry3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Biofoundry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Some shots from NIST biofoundry &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nist.gov/feature-stories/nist-biofoundry-taking-engineering-biology-artisanal-automated&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;[source]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I give rundown of some key points I distilled from OECD study &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/innovation/collaborative-platforms-for-emerging-technology-ed1e030d-en.htm&quot;&gt;“Collaborative platforms for emerging technology: Creating convergence spaces”&lt;/a&gt; that appeared last year in the series &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1787/23074957&quot;&gt;OECD Science, Technology and Industry Policy Papers&lt;/a&gt;. The study aims to support policy makers and innovators to realize the potential of emerging technologies through collaborative platforms. What is a collaborative platform I hear you ask? Don’t worry we will get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question I focused in this overview mainly on is: “What policies would allow the expansion of biological engineering and enable broader community of innovators to commercialize new bio-based products?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this important? Private actors always face risks with new investments, and engineering biology is no exception. Usual financial risks are exacerbated by longer development times and customer opinion on biologically engineered products can shift rapidly to unfavorable stance. Consequently, strong public support is usually needed to make the investments attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaborative-platforms&quot;&gt;Collaborative platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, back to your question - what are those collaborative platforms? In a nutshell collaborative platforms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are organizational arrangements around shared resources, across private and public sector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow different partners (across academia, industry and public sphere) to work together in new ways, accelerating innovation and value creation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative platforms, when they materialize as physical infrastructure, are places where technological innovations melt together to deliver more value and often lead to development of new technologies. Already this short summary makes it quite apparent that establishing such platform and keeping it running requires substantial investments, and that such infrastructure must continuously attract and train scientific staff with expertise across multiple disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;collaborative-platforms-for-engineering-biology&quot;&gt;Collaborative platforms for engineering biology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my focus in this summary is mainly on physical infrastructure (so the first two bullet points below), more abstract arrangements also further the mission of collaborative platforms. Zooming on engineering biology, those are the platform the paper highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biofoundry: highly automated facility implementing Design-Build-Test-Learn (DBTL) cycle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biological research center&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: a physical repository of molecular biological diversity (basically preserving cells of many organisms together with their annotated genomes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human capital infrastructure: an abstract place where core stakeholders and top researchers in given field interact (in practice this can be independent advisory bodies or boards of research consortia such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebrc.org/&quot;&gt;EBRC&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demonstrator facility: Infrastructure between pilot and full scale production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, lets keep the focus on biofoundries. Note that while they are the most often thought of as centralized, it can also be a network of distributed infrastructure units (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilebiofoundry.org&quot;&gt;Agile Biofoundry in US&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/biofoundry_dbtl.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Design - Build - Test - Learn Cycle at biofoundry and the various roles of a biofoundry. Image taken directly from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/innovation/collaborative-platforms-for-emerging-technology-ed1e030d-en.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;[report]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-suggestions-for-design-of-collaborative-platforms&quot;&gt;Policy suggestions for design of collaborative platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meat of the paper is in providing suggestions for policy makers on how to successfully kickstart collaborative platforms. We already know that this is one of the important ways how to incentivize innovation in biological engineering as government involvement in collaborative platforms can incentivize and de-risk private investments in emerging technologies. The overall goal should be to make the platform as accessible as possible across sectors for various actors across sectors as its increased usage will mostly lead to its increased value for existing and new users (so called network effect). Here are the major recommendations from the paper as I identified them, with added accent on biological engineering:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design access and IP policies that maximize usage of platform’s resources and interaction among users (e.g. smaller actors pay less)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider education and training as created value
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;consider also professional training and collaboration with institutions other than higher ed (such as vocational schools, community colleges, …)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;contribute to undergrad and grad programs by providing platform to develop more tech- and data savvy- biologists&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer job security despite project-based funding (long term commitment needed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leverage collaborative platforms as spaces to implement shared mission, potentially across borders (e.g. development of new sustainable materials and food products or biosurveillaince)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards are necessity and should be implemented via industry consensus with sufficient flexibility to allow growth and innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement strong data management systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use collaborative platforms as space to engage with broader society (e.g. build a productive two-sided dialogue around GMOs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next to private investments, judge platform performance by other metrics, especially in early stages (patents, job creation, publications, …)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Life cycle analysis (LCA) of new products to demonstrate their sustainability in robust manner is likely to become more common. Consider adopting it early.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;governance-of-collaborative-platforms&quot;&gt;Governance of collaborative platforms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are commonly not entirely in place for emerging technologies and collaborative platforms help to shape them through various modes of governance. Here the most salient points from the report on this topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emerging technologies are most often governed collaboratively, by governmental and private actors. Development of governance often includes feedback from civil society.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;multiple strategies are often pursued simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;governance both top-down (e.g. restrictions on access) and bottom-up (standardization and propagation of social roles and values)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standards delivery competitive advantage and support network effects&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;create compatibility, facilitate automation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;provide assurance of safety and quality and thus enhance consumer and investor confidence&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;approaches-to-govern-intellectual-property-in-collaborative-platforms&quot;&gt;Approaches to govern intellectual property in collaborative platforms&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative platforms are by their definition places where different actors across academia, industry and public sphere come together, often with the goal to innovate and develop new products or technologies. How such platforms will manage intellectually property (IP) is a critical design decisions that they need to take early on. Here are four possible ways how to do so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Platforms own IP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP is held and managed by parent research institution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP policy depends on platform usage or project type&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaboration agreements determine IP rights before the project onset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the most prevalent mode of IP management at collaborative platforms, and in particular in biofoundries, is number &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt; - IP is held by parent research institution. While this has been a common practice in academic settings, it is rarely attractive for private partners, which would usually prefer approaches &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt; that give them more straightforward access to the resulting IP. In option &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; this could be for example by buying IP rights for project’s cost plus some form of ‘success fee’ derived from commercialization success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative platforms are important hotbeds of innovation, with marked importance for emerging technologies and markets. They can have wide spread positive impacts ranging from implementing ‘mission-type’ solutions (e.g. as responses to societal and environmental issues that are not currently economically viable and may have to be incentivized), crafting fields’ governance, accelerating technology transfer, and managing open debate with public, among many others. In the field of biological engineering, biofoundries are the most prominent examples of collaborative platforms with physical presence. While &lt;a href=&quot;https://biofoundries.org/&quot;&gt;many countries have already embraced this paradigm&lt;/a&gt;, many more are still considering it or lacking further behind. The recommendations and experiences highlighted in the report, while useful across the board, will be of the most use to policymakers and stakeholders in early stages of platform establishment, who seek to install good practices in this rapidly developing space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
* Biofoundries can play role in prototyping standards, methods for (diagnostic) testing
  - Can also leverage computational resources for e.g. modeling of proteins/targets/molecules and data analysis

---&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1787/9789264193550-en&quot;&gt;Biological Resource Centers&lt;/a&gt;, check also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.earthbiogenome.org/&quot;&gt;Earth Biogenome Project&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nbt.2017.05.001&quot;&gt;de Lorenzo, V. and M. Schmidt (2018), Biological standards for the Knowledge-Based BioEconomy: What is at stake&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="SynBio" /><category term="policy" /><category term="SynBio" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Some shots from NIST biofoundry [source] Introduction In this post I give rundown of some key points I distilled from OECD study “Collaborative platforms for emerging technology: Creating convergence spaces” that appeared last year in the series OECD Science, Technology and Industry Policy Papers. The study aims to support policy makers and innovators to realize the potential of emerging technologies through collaborative platforms. What is a collaborative platform I hear you ask? Don’t worry we will get there. The question I focused in this overview mainly on is: “What policies would allow the expansion of biological engineering and enable broader community of innovators to commercialize new bio-based products?” Why is this important? Private actors always face risks with new investments, and engineering biology is no exception. Usual financial risks are exacerbated by longer development times and customer opinion on biologically engineered products can shift rapidly to unfavorable stance. Consequently, strong public support is usually needed to make the investments attractive. Collaborative platforms OK, back to your question - what are those collaborative platforms? In a nutshell collaborative platforms: are organizational arrangements around shared resources, across private and public sector allow different partners (across academia, industry and public sphere) to work together in new ways, accelerating innovation and value creation Collaborative platforms, when they materialize as physical infrastructure, are places where technological innovations melt together to deliver more value and often lead to development of new technologies. Already this short summary makes it quite apparent that establishing such platform and keeping it running requires substantial investments, and that such infrastructure must continuously attract and train scientific staff with expertise across multiple disciplines. Collaborative platforms for engineering biology While my focus in this summary is mainly on physical infrastructure (so the first two bullet points below), more abstract arrangements also further the mission of collaborative platforms. Zooming on engineering biology, those are the platform the paper highlights: Biofoundry: highly automated facility implementing Design-Build-Test-Learn (DBTL) cycle Biological research center1: a physical repository of molecular biological diversity (basically preserving cells of many organisms together with their annotated genomes) Human capital infrastructure: an abstract place where core stakeholders and top researchers in given field interact (in practice this can be independent advisory bodies or boards of research consortia such as EBRC) Demonstrator facility: Infrastructure between pilot and full scale production For now, lets keep the focus on biofoundries. Note that while they are the most often thought of as centralized, it can also be a network of distributed infrastructure units (such as Agile Biofoundry in US). Design - Build - Test - Learn Cycle at biofoundry and the various roles of a biofoundry. Image taken directly from the [report] Policy suggestions for design of collaborative platforms The meat of the paper is in providing suggestions for policy makers on how to successfully kickstart collaborative platforms. We already know that this is one of the important ways how to incentivize innovation in biological engineering as government involvement in collaborative platforms can incentivize and de-risk private investments in emerging technologies. The overall goal should be to make the platform as accessible as possible across sectors for various actors across sectors as its increased usage will mostly lead to its increased value for existing and new users (so called network effect). Here are the major recommendations from the paper as I identified them, with added accent on biological engineering: Design access and IP policies that maximize usage of platform’s resources and interaction among users (e.g. smaller actors pay less) Consider education and training as created value consider also professional training and collaboration with institutions other than higher ed (such as vocational schools, community colleges, …) contribute to undergrad and grad programs by providing platform to develop more tech- and data savvy- biologists Offer job security despite project-based funding (long term commitment needed) Leverage collaborative platforms as spaces to implement shared mission, potentially across borders (e.g. development of new sustainable materials and food products or biosurveillaince) Standards are necessity and should be implemented via industry consensus with sufficient flexibility to allow growth and innovation Implement strong data management systems Use collaborative platforms as space to engage with broader society (e.g. build a productive two-sided dialogue around GMOs) Next to private investments, judge platform performance by other metrics, especially in early stages (patents, job creation, publications, …) Life cycle analysis (LCA) of new products to demonstrate their sustainability in robust manner is likely to become more common. Consider adopting it early. Governance of collaborative platforms Markets are commonly not entirely in place for emerging technologies and collaborative platforms help to shape them through various modes of governance. Here the most salient points from the report on this topic: Emerging technologies are most often governed collaboratively, by governmental and private actors. Development of governance often includes feedback from civil society. multiple strategies are often pursued simultaneously governance both top-down (e.g. restrictions on access) and bottom-up (standardization and propagation of social roles and values) Standards delivery competitive advantage and support network effects2 create compatibility, facilitate automation provide assurance of safety and quality and thus enhance consumer and investor confidence Approaches to govern intellectual property in collaborative platforms Collaborative platforms are by their definition places where different actors across academia, industry and public sphere come together, often with the goal to innovate and develop new products or technologies. How such platforms will manage intellectually property (IP) is a critical design decisions that they need to take early on. Here are four possible ways how to do so: Platforms own IP IP is held and managed by parent research institution IP policy depends on platform usage or project type Collaboration agreements determine IP rights before the project onset Currently, the most prevalent mode of IP management at collaborative platforms, and in particular in biofoundries, is number 2 - IP is held by parent research institution. While this has been a common practice in academic settings, it is rarely attractive for private partners, which would usually prefer approaches 3 or 4 that give them more straightforward access to the resulting IP. In option 3 this could be for example by buying IP rights for project’s cost plus some form of ‘success fee’ derived from commercialization success. Conclusion Collaborative platforms are important hotbeds of innovation, with marked importance for emerging technologies and markets. They can have wide spread positive impacts ranging from implementing ‘mission-type’ solutions (e.g. as responses to societal and environmental issues that are not currently economically viable and may have to be incentivized), crafting fields’ governance, accelerating technology transfer, and managing open debate with public, among many others. In the field of biological engineering, biofoundries are the most prominent examples of collaborative platforms with physical presence. While many countries have already embraced this paradigm, many more are still considering it or lacking further behind. The recommendations and experiences highlighted in the report, while useful across the board, will be of the most use to policymakers and stakeholders in early stages of platform establishment, who seek to install good practices in this rapidly developing space. Footnotes Biological Resource Centers, check also Earth Biogenome Project &amp;#8617; de Lorenzo, V. and M. Schmidt (2018), Biological standards for the Knowledge-Based BioEconomy: What is at stake &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Convention on Biological Diversity Technical Series on Synthetic Biology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/05/20/CBDSynBio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Convention on Biological Diversity Technical Series on Synthetic Biology" /><published>2022-05-20T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-20T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/05/20/CBDSynBio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/synbio/policy/2022/05/20/CBDSynBio.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/cbd_synbio.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Cover page of the report
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbd.int/&quot;&gt;Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD)&lt;/a&gt; is a multilateral treaty with the objective to develop national strategies for the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity. As such, it is often seen as a key document regarding sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CBD has two supplementary agreements, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartagena_Protocol_on_Biosafety&quot;&gt;Cartagena Protocol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagoya_Protocol&quot;&gt;Nagoya Protocol&lt;/a&gt;. The former deals with international shipments of genetically modified organisms. The latter provides a legal framework for the equitable sharing of benefits of utilization of genetic resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the CBD is a treaty which became effective on 29th December 1993, it lead to establishment of several international bodies that continue to operate to date. The CBD Secretariat is based in Montreal, Canada and operates under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unep.org/&quot;&gt;United Nations Environment Programme&lt;/a&gt;.  Its main functions are to organize meetings, draft documents and assist member governments in the implementation of the CBD treaty. In this capacity, it has published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbd.int/ts/&quot;&gt;Technical Series note (No. 100)&lt;/a&gt; that I will summarize below. The topic of the note is Synthetic Biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parties to the CBD have demonstrated interest in the potential impacts of synthetic biology (SynBio) on the goals of the CBD and requested to write a technical note on the subject, which updates a note on the topic published in 2015. The document was peer-reviewed within one month by one individual, seventeen countries, two intergovernmental organizations and twenty-nine other organizations. A total of 2005 comments were received during the process. The technical work underlying the document was supported by grants from the Governments of Austria and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;selected-takeaways&quot;&gt;Selected takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The over 200 page document comes with a great 13-point summary. I personally found some of those points overlapping or otherwise redundant, so I am providing a summary of the points that I found personally the most interesting below. If you find them relevant, you should certainly also check the original summary (references to its key points are included) and potentially the whole document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no internationally agreed definition of synthetic biology, which in turn poses challenges to its governance. (#2)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The global synthetic biology market was estimated at US$ 6.8 billion in 2020 and is projected to grow at 23.9% compound annual growth rate through 2025 (#3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The majority of synthetic biology products are produced in containment (e.g. synthetic DNA, RNA and oligonucleotides) (#3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and development in SynBio mostly occurs in limited number of countries. 70.6% of synthetic biology research is funded by mere 20 agencies (6 USA, 3 China, 2 Canada, 2 Germany, 2 Japan, 2 UK, 2 EU and 1 South Korea) (#4)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most commercial applications of synthetic biology to date are reserved for contained industrial or laboratory settings (e.g. cosmetics and fragrances, food ingredients and flavors, fabrics). New applications are increasingly targeting (semi-)managed, urban and unmanaged settings where interaction with the biodiversity of the environment are more likely or even desired (#5, #6). There is little data to assess impact of these technologies on the environment. (#5, #6)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assessment of impact of new products is complex. Discussions with involved stakeholders, incl. communities, is vital and cannot be circumvented. Substitution of synthetic alternative for a natural product, while seemingly having clear net positive environmental impact, could for example displace traditional cultivation practices and aggravate fragile economic condition of small producers. (#7, #8, #9)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While biosecurity of synthetic biology is already receiving some attention, it could be further advanced by increased transparency, communication with the public and policymakers and pro-active self-regulation (#10)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resources will be needed for development and update of various regulatory systems that relate to synthetic biology. It is likely that these resources will be lacking especially in countries that already have under-developed regulatory structure (incl. biosafety) (#11)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthetic biology is at the moment governed by multitude of institutions at various levels, without a global overarching framework. The breadth of the field and the current regulatory structure suggest that the most effective development in international governance will be achieved by individual stakeholders engaging in consortia and broader initiatives in order to facilitate coordination and adoption of norms. (#12)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As SynBio is young and rapidly evolving field, early foresight of upcoming technologies is important for timely development of appropriate regulation. (#13)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat to the CBD and the Parties to the CBD recognize need to &lt;strong&gt;i)&lt;/strong&gt; better integrate and coordinate governance of synthetic biology and &lt;strong&gt;ii)&lt;/strong&gt; to expand the focus beyond biosafety, human health and the physical environment to include social and ethical impacts taking into account national contexts. New governance methods, integration with social sciences and engagement with involved stakeholders and communities will be required in the regulatory development, accounting for the ability to foster scientific creativity and to allow effective, yet responsible, new product development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biodiversity-day&quot;&gt;Biodiversity Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while you are reading this: 22nd of May is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbd.int/biodiversity-day&quot;&gt;Biodiversity Day&lt;/a&gt;! Check the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbd.int/biodiversity-day/activities/22&quot;&gt;22 actions for biodiversity that anyone can do&lt;/a&gt;!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/idb-logo-en-web.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Biodiversity Day 2022 is on May 22nd!!!
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="SynBio" /><category term="policy" /><category term="SynBio" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Cover page of the report Introduction The Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) is a multilateral treaty with the objective to develop national strategies for the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity. As such, it is often seen as a key document regarding sustainable development. The CBD has two supplementary agreements, the Cartagena Protocol and Nagoya Protocol. The former deals with international shipments of genetically modified organisms. The latter provides a legal framework for the equitable sharing of benefits of utilization of genetic resources. While the CBD is a treaty which became effective on 29th December 1993, it lead to establishment of several international bodies that continue to operate to date. The CBD Secretariat is based in Montreal, Canada and operates under the United Nations Environment Programme. Its main functions are to organize meetings, draft documents and assist member governments in the implementation of the CBD treaty. In this capacity, it has published a Technical Series note (No. 100) that I will summarize below. The topic of the note is Synthetic Biology. The parties to the CBD have demonstrated interest in the potential impacts of synthetic biology (SynBio) on the goals of the CBD and requested to write a technical note on the subject, which updates a note on the topic published in 2015. The document was peer-reviewed within one month by one individual, seventeen countries, two intergovernmental organizations and twenty-nine other organizations. A total of 2005 comments were received during the process. The technical work underlying the document was supported by grants from the Governments of Austria and the Netherlands. Selected takeaways The over 200 page document comes with a great 13-point summary. I personally found some of those points overlapping or otherwise redundant, so I am providing a summary of the points that I found personally the most interesting below. If you find them relevant, you should certainly also check the original summary (references to its key points are included) and potentially the whole document. There is no internationally agreed definition of synthetic biology, which in turn poses challenges to its governance. (#2) The global synthetic biology market was estimated at US$ 6.8 billion in 2020 and is projected to grow at 23.9% compound annual growth rate through 2025 (#3) The majority of synthetic biology products are produced in containment (e.g. synthetic DNA, RNA and oligonucleotides) (#3) Research and development in SynBio mostly occurs in limited number of countries. 70.6% of synthetic biology research is funded by mere 20 agencies (6 USA, 3 China, 2 Canada, 2 Germany, 2 Japan, 2 UK, 2 EU and 1 South Korea) (#4) Most commercial applications of synthetic biology to date are reserved for contained industrial or laboratory settings (e.g. cosmetics and fragrances, food ingredients and flavors, fabrics). New applications are increasingly targeting (semi-)managed, urban and unmanaged settings where interaction with the biodiversity of the environment are more likely or even desired (#5, #6). There is little data to assess impact of these technologies on the environment. (#5, #6) Assessment of impact of new products is complex. Discussions with involved stakeholders, incl. communities, is vital and cannot be circumvented. Substitution of synthetic alternative for a natural product, while seemingly having clear net positive environmental impact, could for example displace traditional cultivation practices and aggravate fragile economic condition of small producers. (#7, #8, #9) While biosecurity of synthetic biology is already receiving some attention, it could be further advanced by increased transparency, communication with the public and policymakers and pro-active self-regulation (#10) Resources will be needed for development and update of various regulatory systems that relate to synthetic biology. It is likely that these resources will be lacking especially in countries that already have under-developed regulatory structure (incl. biosafety) (#11) Synthetic biology is at the moment governed by multitude of institutions at various levels, without a global overarching framework. The breadth of the field and the current regulatory structure suggest that the most effective development in international governance will be achieved by individual stakeholders engaging in consortia and broader initiatives in order to facilitate coordination and adoption of norms. (#12) As SynBio is young and rapidly evolving field, early foresight of upcoming technologies is important for timely development of appropriate regulation. (#13) Conclusion The Secretariat to the CBD and the Parties to the CBD recognize need to i) better integrate and coordinate governance of synthetic biology and ii) to expand the focus beyond biosafety, human health and the physical environment to include social and ethical impacts taking into account national contexts. New governance methods, integration with social sciences and engagement with involved stakeholders and communities will be required in the regulatory development, accounting for the ability to foster scientific creativity and to allow effective, yet responsible, new product development. Biodiversity Day And while you are reading this: 22nd of May is Biodiversity Day! Check the 22 actions for biodiversity that anyone can do!!! Biodiversity Day 2022 is on May 22nd!!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I Became Conversational in Dutch in Less Than Six Months and Without an Instructor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/education/nl/2022/01/30/LearningDutch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I Became Conversational in Dutch in Less Than Six Months and Without an Instructor" /><published>2022-01-30T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-30T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/education/nl/2022/01/30/LearningDutch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/education/nl/2022/01/30/LearningDutch.html">&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/nietperfectisookgoed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Translation: Not perfect is also fine!
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How did you learn Dutch so well and so quick?” I get this question often. I am in the few percent of expats who can hold fluent conversation and I got to this point in seemingly no time. And while my Dutch is by no means perfect, it gets the job done. Which is what matters to me and what I take some amount of pride in. Here I will describe how I become fluent in under half a year, without an instructor, while working a full-time job where I did not use any Dutch. What’s more, while I will give Dutch-specific references the approach can be applied to virtually any language, it can cost you as no money, and does not require you to live in place where you would use the learnt language (although that would usually help with the motivation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-a-foreign-language-do-i-have-to&quot;&gt;Learning a foreign language, do I have to?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me get this clear straight away - no you don’t. In most of common expat locations you will be fine with English and people wont frown upon you. There is plenty of good reasons for not doing it. Do you already have few hobbies that you enjoy and that take up all of your free time?  Don’t feel guilty for not squeezing in time for language learning. Are you perfectly set in your social and work life and don’t feel need for mingling with the locals? That’s fine too.
That being said, there are also bad reason. Would you love to speak the language, but are afraid of the embarrassing moments when you try to appear smart with the vocabulary of a three year old and pronunciation of someone after palsy? Then it should not stop you - go ahead and start learning, your fear of embarrassment and your perfectionism will eventually even help you to be better at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-a-foreign-language-how-long-will-it-take&quot;&gt;Learning a foreign language, how long will it take?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When deciding if to learn a new language, you should evaluate the investment if time end effort is worth if for you. For that you will need to know what your target level at that language is, how long do you expect to have to learn it to reach that level and what is the opportunity cost - the things you &lt;strong&gt;won’t&lt;/strong&gt; be doing because you are learning the new language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, I guess you saw this coming, learning a new language is a substantial commitment of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look how the decision process looked for me when it came to Dutch.
I lived in the Netherlands for whole one year, refusing to learn any of their language. I got by with English perfectly fine. Not showing any interest in Dutch was sort of a personal revolt against the terrible weather and other things that made me dislike the country (that’s of course a curse of all expats, after brief spell of seeing only the great things, we go through somewhat longer period of seeing only the things that are wretched about this god damn new place we decided to move into, god knows why, for f\&lt;em&gt;\&lt;/em&gt;k’s sake).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/expat_curve.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
Expat curve
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About after one year living here (December 2020), I collected some positive experiences that convinced me the country is not all that bad. I thus decided to be a good immigrant and learn the local language. My goal was to become conversational by the end of 2021. The goal is important - I was not interested in writing essays, I did not want to brim with eloquence - I just wanted to get to the point when I can talk with anybody about anything - how many mistakes I make was not that important as long as I could make myself understood and the conversation could flow naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dedicated one morning a week to learning the grammar and established a routine when I was putting in about an hour of learning on most of the other days.
I became conversational much sooner than expected, roughly in May 2021. With average investment of 8 hours per week, in six months this amounts to under 200 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can expect similar amount of time if you have reasons to think that the language you will learn will be rather easy for you (for example because you already learnt couple of languages, or because it resembles a language you already know). In most other cases, you should double the estimate (to 400 hours) to reach similar goal as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-am-down-for-it-how-do-i-even-start&quot;&gt;I am down for it. How do I even start?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so you evaluated the pro’s and con’s, found place in your crammed agenda, and decided to learn a new language. Congratulations! (If you decided not to learn and are still reading - stop! you have better things to do, don’t you?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first - where do you even start? In the beginning, you don’t know anything about the new language - so you need to make the learning as easy for yourself as possible. Luckily there is dozens of apps that aim to make the learning almost as much fun and half as addictive as scrolling your social media feed. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.duolingo.com/&quot;&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt; and that’s what I would recommend for many, if not most, languages too (I heard good stuff about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hellochinese.cc/&quot;&gt;Hello Chinese&lt;/a&gt; for, guess what, Chinese – Mandarin in this case). I would advocate for using an app on your phone rather than a website on your PC – in my experience, it is easier to build a habit from it this way and it feels less like work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using just Duolingo, you will easily reach level A2 in a month or two. Critically, listen to the app’s advice on how to learn the most effectively! Does the app suggest that you should pronounce the words and phrases out loud? Then do it and do it every time because if you don’t you are not using your time efficiently. Does the app tell you to write down all new words? Ditto - do it. Such pieces of advice are based on solid research on how to learn efficiently, you ignore them at your own disservice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I aimed to finish the whole Dutch course on Duolingo (7 units), completing each lesson to level 1 (which equaled to about 10’000 XP). I found that in that way I have seen most of what it has to offer. Towards the end (maybe the last two or three units), I started feeling I was not getting that much new content anymore, but I stuck with it just to complete all the units. I did Duolingo consistently every day for close to two months. I wrote down all new phrases into a document on my computer and noted all new words. I also read through Duolingo’s grammar guide for Dutch. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-your-vocabulary&quot;&gt;Building your vocabulary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no going around this, language learning requires lot of memorizing. You will need to be able to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fluentu.com/blog/how-many-words-do-i-need-to-know/&quot;&gt;somewhere between couple of hundred to few thousands words&lt;/a&gt; to be conversational at your desired level and you will need to cram them in your head. When it comes to memorizing stuff for long term, there is a fail-proof strategy: repeated exposure. You will want to have seen and understood a word many times before it will become part of your vocabulary.
I tested many strategies for learning new words - looking up a word every time I encounter it, having a dedicated paper notebook and paper flashcards are just some examples. Finally, I settled on a strategy that works extremely well for me. Here it is: every time I encounter a new word, first, I write it down (it is great if you can write down the context too, but I am almost always too lazy/busy at that moment, and just write down the word) … and then I don’t do anything with that word.
Yes, you read correctly, note every new word, and then don’t do anything with it. It does not make sense, you think? Well, it does and does not - you should not do anything &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, you should look up all the new words whenever you have lot of them written down already. This way you efficiently batch your time between consuming new content and doing some work on it.
Sounds pretty straightforward, right? For the most part it is, but there is also a catch, after looking up the new word, you will forget it extremely quickly, sometimes within minutes, sometimes within seconds. No matter how annoying, it is fine that way -  that’s how our minds evolved to practically function in a word abounding with stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will thus need to find a way how to re-expose yourself to the new word couple of times. I am using &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; for this. Anki is a mobile and (importantly) also computer app where you can create your own flashcards. You can really go wild with them, with many custom fields, embedded images and even sound files and recordings. The app automates the learning process for you - it will expose you to chosen number of words each day, and prompt you for your level of confidence in remembering the meaning of each word. The better you know a word already, the later in the future it will be showed again. The fact that you can run the app on your computer too (and synchronize the content with your mobile devices) is invaluable when creating new flashcards - I highly suggest doing this on your laptop or PC, you will be much quicker than doing it on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of my flashcards has the following fields:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Front (the new word or phrase in the language I am learning)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back (the new word in language(s) I already know)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Article / Conjugation (whichever applies)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meaning (explanation in the language I am learning, usually with synonyms and sometimes antonyms)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples (some examples of usage in context)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I would throw in an image or a pronunciation as a sound file. In Anki, you can drag and drop the file on any field to automatically insert it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/anki_new_card.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
This is how each of my new cards in Anki look like.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating flashcards or looking up new words, you will need a good dictionary. I never had any issue finding a good one available online for free. I would always use multiple dictionaries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thesaurus (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vandale.nl/&quot;&gt;Van Dale for Dutch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.larousse.fr/&quot;&gt;Larousee&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lerobert.com/&quot;&gt;Le Robert&lt;/a&gt; for French.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;English / Target-Language dictionary (oftentimes from the same source as above)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Database of contexts (I used &lt;a href=&quot;reverso.com&quot;&gt;Reverso&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specialized dictionaries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think it is fun to learn some slang or expressive language too, for that I would usually some sort of street-language dictionary (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www. straatwoordenboek.nl&quot;&gt;straatwoordenboek.nl&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.straattaalwoordenboek.nl&quot;&gt;straattaalwoordenboek.nl&lt;/a&gt; for Dutch)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can recommend all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from creating your own flashcards on Anki, you can also download &lt;a href=&quot;https://ankiweb.net/shared/decks/dutch&quot;&gt;a deck someone else created&lt;/a&gt; and use it! While this is somewhat less beneficial and could be arguably skipped, I still found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ankiweb.net/shared/info/665133953&quot;&gt;one with Dutch phrases (audio and text) useful&lt;/a&gt; – it will help you too if you, as with Duolingo, pronounce the sentences out loud. I usually did this immediately before or after my daily Duolingo routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-new-language-is-it-any-fun&quot;&gt;Learning new language, is it any fun?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, while the apps mentioned above will make the learning feel quite smooth, and they do their best to build a habit and make the learning somewhat automatized, there are not exactly fun. It will still feel like studying. So it is time to inject some more fun into your language learning. By now, you will be around level A2, maybe even B1 if you have done some grammar work (see my comment on Duolingo’s grammar above), which means you should be able to understand basic written and spoken text. That’s when learning becomes fun. You should pick any medium in the language you are learning and then just try your best at it, still noting every new word and phrase you encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest you pick a written text, because that one is truly self-paced (you can read as quickly, or slowly, as you feel you need to, and you can even reread parts of text), but podcasts or video will work too. I like books, and I therefore picked one in Dutch to start with.  Often you will be advised to pick a simplified reading or book for children. I don’t like that advice, rather I suggest you pick a book that you would like to read because of it contents, and it just happens to be in the language you are learning (I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infidel:_My_Life&quot;&gt;‘Mijn vrijheid’&lt;/a&gt; from Ayaan-Hirsi Ali which is stunning autobiography of social and human-right activist, a Dutch immi- and emi-grant, that I can certainly recommend). That being said, no matter how much you may love 18th century historical novels, this is not the time to read them. You should opt for something with contemporary language as your entry book :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;total-immersion&quot;&gt;Total immersion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Books are great, but they will not be enough to reach your language goals quickly. You will see the best results if you endeavor on strategy of ‘totally immersion’. It is what it sounds like, you should try to surround yourself with the new language as much as possible.
At this moment you are probably not good enough to start speaking it (this will depend on how shy or not you are, I on the shy side so was not yet at the point of using the language in conversations), so you will have to do with passive consumption. But you are lucky, the internet has you covered when it comes to easily digestible entertaining content. I personally enjoy listening to podcasts and watching video on demand - so I switched them both almost entirely to Dutch. I threw some music on top of that too. All of these are cool also because next to the language, you will be learning more about the country’s culture, something that is usually really fun and broadens your horizons quickly.
It will be great if you still can keep noting every new word you encounter, but do not be too hard on yourself. You are having fun in the end. For example, I would never note new words while listening to music or podcasts and only very seldomly when watching videos. And it still worked out fine for me. Also do not worry if you do not understand everything. You need to be able to get the gist (if that is not the case, choose slower play rate, different content or watch videos with subtitles) and that already will allow you to develop feeling and train your ear for the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;grammar-grammar-&quot;&gt;Grammar? Grammar! ☹&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, you are having some fun learning the new language, and you are seeing some progress. By now you are too invested to just drop it at a whim. It is thus a good time to do some nasty work - learning grammar. I do not care what you may have heard - if you want to use the language actively (speaking, texting, writing, …) you will need to understand its rules. Luckily, it will not be as bad as you may fear. I would strongly suggest going tech-free for the grammar learning process. I got a grammar-book that comes together with a workbook (which also had solutions available at the end). Then I would go through it, page by page, and whenever I would finish a grammar section, I would do the associated exercises. I would then check their correctness against the solutions and use red marker to correct my mistakes.
That’s it, that’s how I learnt grammar. The exercises are essential, and you will need to do plenty of them, but it is sort of work that can be bit-sized almost infinitely - even if you just have couple of minutes, you can do an exercise and correct it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/learn-grammar-you-must.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
This fella always has a point, right?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to commit to work on it regularly (for me this was Saturday mornings) and to commit to finishing the whole book. You will be then able to see your progress as you move through it, and you will have a clear endpoint. Some argument can be made for skipping section of the book that you do not find all that useful for your particular case (for example you may not need to use much of indirect speech, that mostly employed by journalists and politicians). I like to do these sections too as it gives me more complete grasp of the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are done with the book, I recommend that you make your own personal grammar summary. I again suggest doing it by pen and paper, use colors and do as much cross-referencing as your find practical. You go through the just-finished books and write as-concise-as-possible summary of all the grammar phenomena that you find useful. You should pay special attention to those where you made the most mistakes (remember the red marker?) - but be practical - is it for example in archaic or bureaucratic language that you erred? Then chances are that you will never really use it that much, and you needn’t worry about mistakes you made.
Once you have completed your first version of grammar summary, you can transfer it to an electronic document, that way it will be easier to add stuff in the future as you keep learning(I did that, and I am now at over 25 pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one additional grammar tip: you can get &lt;a href=&quot;https://beterspellen.nl/website/index.php&quot;&gt;Better Spellen&lt;/a&gt; app on your phone which will supply you with 12 grammar questions every workday. Sometimes these are quite tricky, even a native speaker would struggle, so you should not do this before you have finished your grammar book. It is efficient; the questions take just a short time to answer, and I am usually done with them in 3 or 4 minutes. After giving your answers you are provided with solutions with link to very detailed explanation of that given grammar phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;can-we-have-some-fun-again&quot;&gt;Can we have some fun again?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have been through the drudgery of grammar, it is time to reward yourself. You will do this by using the language you have been working so hard to learn. You could probably start with either writing or speaking, but I would advocate for speaking. You would have done bit of writing (usually single sentences) by now during your grammar exercises, and for most people, speaking will be their goal anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best place when to start using the language is in low stakes environment. This can be with your friends, in a meet-up or during language exchange. Chances are, no matter where you live, that there already is a small community of people learning the same language you are - join it and hone your skills in this environment. I used to attend language meetups back in the Czech Republic when I was learning French and not only did it improve my ability to speak, but I made new friends and had good time (which was all worth the regular headache from too much red wine afterwards). I was learning Dutch during COVID pandemic, which came with multitude of restrictions on social lives of most. I thus opted to start speaking during an online exchange which I was doing with a Dutch student who wanted to learn some Czech.  It was an excellent decision (thanks Carel!) - not only this creates an extremely safe environment for you to practice, but you can get the feel-good vibes from teach something to the other person too. Finally, as this was online and we were just two involved, it was very efficient.  I kept doing this for about two months before I noticed I am hitting somewhat diminishing returns. We continued the exchange nevertheless for few more months afterwards, because it remained enjoyable, and the other guy had more work to on their Czech than I had on my Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have been able to use the new language couple of times in your safe ‘training’ environment of choice, you are ready for the next step - using the language to speak to strangers. If you live in the country where the language you are learning this will be simple and should become part of your everyday life. There is no good excuse for not doing it, the people you engage with will be almost universally happy with your attempts and often will compliment you for your efforts, which will be both great reward and motivation for ongoing learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, that is if you cannot use the language where you live, you will probably have to continue the (online) language exchange and meetups for longer. In such cases it would be good to switch the focus from language learning to some topic-specific meetups - pursuing your interests and hobbies while continuing to learn the new language. In both above cases, you can usually do some email writing to practice simple written communication (think of inquiring about some organization or institution, booking your next vacation or maybe even using the language for work purposes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-am-conversational-whats-next&quot;&gt;I am conversational, what’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, you will want to, aside from using it, continue learning the language even after reaching your initial goal. Usually this will be at reduced pace. For example, I continue reading in Dutch and I keep expanding my set of flashcards with new words and phrases (I am now actually reading the 18th century history novel and while I can progress through it comfortably, I encounter many words that I have not seen before because they are not that commonly used anymore).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, such as when you want to communicate to larger audiences or when you want to pass advanced (C1 and C2) language proficiency exams, you will have to take your language to yet next level.
To do that, you should start writing longer pieces of text. What those would be depends on your goals and interests, but short stories, columns and essays are all good candidates. You could also start with blogging and slowly transition to the above forms as they, in contrast to blog which is usually written in quite a plain language (such as this one), lend themselves more naturally to advanced language use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that writing at this stage is essential. I went through this process for English (when I was preparing for C2-level exams). After a plateau in language learning, this was something that truly allowed me to level up and quite rapidly.
 It is only in writing that you will have enough time and space to use more elaborate constructions, to review and rewrite and when you will be able to dig into your memory or even a dictionary to find an eloquent synonym. Once you have been able to use those in writing, they will slowly find their way to your speech too. If you realize that your vocabulary is not yet large enough, you will also need to expand it simultaneously. While you could do this by reading more, that will usually be pretty low-efficiency (as the advanced language constructions you want to learn will come up only rarely) - this would be another good time to get a good textbook - aimed at writers and other very advanced users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your writing at this point will be nearing the level of essays and novels (though probably not in content :)) and you want it to be grammatically very correct - you won’t be able to proof-read this alone and you will thus want someone who is either learning at the same or higher level or someone native who has very good language use themself to review your text and point to places where you need to improve and adjust. If you aim to communicate to public anyway, you could consider asking your audiences to provide you with feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning new language is great hobby with many benefits. On my example described here you can see that while it is quite some work, it is all manageable - and that in few months and even without any instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have reached your goals in learning new language yourself, you should justly congratulate yourself. You have worked hard, and you have seen your efforts transform into results. Aside from having learnt a new language, you now have a very personal example of how your own initiative and directed work can transform the person you are. If you managed this, imagine other skills you could learn and the other habits you could develop!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this text useful to you? Please let me know underneath and share it. Let me know if you have any feedback or questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Duolingo grammar tips appear only when you use it via the website (thus not in the app) and are probably not accessible on-demand. Luckily, someone has done the work of pulling them out and combining them into a document that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://duome.eu/tips/en/dn&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Holub</name></author><category term="education" /><category term="nl" /><category term="nl" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">Translation: Not perfect is also fine! “How did you learn Dutch so well and so quick?” I get this question often. I am in the few percent of expats who can hold fluent conversation and I got to this point in seemingly no time. And while my Dutch is by no means perfect, it gets the job done. Which is what matters to me and what I take some amount of pride in. Here I will describe how I become fluent in under half a year, without an instructor, while working a full-time job where I did not use any Dutch. What’s more, while I will give Dutch-specific references the approach can be applied to virtually any language, it can cost you as no money, and does not require you to live in place where you would use the learnt language (although that would usually help with the motivation). Learning a foreign language, do I have to? Let me get this clear straight away - no you don’t. In most of common expat locations you will be fine with English and people wont frown upon you. There is plenty of good reasons for not doing it. Do you already have few hobbies that you enjoy and that take up all of your free time? Don’t feel guilty for not squeezing in time for language learning. Are you perfectly set in your social and work life and don’t feel need for mingling with the locals? That’s fine too. That being said, there are also bad reason. Would you love to speak the language, but are afraid of the embarrassing moments when you try to appear smart with the vocabulary of a three year old and pronunciation of someone after palsy? Then it should not stop you - go ahead and start learning, your fear of embarrassment and your perfectionism will eventually even help you to be better at it. Learning a foreign language, how long will it take? When deciding if to learn a new language, you should evaluate the investment if time end effort is worth if for you. For that you will need to know what your target level at that language is, how long do you expect to have to learn it to reach that level and what is the opportunity cost - the things you won’t be doing because you are learning the new language. Because, I guess you saw this coming, learning a new language is a substantial commitment of time. Let’s look how the decision process looked for me when it came to Dutch. I lived in the Netherlands for whole one year, refusing to learn any of their language. I got by with English perfectly fine. Not showing any interest in Dutch was sort of a personal revolt against the terrible weather and other things that made me dislike the country (that’s of course a curse of all expats, after brief spell of seeing only the great things, we go through somewhat longer period of seeing only the things that are wretched about this god damn new place we decided to move into, god knows why, for f\\k’s sake). Expat curve About after one year living here (December 2020), I collected some positive experiences that convinced me the country is not all that bad. I thus decided to be a good immigrant and learn the local language. My goal was to become conversational by the end of 2021. The goal is important - I was not interested in writing essays, I did not want to brim with eloquence - I just wanted to get to the point when I can talk with anybody about anything - how many mistakes I make was not that important as long as I could make myself understood and the conversation could flow naturally. I dedicated one morning a week to learning the grammar and established a routine when I was putting in about an hour of learning on most of the other days. I became conversational much sooner than expected, roughly in May 2021. With average investment of 8 hours per week, in six months this amounts to under 200 hours. You can expect similar amount of time if you have reasons to think that the language you will learn will be rather easy for you (for example because you already learnt couple of languages, or because it resembles a language you already know). In most other cases, you should double the estimate (to 400 hours) to reach similar goal as I did. I am down for it. How do I even start? Ok, so you evaluated the pro’s and con’s, found place in your crammed agenda, and decided to learn a new language. Congratulations! (If you decided not to learn and are still reading - stop! you have better things to do, don’t you?) First things first - where do you even start? In the beginning, you don’t know anything about the new language - so you need to make the learning as easy for yourself as possible. Luckily there is dozens of apps that aim to make the learning almost as much fun and half as addictive as scrolling your social media feed. I used Duolingo and that’s what I would recommend for many, if not most, languages too (I heard good stuff about Hello Chinese for, guess what, Chinese – Mandarin in this case). I would advocate for using an app on your phone rather than a website on your PC – in my experience, it is easier to build a habit from it this way and it feels less like work. Using just Duolingo, you will easily reach level A2 in a month or two. Critically, listen to the app’s advice on how to learn the most effectively! Does the app suggest that you should pronounce the words and phrases out loud? Then do it and do it every time because if you don’t you are not using your time efficiently. Does the app tell you to write down all new words? Ditto - do it. Such pieces of advice are based on solid research on how to learn efficiently, you ignore them at your own disservice. In my case, I aimed to finish the whole Dutch course on Duolingo (7 units), completing each lesson to level 1 (which equaled to about 10’000 XP). I found that in that way I have seen most of what it has to offer. Towards the end (maybe the last two or three units), I started feeling I was not getting that much new content anymore, but I stuck with it just to complete all the units. I did Duolingo consistently every day for close to two months. I wrote down all new phrases into a document on my computer and noted all new words. I also read through Duolingo’s grammar guide for Dutch. 1 Building your vocabulary There is no going around this, language learning requires lot of memorizing. You will need to be able to use somewhere between couple of hundred to few thousands words to be conversational at your desired level and you will need to cram them in your head. When it comes to memorizing stuff for long term, there is a fail-proof strategy: repeated exposure. You will want to have seen and understood a word many times before it will become part of your vocabulary. I tested many strategies for learning new words - looking up a word every time I encounter it, having a dedicated paper notebook and paper flashcards are just some examples. Finally, I settled on a strategy that works extremely well for me. Here it is: every time I encounter a new word, first, I write it down (it is great if you can write down the context too, but I am almost always too lazy/busy at that moment, and just write down the word) … and then I don’t do anything with that word. Yes, you read correctly, note every new word, and then don’t do anything with it. It does not make sense, you think? Well, it does and does not - you should not do anything immediately. Instead, you should look up all the new words whenever you have lot of them written down already. This way you efficiently batch your time between consuming new content and doing some work on it. Sounds pretty straightforward, right? For the most part it is, but there is also a catch, after looking up the new word, you will forget it extremely quickly, sometimes within minutes, sometimes within seconds. No matter how annoying, it is fine that way - that’s how our minds evolved to practically function in a word abounding with stimuli. You will thus need to find a way how to re-expose yourself to the new word couple of times. I am using Anki for this. Anki is a mobile and (importantly) also computer app where you can create your own flashcards. You can really go wild with them, with many custom fields, embedded images and even sound files and recordings. The app automates the learning process for you - it will expose you to chosen number of words each day, and prompt you for your level of confidence in remembering the meaning of each word. The better you know a word already, the later in the future it will be showed again. The fact that you can run the app on your computer too (and synchronize the content with your mobile devices) is invaluable when creating new flashcards - I highly suggest doing this on your laptop or PC, you will be much quicker than doing it on the phone. Each of my flashcards has the following fields: Front (the new word or phrase in the language I am learning) Back (the new word in language(s) I already know) Article / Conjugation (whichever applies) Meaning (explanation in the language I am learning, usually with synonyms and sometimes antonyms) Examples (some examples of usage in context) Sometimes I would throw in an image or a pronunciation as a sound file. In Anki, you can drag and drop the file on any field to automatically insert it. This is how each of my new cards in Anki look like. When creating flashcards or looking up new words, you will need a good dictionary. I never had any issue finding a good one available online for free. I would always use multiple dictionaries: Thesaurus (e.g. Van Dale for Dutch and Larousee or Le Robert for French. English / Target-Language dictionary (oftentimes from the same source as above) Database of contexts (I used Reverso) Specialized dictionaries I think it is fun to learn some slang or expressive language too, for that I would usually some sort of street-language dictionary (straatwoordenboek.nl or straattaalwoordenboek.nl for Dutch) I can recommend all of them. Aside from creating your own flashcards on Anki, you can also download a deck someone else created and use it! While this is somewhat less beneficial and could be arguably skipped, I still found the one with Dutch phrases (audio and text) useful – it will help you too if you, as with Duolingo, pronounce the sentences out loud. I usually did this immediately before or after my daily Duolingo routine. Learning new language, is it any fun? Ok, while the apps mentioned above will make the learning feel quite smooth, and they do their best to build a habit and make the learning somewhat automatized, there are not exactly fun. It will still feel like studying. So it is time to inject some more fun into your language learning. By now, you will be around level A2, maybe even B1 if you have done some grammar work (see my comment on Duolingo’s grammar above), which means you should be able to understand basic written and spoken text. That’s when learning becomes fun. You should pick any medium in the language you are learning and then just try your best at it, still noting every new word and phrase you encounter. I would suggest you pick a written text, because that one is truly self-paced (you can read as quickly, or slowly, as you feel you need to, and you can even reread parts of text), but podcasts or video will work too. I like books, and I therefore picked one in Dutch to start with. Often you will be advised to pick a simplified reading or book for children. I don’t like that advice, rather I suggest you pick a book that you would like to read because of it contents, and it just happens to be in the language you are learning (I chose ‘Mijn vrijheid’ from Ayaan-Hirsi Ali which is stunning autobiography of social and human-right activist, a Dutch immi- and emi-grant, that I can certainly recommend). That being said, no matter how much you may love 18th century historical novels, this is not the time to read them. You should opt for something with contemporary language as your entry book :). Total immersion Books are great, but they will not be enough to reach your language goals quickly. You will see the best results if you endeavor on strategy of ‘totally immersion’. It is what it sounds like, you should try to surround yourself with the new language as much as possible. At this moment you are probably not good enough to start speaking it (this will depend on how shy or not you are, I on the shy side so was not yet at the point of using the language in conversations), so you will have to do with passive consumption. But you are lucky, the internet has you covered when it comes to easily digestible entertaining content. I personally enjoy listening to podcasts and watching video on demand - so I switched them both almost entirely to Dutch. I threw some music on top of that too. All of these are cool also because next to the language, you will be learning more about the country’s culture, something that is usually really fun and broadens your horizons quickly. It will be great if you still can keep noting every new word you encounter, but do not be too hard on yourself. You are having fun in the end. For example, I would never note new words while listening to music or podcasts and only very seldomly when watching videos. And it still worked out fine for me. Also do not worry if you do not understand everything. You need to be able to get the gist (if that is not the case, choose slower play rate, different content or watch videos with subtitles) and that already will allow you to develop feeling and train your ear for the language. Grammar? Grammar! ☹ Ok, you are having some fun learning the new language, and you are seeing some progress. By now you are too invested to just drop it at a whim. It is thus a good time to do some nasty work - learning grammar. I do not care what you may have heard - if you want to use the language actively (speaking, texting, writing, …) you will need to understand its rules. Luckily, it will not be as bad as you may fear. I would strongly suggest going tech-free for the grammar learning process. I got a grammar-book that comes together with a workbook (which also had solutions available at the end). Then I would go through it, page by page, and whenever I would finish a grammar section, I would do the associated exercises. I would then check their correctness against the solutions and use red marker to correct my mistakes. That’s it, that’s how I learnt grammar. The exercises are essential, and you will need to do plenty of them, but it is sort of work that can be bit-sized almost infinitely - even if you just have couple of minutes, you can do an exercise and correct it. This fella always has a point, right? I encourage you to commit to work on it regularly (for me this was Saturday mornings) and to commit to finishing the whole book. You will be then able to see your progress as you move through it, and you will have a clear endpoint. Some argument can be made for skipping section of the book that you do not find all that useful for your particular case (for example you may not need to use much of indirect speech, that mostly employed by journalists and politicians). I like to do these sections too as it gives me more complete grasp of the language. Once you are done with the book, I recommend that you make your own personal grammar summary. I again suggest doing it by pen and paper, use colors and do as much cross-referencing as your find practical. You go through the just-finished books and write as-concise-as-possible summary of all the grammar phenomena that you find useful. You should pay special attention to those where you made the most mistakes (remember the red marker?) - but be practical - is it for example in archaic or bureaucratic language that you erred? Then chances are that you will never really use it that much, and you needn’t worry about mistakes you made. Once you have completed your first version of grammar summary, you can transfer it to an electronic document, that way it will be easier to add stuff in the future as you keep learning(I did that, and I am now at over 25 pages). And one additional grammar tip: you can get Better Spellen app on your phone which will supply you with 12 grammar questions every workday. Sometimes these are quite tricky, even a native speaker would struggle, so you should not do this before you have finished your grammar book. It is efficient; the questions take just a short time to answer, and I am usually done with them in 3 or 4 minutes. After giving your answers you are provided with solutions with link to very detailed explanation of that given grammar phenomenon. Can we have some fun again? Once you have been through the drudgery of grammar, it is time to reward yourself. You will do this by using the language you have been working so hard to learn. You could probably start with either writing or speaking, but I would advocate for speaking. You would have done bit of writing (usually single sentences) by now during your grammar exercises, and for most people, speaking will be their goal anyway. The best place when to start using the language is in low stakes environment. This can be with your friends, in a meet-up or during language exchange. Chances are, no matter where you live, that there already is a small community of people learning the same language you are - join it and hone your skills in this environment. I used to attend language meetups back in the Czech Republic when I was learning French and not only did it improve my ability to speak, but I made new friends and had good time (which was all worth the regular headache from too much red wine afterwards). I was learning Dutch during COVID pandemic, which came with multitude of restrictions on social lives of most. I thus opted to start speaking during an online exchange which I was doing with a Dutch student who wanted to learn some Czech. It was an excellent decision (thanks Carel!) - not only this creates an extremely safe environment for you to practice, but you can get the feel-good vibes from teach something to the other person too. Finally, as this was online and we were just two involved, it was very efficient. I kept doing this for about two months before I noticed I am hitting somewhat diminishing returns. We continued the exchange nevertheless for few more months afterwards, because it remained enjoyable, and the other guy had more work to on their Czech than I had on my Dutch. Once you have been able to use the new language couple of times in your safe ‘training’ environment of choice, you are ready for the next step - using the language to speak to strangers. If you live in the country where the language you are learning this will be simple and should become part of your everyday life. There is no good excuse for not doing it, the people you engage with will be almost universally happy with your attempts and often will compliment you for your efforts, which will be both great reward and motivation for ongoing learning. In other cases, that is if you cannot use the language where you live, you will probably have to continue the (online) language exchange and meetups for longer. In such cases it would be good to switch the focus from language learning to some topic-specific meetups - pursuing your interests and hobbies while continuing to learn the new language. In both above cases, you can usually do some email writing to practice simple written communication (think of inquiring about some organization or institution, booking your next vacation or maybe even using the language for work purposes). I am conversational, what’s next? In most cases, you will want to, aside from using it, continue learning the language even after reaching your initial goal. Usually this will be at reduced pace. For example, I continue reading in Dutch and I keep expanding my set of flashcards with new words and phrases (I am now actually reading the 18th century history novel and while I can progress through it comfortably, I encounter many words that I have not seen before because they are not that commonly used anymore). In some cases, such as when you want to communicate to larger audiences or when you want to pass advanced (C1 and C2) language proficiency exams, you will have to take your language to yet next level. To do that, you should start writing longer pieces of text. What those would be depends on your goals and interests, but short stories, columns and essays are all good candidates. You could also start with blogging and slowly transition to the above forms as they, in contrast to blog which is usually written in quite a plain language (such as this one), lend themselves more naturally to advanced language use. I am convinced that writing at this stage is essential. I went through this process for English (when I was preparing for C2-level exams). After a plateau in language learning, this was something that truly allowed me to level up and quite rapidly. It is only in writing that you will have enough time and space to use more elaborate constructions, to review and rewrite and when you will be able to dig into your memory or even a dictionary to find an eloquent synonym. Once you have been able to use those in writing, they will slowly find their way to your speech too. If you realize that your vocabulary is not yet large enough, you will also need to expand it simultaneously. While you could do this by reading more, that will usually be pretty low-efficiency (as the advanced language constructions you want to learn will come up only rarely) - this would be another good time to get a good textbook - aimed at writers and other very advanced users. Your writing at this point will be nearing the level of essays and novels (though probably not in content :)) and you want it to be grammatically very correct - you won’t be able to proof-read this alone and you will thus want someone who is either learning at the same or higher level or someone native who has very good language use themself to review your text and point to places where you need to improve and adjust. If you aim to communicate to public anyway, you could consider asking your audiences to provide you with feedback. Conclusion Learning new language is great hobby with many benefits. On my example described here you can see that while it is quite some work, it is all manageable - and that in few months and even without any instructor. If you have reached your goals in learning new language yourself, you should justly congratulate yourself. You have worked hard, and you have seen your efforts transform into results. Aside from having learnt a new language, you now have a very personal example of how your own initiative and directed work can transform the person you are. If you managed this, imagine other skills you could learn and the other habits you could develop! Was this text useful to you? Please let me know underneath and share it. Let me know if you have any feedback or questions! Footnotes Duolingo grammar tips appear only when you use it via the website (thus not in the app) and are probably not accessible on-demand. Luckily, someone has done the work of pulling them out and combining them into a document that is available here. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry></feed>