<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-12T17:38:04+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Martin Holub Blog</title><subtitle>Personal Website and Blog
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Get the (S)hell Back Here!</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Shell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get the (S)hell Back Here!" /><published>2025-01-08T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Shell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Shell.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt; In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #10:&lt;/strong&gt; The benefits of Shell’s residency in the Netherlands far outweighed its environmental controversies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell, one of the world’s largest and most recognizable energy companies, has long been a titan in the global market. Founded in 1907 through the merger of Royal Dutch Petroleum and the Shell Transport and Trading Company, it boasts a market capitalization of about $200 billion and operations spanning nearly 100 countries. Shell is synonymous with innovation and resilience in the energy sector - but also with controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, the birthplace of its Royal Dutch heritage, Shell’s reputation is complicated. Critics highlight its environmental record, legal battles over oil spills in Nigeria, and accusations of insufficient action on climate change. The company’s prominent role in Dutch society has often made it a lightning rod for environmental and social protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally formed in a Dutch-British structure, in 2021, the company made a historic decision: to move its headquarters entirely to the United Kingdom. The move, presented as company’s larger strategy in a changing energy landscape, appeared motivated by the aim to escpae increasingly unfriendly Dutch business environment and environmental lawsuits. In this article, I want to argue that this move has negatively impacted the Dutch innovation and economic landscape, and that the Dutch made a mistake in putting their environmental wokeness above their economic interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;shells-history&quot;&gt;Shell’s history&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shells-predecessors&quot;&gt;Shell’s predecessors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shell.com/who-we-are/our-history/our-company-history.html&quot;&gt;Royal Dutch Petroleum Company&lt;/a&gt; was founded in 1890 by August Kessler and Henri Deterding in the Dutch East Indies (modern-day Indonesia). The company was established to develop and export oil discovered in these regions, with its operations crucial for turning oil into a strategic resource for industrial economies. By the late 19th century, Royal Dutch had become a significant player in the oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Shell Transport and Trading Company emerged in 1833 as a small London-based firm trading seashells, founded by Marcus Samuel. By the 1890s, under the leadership of Marcus Samuel Jr., the company shifted to transporting kerosene from the Caspian Sea region. Samuel’s innovative use of oil tankers capable of traversing the Suez Canal positioned Shell as a key player in the global oil trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;company-merger-and-creation-of-modern-shell&quot;&gt;Company merger and creation of modern Shell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1907, the Royal Dutch Petroleum Company and the Shell Transport and Trading Company merged to create the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shell_plc&quot;&gt;Royal Dutch Shell Group&lt;/a&gt;. The merger was driven by intense competition with Standard Oil and the growing demand for efficient global oil distribution. Henri Deterding, often called “The Napoleon of Oil,” played a pivotal role in this unification, recognizing the benefits of combining Royal Dutch’s production strength with Shell’s transportation and marketing expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dual Dutch-British structure emerged from the companies’ respective national identities. Royal Dutch owned 60% of the merged entity, and Shell Transport held 40%. This arrangement allowed the company to leverage financial and strategic advantages in both nations, such as tax benefits, access to capital markets, and diversified operational bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_10_shellLogo2.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Evolution of Shell’s logo.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shells-innovation&quot;&gt;Shell’s innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s history is marked by numerous technical achievements. The company was a pioneer in the development of seismic surveying techniques for oil exploration starting from 1920s. These methods allowed for more accurate mapping of geological formations, which improved oil discovery rates both on land and underwater. Shell also developed advanced refining processes for transforming crude oil into high-value products. This included &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.e-education.psu.edu/fsc432/content/uses-hydrocracking&quot;&gt;hydrocracking&lt;/a&gt;, which refers to breaking of carbon-carbon bonds in complex hydrocarbons with the aid of hydrogen, yielding shorter chains. This technique is used for example to produce diesel and kerosene. Shell is one of the licensors of the technology and continues to advance it, e.g. through introduction of new catalysts.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As oil exploration continued, newly discovered surface reserves were becoming less profitable. Companies gradually shifted to offshore exploration. While basically negligible in the early 50’s, offshore now accounts for about 30% of global oil production. According to current estimates, half of all remaining reserves are offshore, quarter of that being in deepwater. Shell has made significant advancements in deepwater drilling technologies in past decades, enabling access to previously untapped oil reserves. This is exemplified with Shell’s ‘Mars’, one of the largest deepwater rigs in the Gulf of Mexico. The prospecting work started in 1985, and the first platform entered production in 1996, netting establishment costs of more than $1B. Second platform, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.offshore-technology.com/projects/mars-b-olympus-project-gulf-of-mexico/?cf-view&quot;&gt;Mars B Olympus&lt;/a&gt;, opened in 2014, extending the field’s lifetime to at least to 2050.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell has also been a pioneer in the development of gas-to-liquids (GTL) conversion, particularly through the Fischer-Tropsch synthesis process, with number of patents in the area.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The technique enables natural gas to be transformed into liquid fuels and other products. Nowadays, Shell’s GTL facility in Qatar, known as Pearl GTL, is the largest and most advanced GTL plant globally. The plant represents over 50% of the world’s total commercial-scale GTL capacity. Together with smaller plants, this means that Shell controls nearly 75% of all the GTL capacity worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production capacity and process knowledge help to cement Shell’s position in the field of lubricants, where it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://oil.jungent.eu/en/shell-leads-global-lubricants-market-for-17%e1%b5%97%ca%b0-year/&quot;&gt;a market leader for 17 consecutive years&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, Shell is one of the leaders in production of low-carbon synthetic fuels, that particularly attractive as ways to reduce emissions in hard-to-decarbonize sectors such as aviation and shipping.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; More recently, Shell has been investing in renewables and new energy technologies, including building wind farms, acquiring solar capacity, developing carbon capture and storage and green hydrogen production.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s early recognition for the potential of oil and gas business, and the drive for innovation baked into its DNA, quickly positioned it to become one of the leaders in oil production and distribution worldwide. By the mid-20th century, Shell was producing approximately 11% of the world’s crude oil supply and owning about 10% of global tanker tonnage. Nowadays, Shell continues to belong &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/280705/leading-oil-companies-worldwide-based-on-daily-oil-production/&quot;&gt;to top 10 crude oil producers worldwide&lt;/a&gt;, but its market share has fallen to about 3%. Correspondingly, Shell now owns 2% of the global tanker tonnage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shells-controversies&quot;&gt;Shell’s controversies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell being a major player in discovery and utilization of one of the most valuable natural resources, its global operations often intersected with geopolitical tensions and caused environmental concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of its earliest controversies involved its role in the Nigerian oil industry. By the 1950s, Shell’s operations in the Niger Delta began raising alarms due to environmental degradation and displacement of local communities. Shell even faced lawsuits alleging complicity in human rights abuses in Nigeria.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The most notable case involved accusation of the company’s role in executions of local activists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout its history, Shell has been one of the largest contributors to greenhouse gas emissions, ranking 9th in the period from 1988 to 2015.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The controversy that likely shaped today’s view of the company the most dates back to late 80’s and early 90’s. It likely started with very good intentions. In 1991, Shell &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/feb/28/shell-knew-oil-giants-1991-film-warned-climate-change-danger&quot;&gt;produced a 28-minute documentary&lt;/a&gt; about the effects of fossil fuel economy on the climate. The movie was made for public, schools and universities. It raised a clear and sound alarm about industry’s role in global warming, and its potential consequences, including floods, famine, and populational displacement. The science on climate change was only being established, but the film’s message was endorsed by broad scientific consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, Shell slipped. Shortly after the film went public, the company distanced itself from it and stopped distributing it. It was &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecorrespondent.com/6286/if-shell-knew-climate-change-was-dire-25-years-ago-why-still-business-as-usual-today/692773774-4d15b476&quot;&gt;only in 2017&lt;/a&gt;, when the Dutch newspaper De Correspondent got access to the movie, that its existence became widely known and discussed. This further deteriorated Shell’s public image, the company already being under heavy security due to its lobbying against renewable energy targets, and against science backing climate change, in the years prior. To make matters even worse, it turned out that Shell had confidential internal documents pointing to man-induced climate change dating as far back as 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, group of Dutch environmental scientists and NGOs, together with more than 17’000 citizens sued Shell. They accused the company from ongoing harm to climate despite being in possession of evidence of global warming, suing them for hazardous negligence. In 2021, the Dutch court ruled that Shell must reduce its CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions by 45% by 2030. Shell contested, arguing that it is already doing enough, and if more needs to be done, the guidelines should be implemented by governments, not private companies. The court’s 2021 decision &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cx240l9xq2yo&quot;&gt;has been repealed in November 2024&lt;/a&gt;. In 2022, Shell was, along with BP, Chevron Corporation, and ExxonMobil, accused from greenwashing by the  U.S. House Oversight and Reform Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell has taken action to reduce its carbon footprint in recent years, but the public sees this as lackluster and insufficient. The company continues to engage in environmentally concerning practices. For example, through 2022, Shell pursued seismic oil reserve exploration off the South African coast. This effort, criticized by environmentalists, can potentially interfere with migratory and breeding patterns of whales in these areas and permanently alter the coastal marine ecosystems.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_10_GetShellOut.jpg&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;’Get the (S)hell out of here!’ is an extremely popular slogan in the Netherlands. You can find it on stickers everywhere.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;get-the-shell-back-here&quot;&gt;Get the (S)hell back here!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contextualizing-shells-environmental-impact&quot;&gt;Contextualizing Shell’s environmental impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s history as a global energy player is as much a story of innovation as it is of environmental controversy. While its operations have undoubtedly contributed to greenhouse gas emissions, they are tied to the fundamental realities of the oil and gas sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is clear that the oil and gas industry must innovate, the responsibility for reducing emissions has to extend beyond these companies. Transformation is needed across industries. Governments, not publicly traded companies, must take the lead in driving these systemic changes. Public companies like Shell operate under the imperative of maximizing shareholder returns, which inherently limits their ability to prioritize long-term environmental goals over short-term profitability. Ignoring this this means ignoring how market works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operations like crude oil extraction and transportation are carried out by many industry players and are inevitably interfering with the environment. Chemical processes, in particular the Fischer-Tropsch GTL conversion, are extremely energy intensive, yet essential for producing fuels and materials much of our society depends on. These processes currently have no viable scalable substitutes. The rising global demand for energy - fueled by population growth and the expanding middle class – unavoidably necessitates continued reliance on carbon-based energy sources in the near term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Shell’s efforts to address environmental concerns should not be overlooked. In 2024, the company &lt;a href=&quot;https://nltimes.nl/2024/03/14/shell-invest-15-billion-renewables-2026&quot;&gt;pledged to invest $10 to $15 billion&lt;/a&gt; in renewable energy projects by 2026. In terms of share of total investment this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldecomag.com/how-saudi-aramco-balances-oil-production-with-green-energy-investments/&quot;&gt;comparable&lt;/a&gt; to other oil and gas industry leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits-of-shells-domicile-in-the-netherlands&quot;&gt;Benefits of Shells’ domicile in the Netherlands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tax-revenue-and-rd-spending&quot;&gt;Tax Revenue and R&amp;amp;D Spending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s presence in the Netherlands brought substantial tax revenues that supported public programs and infrastructure. In 2021, when Shell maintained its dual-residency structure, Shell’s tax contributions to Dutch authorities exceeded $165M. In the same year, the tax contributions to the UK were only $54M.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Conversely, in 2023 after movement of the company entirely to the UK, the corporate tax payable to the Netherlands reached $314M, while that payable to UK jumped to $1’450M.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Shell belonged to some of the major R&amp;amp;D investors in the Netherlands. In 1999, with €171M, it was the 3rd biggest spender in this area.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Recent economic research indicates that Shell’s energy-related investments in the Netherlands have exceeded €3B between 2016 and 2021, and its Dutch R&amp;amp;D expenditure reached €60M annually between 2011 and 2022.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While data on R&amp;amp;D spending in the Netherlands after 2022 is not available, governmental reports expect that the company will behave as similar companies worldwide, shifting parts of its R&amp;amp;D spending to new country of its residence, the UK.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talent-development-and-strategic-expertise&quot;&gt;Talent Development and Strategic Expertise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s operations also provided Dutch professionals with unique opportunities for career growth. The company’s managerial positions exposed employees to global-scale challenges, in an industry with an outsized impact, offering hard-to-replace training opportunities and experience. This pipeline of skilled talent not only benefited Shell but also enriched the broader Dutch economy as individuals moved on to work in other positions across the industry, or mentor and teach others.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite progress in renewable energy, oil and gas will remain critical to global energy supply for decades, making Shell’s technical and business expertise highly relevant. But besides oil and gas, Shell’s expertise is relevant in other, equally critical areas. One example is the discovery and mining of critical materials and metals. These elements represent strategic resources for energy storage and conversion, as well as semiconductor manufacturing. Indeed, they have been a cause for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_raw_materials#Geopolitical_risk&quot;&gt;recent geopolitical tensions&lt;/a&gt;. Another area where Shell’s expertise has immense value is geothermal energy, the thermal energy extracted from Earth’s crust. It is estimated that the amount of energy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php?id=3970&quot;&gt;stored&lt;/a&gt; there is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elidourado.com/p/geothermal&quot;&gt;more than 40-fold&lt;/a&gt; that of all known petroleum and nuclear fuel reserves. Geothermal, therefore, offers a sustainable energy alternative, without the on-and-off inconveniences of renewables like wind, and solar. Finally, more futuristic undertakings such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://markets.businessinsider.com/news/commodities/asteroid-psyche-nasa-probe-iron-nickel-gold-10-quintillion-spacex-2023-10&quot;&gt;asteroid mining&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_water&quot;&gt;lunar water extraction&lt;/a&gt; could both benefit from the unique expertise of oil and gas companies like Shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell’s history is one of duality: a pioneer of innovation and a source of controversy. While Shell’s environmental controversies are serious, they are not entirely unique to the company. As a part of a broader systemic challenge, they require collective action. The role of publicly traded companies in addressing these challenges can be only a limited one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of driving Shell away, the Netherlands should have worked on strategically aligning goals, and leveraging its presence to further both economic and environmental goals, fostering innovation and collaboration in addressing global energy challenges. By prioritizing wokeness over a pragmatic understanding of business and market dynamics, the Netherlands lost a valuable corporate partner that it may never be able to recreate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;patents&quot;&gt;Patents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fischer-tropsch.org/primary_documents/patents/pattoc.htm&quot;&gt;Patents relating to the Fischer-Tropsch process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://patents.google.com/?assignee=Shell+Internationale+Research+Maatschappij+B.V.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://patents.google.com/?assignee=SHELL+OIL+COMPANY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://patents.justia.com/assignee/shell-oil-company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;seismic-technology&quot;&gt;Seismic technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Glenn-Morton-3/publication/342183221_History_of_Seismic_In_The_Gulf_of_Mexico/links/5ee7be1b299bf1faac56388b/History-of-Seismic-In-The-Gulf-of-Mexico.pdf&quot;&gt;History of Seismic In The Gulf of Mexico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://api.pageplace.de/preview/DT0400.9781139632386_A23868433/preview-9781139632386_A23868433.pdf&quot;&gt;Exploration Seismology (textbook)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://library.seg.org/doi/pdf/10.1190/1.1441805?casa_token=a8hjl4WPX_IAAAAA:OMegrp2pHw8EBBRCJdo8yzK73mr88lZp6U_F-BGg79c1mmLzPd2WSmwchovE8jvzt1Cp7_QdI94r&quot;&gt;The History and Development of Seismic Prospecting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://library.seg.org/doi/epdf/10.1190/1.1441053&quot;&gt;Seismic Method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sbgf.org.br/mysbgf/eventos/expanded_abstracts/VIII_SimBGf/Seismic%20Technology%20-%20Offshore%20Exploration%20and%20Production.pdf&quot;&gt;Seismic Technology - Offshore Exploration and Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gas-to-liquids-conversion&quot;&gt;Gas-to-liquids conversion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://petrowiki.spe.org/Gas_to_liquids_(GTL)&quot;&gt;Petrowiki – Gas-to-liquids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oil-gasportal.com/gtl-small-scale-and-modular-technologies-for-gas-to-liquid-industry/&quot;&gt;Small scale and modular technologies for GTL industry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deepwater-prospecting-and-oil-recovery&quot;&gt;Deepwater prospecting and oil recovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Tyler-Priest/publication/335680324_Shell_Oil&apos;s_Deepwater_Mission_to_Mars/links/5d73d1f1299bf1cb808fdc03/Shell-Oils-Deepwater-Mission-to-Mars.pdf&quot;&gt;Tyler Priest – Shell Oil’s Deepwater Mission to Mars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hydrocracking&quot;&gt;Hydrocracking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.36253/Substantia-1191&quot;&gt;A Brief History of Oil Refining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://catalysts.shell.com/hubfs/Content%20Library/Next%20Level%20Hydrocracking%20Technology%20White%20Paper.pdf?hsa_acc=503527059&amp;amp;hsa_cam=621957736&amp;amp;hsa_grp=184644656&amp;amp;hsa_ad=190174386&amp;amp;hsa_net=linkedin&amp;amp;hsa_ver=3&quot;&gt;Shell Catalysts &amp;amp; Technologies - Next-Level Hydrocracker Flexibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geothermal&quot;&gt;Geothermal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/the-technological-innovations-that-produced-the-shale-revolution/&quot;&gt;IFP - The Technological Innovations that Produced the Shale Revolution (Brian Potter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-on-shell&quot;&gt;More on Shell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/topics/1560/shell/#statisticChapter&quot;&gt;Shell’s page at Statista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.the-low-countries.com/article/never-sell-shell.-a-history-of-royal-dutch-shell-1/&quot;&gt;Overview of “Never Sell Shell”, four-volume history book on Shell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.osti.gov/biblio/6092581 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://catalysts.shell.com/hubfs/SCT_ParadigmBusters.pdf?hsLang=en &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.offshore-technology.com/projects/mars-b-olympus-project-gulf-of-mexico/?cf-view &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.fischer-tropsch.org/primary_documents/patents/pattoc.htm &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.kenresearch.com/industry-reports/global-synthetic-fuel-market &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://blog.wearedrew.co/en/shell-case-study-innovating-for-a-clean-energy-future &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.cetim.ch/cases-of-environmental-human-rights-violations-by-shell-in-nigeria%E2%80%99s-niger-delta/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/2017/jul/10/100-fossil-fuel-companies-investors-responsible-71-global-emissions-cdp-study-climate-change &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://undark.org/2022/02/10/whale-ears-shell-oil-and-the-hidden-toll-of-seismic-surveys/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.shell.com/news-and-insights/annual-reports-and-publications/tax-contribution-report &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.shell.com/news-and-insights/annual-reports-and-publications/tax-contribution-report &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://vector.tno.nl/en/articles/top-30-companies-investing-most/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.shell.nl/about-us/news/2022/investeerders-in-de-nederlandse-energietransitie &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.bedrijvenbeleidinbeeld.nl/bouwstenen-bedrijvenbeleid/documenten/publicaties/2024/10/15/index &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have an interesting example of this. Recently, a new Dutch contract research organization developing formulations of RNA therapeutics was established. The company is led by a former Shell executive. This individual retired early, then got bored, and joined the National Growth Program, where he came across scientific work that attracted his interest. He recognized a business opportunity, contacted the scientists, and together they launched a new company. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #10: The benefits of Shell’s residency in the Netherlands far outweighed its environmental controversies. Introduction Shell, one of the world’s largest and most recognizable energy companies, has long been a titan in the global market. Founded in 1907 through the merger of Royal Dutch Petroleum and the Shell Transport and Trading Company, it boasts a market capitalization of about $200 billion and operations spanning nearly 100 countries. Shell is synonymous with innovation and resilience in the energy sector - but also with controversy. In the Netherlands, the birthplace of its Royal Dutch heritage, Shell’s reputation is complicated. Critics highlight its environmental record, legal battles over oil spills in Nigeria, and accusations of insufficient action on climate change. The company’s prominent role in Dutch society has often made it a lightning rod for environmental and social protests. Originally formed in a Dutch-British structure, in 2021, the company made a historic decision: to move its headquarters entirely to the United Kingdom. The move, presented as company’s larger strategy in a changing energy landscape, appeared motivated by the aim to escpae increasingly unfriendly Dutch business environment and environmental lawsuits. In this article, I want to argue that this move has negatively impacted the Dutch innovation and economic landscape, and that the Dutch made a mistake in putting their environmental wokeness above their economic interests. Shell’s history Shell’s predecessors The Royal Dutch Petroleum Company was founded in 1890 by August Kessler and Henri Deterding in the Dutch East Indies (modern-day Indonesia). The company was established to develop and export oil discovered in these regions, with its operations crucial for turning oil into a strategic resource for industrial economies. By the late 19th century, Royal Dutch had become a significant player in the oil industry. Meanwhile, the Shell Transport and Trading Company emerged in 1833 as a small London-based firm trading seashells, founded by Marcus Samuel. By the 1890s, under the leadership of Marcus Samuel Jr., the company shifted to transporting kerosene from the Caspian Sea region. Samuel’s innovative use of oil tankers capable of traversing the Suez Canal positioned Shell as a key player in the global oil trade. Company merger and creation of modern Shell In 1907, the Royal Dutch Petroleum Company and the Shell Transport and Trading Company merged to create the Royal Dutch Shell Group. The merger was driven by intense competition with Standard Oil and the growing demand for efficient global oil distribution. Henri Deterding, often called “The Napoleon of Oil,” played a pivotal role in this unification, recognizing the benefits of combining Royal Dutch’s production strength with Shell’s transportation and marketing expertise. The dual Dutch-British structure emerged from the companies’ respective national identities. Royal Dutch owned 60% of the merged entity, and Shell Transport held 40%. This arrangement allowed the company to leverage financial and strategic advantages in both nations, such as tax benefits, access to capital markets, and diversified operational bases. Evolution of Shell’s logo. Shell’s innovation Shell’s history is marked by numerous technical achievements. The company was a pioneer in the development of seismic surveying techniques for oil exploration starting from 1920s. These methods allowed for more accurate mapping of geological formations, which improved oil discovery rates both on land and underwater. Shell also developed advanced refining processes for transforming crude oil into high-value products. This included hydrocracking, which refers to breaking of carbon-carbon bonds in complex hydrocarbons with the aid of hydrogen, yielding shorter chains. This technique is used for example to produce diesel and kerosene. Shell is one of the licensors of the technology and continues to advance it, e.g. through introduction of new catalysts.1,2 As oil exploration continued, newly discovered surface reserves were becoming less profitable. Companies gradually shifted to offshore exploration. While basically negligible in the early 50’s, offshore now accounts for about 30% of global oil production. According to current estimates, half of all remaining reserves are offshore, quarter of that being in deepwater. Shell has made significant advancements in deepwater drilling technologies in past decades, enabling access to previously untapped oil reserves. This is exemplified with Shell’s ‘Mars’, one of the largest deepwater rigs in the Gulf of Mexico. The prospecting work started in 1985, and the first platform entered production in 1996, netting establishment costs of more than $1B. Second platform, Mars B Olympus, opened in 2014, extending the field’s lifetime to at least to 2050.3 Shell has also been a pioneer in the development of gas-to-liquids (GTL) conversion, particularly through the Fischer-Tropsch synthesis process, with number of patents in the area.4 The technique enables natural gas to be transformed into liquid fuels and other products. Nowadays, Shell’s GTL facility in Qatar, known as Pearl GTL, is the largest and most advanced GTL plant globally. The plant represents over 50% of the world’s total commercial-scale GTL capacity. Together with smaller plants, this means that Shell controls nearly 75% of all the GTL capacity worldwide. The production capacity and process knowledge help to cement Shell’s position in the field of lubricants, where it is a market leader for 17 consecutive years. Similarly, Shell is one of the leaders in production of low-carbon synthetic fuels, that particularly attractive as ways to reduce emissions in hard-to-decarbonize sectors such as aviation and shipping.5 More recently, Shell has been investing in renewables and new energy technologies, including building wind farms, acquiring solar capacity, developing carbon capture and storage and green hydrogen production.6 Shell’s early recognition for the potential of oil and gas business, and the drive for innovation baked into its DNA, quickly positioned it to become one of the leaders in oil production and distribution worldwide. By the mid-20th century, Shell was producing approximately 11% of the world’s crude oil supply and owning about 10% of global tanker tonnage. Nowadays, Shell continues to belong to top 10 crude oil producers worldwide, but its market share has fallen to about 3%. Correspondingly, Shell now owns 2% of the global tanker tonnage. Shell’s controversies Shell being a major player in discovery and utilization of one of the most valuable natural resources, its global operations often intersected with geopolitical tensions and caused environmental concerns. One of its earliest controversies involved its role in the Nigerian oil industry. By the 1950s, Shell’s operations in the Niger Delta began raising alarms due to environmental degradation and displacement of local communities. Shell even faced lawsuits alleging complicity in human rights abuses in Nigeria.7 The most notable case involved accusation of the company’s role in executions of local activists. Throughout its history, Shell has been one of the largest contributors to greenhouse gas emissions, ranking 9th in the period from 1988 to 2015.8 The controversy that likely shaped today’s view of the company the most dates back to late 80’s and early 90’s. It likely started with very good intentions. In 1991, Shell produced a 28-minute documentary about the effects of fossil fuel economy on the climate. The movie was made for public, schools and universities. It raised a clear and sound alarm about industry’s role in global warming, and its potential consequences, including floods, famine, and populational displacement. The science on climate change was only being established, but the film’s message was endorsed by broad scientific consensus. Then, Shell slipped. Shortly after the film went public, the company distanced itself from it and stopped distributing it. It was only in 2017, when the Dutch newspaper De Correspondent got access to the movie, that its existence became widely known and discussed. This further deteriorated Shell’s public image, the company already being under heavy security due to its lobbying against renewable energy targets, and against science backing climate change, in the years prior. To make matters even worse, it turned out that Shell had confidential internal documents pointing to man-induced climate change dating as far back as 1986. In 2019, group of Dutch environmental scientists and NGOs, together with more than 17’000 citizens sued Shell. They accused the company from ongoing harm to climate despite being in possession of evidence of global warming, suing them for hazardous negligence. In 2021, the Dutch court ruled that Shell must reduce its CO2 emissions by 45% by 2030. Shell contested, arguing that it is already doing enough, and if more needs to be done, the guidelines should be implemented by governments, not private companies. The court’s 2021 decision has been repealed in November 2024. In 2022, Shell was, along with BP, Chevron Corporation, and ExxonMobil, accused from greenwashing by the U.S. House Oversight and Reform Committee. Shell has taken action to reduce its carbon footprint in recent years, but the public sees this as lackluster and insufficient. The company continues to engage in environmentally concerning practices. For example, through 2022, Shell pursued seismic oil reserve exploration off the South African coast. This effort, criticized by environmentalists, can potentially interfere with migratory and breeding patterns of whales in these areas and permanently alter the coastal marine ecosystems.9 ’Get the (S)hell out of here!’ is an extremely popular slogan in the Netherlands. You can find it on stickers everywhere. Get the (S)hell back here! Contextualizing Shell’s environmental impact Shell’s history as a global energy player is as much a story of innovation as it is of environmental controversy. While its operations have undoubtedly contributed to greenhouse gas emissions, they are tied to the fundamental realities of the oil and gas sector. While it is clear that the oil and gas industry must innovate, the responsibility for reducing emissions has to extend beyond these companies. Transformation is needed across industries. Governments, not publicly traded companies, must take the lead in driving these systemic changes. Public companies like Shell operate under the imperative of maximizing shareholder returns, which inherently limits their ability to prioritize long-term environmental goals over short-term profitability. Ignoring this this means ignoring how market works. Operations like crude oil extraction and transportation are carried out by many industry players and are inevitably interfering with the environment. Chemical processes, in particular the Fischer-Tropsch GTL conversion, are extremely energy intensive, yet essential for producing fuels and materials much of our society depends on. These processes currently have no viable scalable substitutes. The rising global demand for energy - fueled by population growth and the expanding middle class – unavoidably necessitates continued reliance on carbon-based energy sources in the near term. Finally, Shell’s efforts to address environmental concerns should not be overlooked. In 2024, the company pledged to invest $10 to $15 billion in renewable energy projects by 2026. In terms of share of total investment this is comparable to other oil and gas industry leaders. Benefits of Shells’ domicile in the Netherlands Tax Revenue and R&amp;amp;D Spending Shell’s presence in the Netherlands brought substantial tax revenues that supported public programs and infrastructure. In 2021, when Shell maintained its dual-residency structure, Shell’s tax contributions to Dutch authorities exceeded $165M. In the same year, the tax contributions to the UK were only $54M.10 Conversely, in 2023 after movement of the company entirely to the UK, the corporate tax payable to the Netherlands reached $314M, while that payable to UK jumped to $1’450M.11 Historically, Shell belonged to some of the major R&amp;amp;D investors in the Netherlands. In 1999, with €171M, it was the 3rd biggest spender in this area.12 Recent economic research indicates that Shell’s energy-related investments in the Netherlands have exceeded €3B between 2016 and 2021, and its Dutch R&amp;amp;D expenditure reached €60M annually between 2011 and 2022.13 While data on R&amp;amp;D spending in the Netherlands after 2022 is not available, governmental reports expect that the company will behave as similar companies worldwide, shifting parts of its R&amp;amp;D spending to new country of its residence, the UK.14 Talent Development and Strategic Expertise Shell’s operations also provided Dutch professionals with unique opportunities for career growth. The company’s managerial positions exposed employees to global-scale challenges, in an industry with an outsized impact, offering hard-to-replace training opportunities and experience. This pipeline of skilled talent not only benefited Shell but also enriched the broader Dutch economy as individuals moved on to work in other positions across the industry, or mentor and teach others.15 Despite progress in renewable energy, oil and gas will remain critical to global energy supply for decades, making Shell’s technical and business expertise highly relevant. But besides oil and gas, Shell’s expertise is relevant in other, equally critical areas. One example is the discovery and mining of critical materials and metals. These elements represent strategic resources for energy storage and conversion, as well as semiconductor manufacturing. Indeed, they have been a cause for recent geopolitical tensions. Another area where Shell’s expertise has immense value is geothermal energy, the thermal energy extracted from Earth’s crust. It is estimated that the amount of energy stored there is more than 40-fold that of all known petroleum and nuclear fuel reserves. Geothermal, therefore, offers a sustainable energy alternative, without the on-and-off inconveniences of renewables like wind, and solar. Finally, more futuristic undertakings such as asteroid mining and lunar water extraction could both benefit from the unique expertise of oil and gas companies like Shell. Conclusion Shell’s history is one of duality: a pioneer of innovation and a source of controversy. While Shell’s environmental controversies are serious, they are not entirely unique to the company. As a part of a broader systemic challenge, they require collective action. The role of publicly traded companies in addressing these challenges can be only a limited one. Instead of driving Shell away, the Netherlands should have worked on strategically aligning goals, and leveraging its presence to further both economic and environmental goals, fostering innovation and collaboration in addressing global energy challenges. By prioritizing wokeness over a pragmatic understanding of business and market dynamics, the Netherlands lost a valuable corporate partner that it may never be able to recreate. Further reading Patents Patents relating to the Fischer-Tropsch process https://patents.google.com/?assignee=Shell+Internationale+Research+Maatschappij+B.V. https://patents.google.com/?assignee=SHELL+OIL+COMPANY https://patents.justia.com/assignee/shell-oil-company Seismic technology History of Seismic In The Gulf of Mexico Exploration Seismology (textbook) The History and Development of Seismic Prospecting Seismic Method Seismic Technology - Offshore Exploration and Production Gas-to-liquids conversion Petrowiki – Gas-to-liquids Small scale and modular technologies for GTL industry Deepwater prospecting and oil recovery Tyler Priest – Shell Oil’s Deepwater Mission to Mars Hydrocracking A Brief History of Oil Refining Shell Catalysts &amp;amp; Technologies - Next-Level Hydrocracker Flexibility Geothermal IFP - The Technological Innovations that Produced the Shale Revolution (Brian Potter) More on Shell Shell’s page at Statista Overview of “Never Sell Shell”, four-volume history book on Shell References https://www.osti.gov/biblio/6092581 &amp;#8617; https://catalysts.shell.com/hubfs/SCT_ParadigmBusters.pdf?hsLang=en &amp;#8617; https://www.offshore-technology.com/projects/mars-b-olympus-project-gulf-of-mexico/?cf-view &amp;#8617; https://www.fischer-tropsch.org/primary_documents/patents/pattoc.htm &amp;#8617; https://www.kenresearch.com/industry-reports/global-synthetic-fuel-market &amp;#8617; https://blog.wearedrew.co/en/shell-case-study-innovating-for-a-clean-energy-future &amp;#8617; https://www.cetim.ch/cases-of-environmental-human-rights-violations-by-shell-in-nigeria%E2%80%99s-niger-delta/ &amp;#8617; https://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/2017/jul/10/100-fossil-fuel-companies-investors-responsible-71-global-emissions-cdp-study-climate-change &amp;#8617; https://undark.org/2022/02/10/whale-ears-shell-oil-and-the-hidden-toll-of-seismic-surveys/ &amp;#8617; https://www.shell.com/news-and-insights/annual-reports-and-publications/tax-contribution-report &amp;#8617; https://www.shell.com/news-and-insights/annual-reports-and-publications/tax-contribution-report &amp;#8617; https://vector.tno.nl/en/articles/top-30-companies-investing-most/ &amp;#8617; https://www.shell.nl/about-us/news/2022/investeerders-in-de-nederlandse-energietransitie &amp;#8617; https://www.bedrijvenbeleidinbeeld.nl/bouwstenen-bedrijvenbeleid/documenten/publicaties/2024/10/15/index &amp;#8617; I have an interesting example of this. Recently, a new Dutch contract research organization developing formulations of RNA therapeutics was established. The company is led by a former Shell executive. This individual retired early, then got bored, and joined the National Growth Program, where he came across scientific work that attracted his interest. He recognized a business opportunity, contacted the scientists, and together they launched a new company. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Historical and Economic Argument for Immigration</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Migration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Historical and Economic Argument for Immigration" /><published>2025-01-08T07:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T07:59:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Migration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/Migration.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #9&lt;/strong&gt;: European countries must position themselves as attractive destinations for international immigration.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;!---break---&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hot take? Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immigration has been in the news as a political scapegoat, blamed for anything from inflation to housing prices. All of these are real and important problems. Take the Netherlands as an example of a European country. It has experienced major housing shortages recently and is projected to continue to do so for another decade. This leads to a lot of frustration among Dutch population, and understandably so. Politicians have blamed immigration as a major contributor to this, and other problems. Consequently, the general attitude of the population towards international migration has shifted, becoming more negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This negative sentiment has been pervasive in the developed world and led to rise of right-wing parties and anti-immigration policies, including recently in the Netherlands and the United States. I find this political shift imprudent and, in the long run, damaging to local economies. Instead, I argue, countries, and particularly the European ones, should try to attract more immigrants. Below I outline a few arguments for why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;migration-is-human-universal&quot;&gt;Migration is human universal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the news would have you think migration is a recent phenomenon. That’s not true. Humans have been migrating since they were humans. Archeological evidence points to spread of anatomically modern humans from East Africa to the rest of the world.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even before then, members of the Homo genus are known to have migrated both within the African continent and out of it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Going ahead in time, both ancient and modern human history is essentially a history of migration. Many examples are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indo-European_migrations&quot;&gt;spread of Indo-European&lt;/a&gt; languages and cultures is linked to migrations from the steppes of Central Asia into Europe and parts of Asia (ca 3500 BC – 1500 BC). This movement contributed to the establishment of various civilizations, including the Greeks, Romans, and Persians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bantu_expansion&quot;&gt;Bantu migrations&lt;/a&gt; from West Africa into Central, Eastern, and Southern Africa (ca 1000 BC – 500 AD) involved the spread of agriculture, ironworking technology, and language. This movement contributed to the establishment of complex societies and kingdoms across Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the decline of the Roman Empire, various groups such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goths&quot;&gt;Goths&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vandals&quot;&gt;Vandals&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huns&quot;&gt;Huns&lt;/a&gt; migrated across Europe during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldhistory.org/Migration_Age/&quot;&gt;Migration Age, or so called Barbarian Invasions&lt;/a&gt; (ca 300 – 750 AD). This period saw significant cultural shifts and the formation of new kingdoms that laid the groundwork for modern European nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_colonization_of_the_Americas&quot;&gt;European Colonization of the Americas&lt;/a&gt; (15th–17th century), millions of Europeans migrated to the New World, establishing colonies that transformed indigenous societies and ecosystems. These migrations marked the beginning of global trade networks and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbian_exchange&quot;&gt;Columbian Exchange&lt;/a&gt;, which involved mutual exchange of foods (e.g. potato, rice), diseases (e.g. smallpox and syphilis), and more. Following this, the Great Atlantic Migration (19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; - early 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century) saw millions of Europeans moving to North America from countries like Ireland, Germany, and Italy due to economic opportunities and political unrest. This influx significantly shaped the American demographics and culture of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_US1910.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Europeans did not see immigration as a problem when then hoarded to the US in 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/07/11/opinion/immigrants-success-america.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_shareBornAbroadClip.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;The US severely restricted immigration in 20’s and rolled measures back in the 60’s after experiencing negative economic consequences [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/07/11/opinion/immigrants-success-america.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when we look at very recent history, the oft-touted claim that migration is getting out of hand simply does not hold. The share of global migrants &lt;a href=&quot;https://heindehaas.blogspot.com/2017/03/myths-of-migration-much-of-what-we.html&quot;&gt;has been steady at around 3%&lt;/a&gt; of global population over the past 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_itKeepsGoing.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;The fraction of migrants in the global population has held steady over the past 50 years [&lt;a href=&quot;https://heindehaas.blogspot.com/2017/03/myths-of-migration-much-of-what-we.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;migration-drives-development-and-lack-of-it-hinders-it&quot;&gt;Migration drives development, and lack of it hinders it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to argue against migration as an engine of cultural and economic development throughout history given the numerous examples highlighted above. Even naively, it seems highly unlikely that anything should change about this in modern times, and migration would suddenly become a burden. But let’s look at some more recent data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at the contribution of migration to countries’ economies is to look at consequences of interventions designed to curb it. In 1882, the U.S. government introduced the, at that time widely popular, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_Exclusion_Act&quot;&gt;Chinese Exclusion Act&lt;/a&gt;. At that time, Chinese migrants constituted about 20% of all migrants in the western states, and local population argued that these migrants reduced their economic opportunities. A recent HBS and NBER working paper examined the consequences of this act, concluding that:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Act reduced the number of Chinese workers of all skill levels residing in the U.S. It also reduced the labor supply and the quality of jobs held by white and U.S.-born workers, the intended beneficiaries of the Act, and reduced manufacturing output. The results suggest that the Chinese Exclusion Act slowed economic growth in western states until at least 1940.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1920’s, with goals to protect local jobs, the U.S. introduced set of measures to curb international immigration. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emergency_Quota_Act&quot;&gt;Emergency Quota Act (1921)&lt;/a&gt; and the subsequent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immigration_Act_of_1924&quot;&gt;Immigration Act of 1924&lt;/a&gt;, introduced global and country-wide quota on migration. Consequently, total immigration to the U.S. dropped by some 80%. Migrants from Asia were entirely banned, and migrants from Eastern and Southern Europe were heavily disfavored. Number of papers examined the consequences of this act, reaching the conclusion that it neither helped protect jobs for Americans, nor drove economic growth. Industries relying on immigrant workforce either shifted to more capital-intensive, less labor-intensive, approaches, or they shrunk. Despite the loss of immigrant labor supply, the wages of US-born workers declined.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;labor-shortages-drive-migration&quot;&gt;Labor shortages drive migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above, I discussed evidence for migration as a driver for economic development. A natural question to consider next is, what drives migration? Anywhere you live, you have probably been delt with the imagery of migrants fleeing from unsafe regions. While a portion certainly does that, it is a minority. For example, in the Netherlands, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nltimes.nl/2024/02/01/38000-people-applied-asylum-netherlands-last-year-8-percent&quot;&gt;less than 10%&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbs.nl/en-gb/dossier/asylum-migration-and-integration/how-many-people-immigrate-to-the-netherlands-&quot;&gt;all immigrants&lt;/a&gt; in 2023 were asylum seekers, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://asylumineurope.org/reports/country/netherlands/overview-main-changes-previous-report-update/&quot;&gt;less than 20% of that&lt;/a&gt; eventually qualified a as refugees. Instead, most migrants arrive to compensate for labor shortages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_itsTheEconomy.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Immigration numbers closely follow the numbers of job openings [&lt;a href=&quot;https://heindehaas.blogspot.com/2024/11/the-immigration-conundrum-in-nutshell.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, data shows that the rate of immigration &lt;a href=&quot;https://heindehaas.blogspot.com/2024/11/the-immigration-conundrum-in-nutshell.html&quot;&gt;closely tracks&lt;/a&gt; the rate of creation of new jobs. International migrants are a critical component of both seasonal and permanent workforce across the globe. In the US, California’s Central Valley is the nation’s largest agricultural producing region. &lt;a href=&quot;https://eu.desertsun.com/story/news/politics/elections/2024/12/30/california-farmworkers-mass-deportation-trump-economic-impact/77092629007/&quot;&gt;Two-thirds of farmworkers&lt;/a&gt; there are undocumented labor migrants. The British NHS is famously known to &lt;a href=&quot;https://fullfact.org/health/foreign-born-nhs-eu/&quot;&gt;rely heavily&lt;/a&gt; poorly paid immigrant labor, and has experienced significant &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/380/bmj.p232&quot;&gt;challenges&lt;/a&gt; after Brexit. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w30960&quot;&gt;A recent study from NBER&lt;/a&gt; examined immigrant labor in nursing homes in the US, finding that immigrants help fill labor shortages, which translates to improved patient outcomes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We show that increased immigration significantly raises the staffing levels of nursing homes in the U.S., particularly in full time positions. We then show that this has an associated very positive effect on patient outcomes […].”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people agree that migrants &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2020/06/10/a-majority-of-americans-say-immigrants-mostly-fill-jobs-u-s-citizens-do-not-want/&quot;&gt;fill roles the local population does not aspire to occupy&lt;/a&gt;. People cleaning offices, driving Ubers, and delivering food are commonly migrants. Their jobs are often relatively low-skill, low-pay and have poor job security. These jobs are critical and have an important contribution to overall availability and quality of services for the local population. They are generally not jobs locals aspire to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the most important argument pointing to how critical immigrant labor is, comes from this laughing contradiction – despite migrants being touted as source of evil by politicians, rarely anybody gets persecuted for employing them. In the US, data indicates that in the year from April 2018 to March 2019, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.syr.edu/immigration/reports/559/&quot;&gt;only 11 individuals&lt;/a&gt; were prosecuted&lt;/em&gt; for illegally employing undocumented workers, with no companies facing charges during that period. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;85,000 prosecutions&lt;/em&gt; for illegal entry and re-entry during the same timeframe have been issued.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Historically, prosecutions of employers have &lt;em&gt;rarely exceeded 15 cases annually&lt;/em&gt;. While the UK has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-66422763&quot;&gt;recently announced strengthening&lt;/a&gt; of oversight for undocumented labor (labour that is), historically the enforcement has been virtually nonexistent. In 2017, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peoplemanagement.co.uk/article/1746632/prosecutions-hiring-illegal-immigrants-fell&quot;&gt;only 3 individuals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; were persecuted for employing illegal immigrants.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;migrants-are-a-desirable-demographic&quot;&gt;Migrants are a desirable demographic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above we have seen that migration has been, and continues to be, an important part of human history, that efforts trying to curb migration tend to lead to negative economic consequences, and that migrants mostly compensate for labor shortages in the countries of their arrival. In this section, I argue that, in addition to the above benefits, migrants are also a desirable demographic to attract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We wanted workers, but we got people instead.” – Max Frisch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migration is a demanding and risk-taking behavior. Data shows that it is the younger, healthier, more educated, more well-off, and harder working people that decide to migrate. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2013/02/07/second-generation-americans/&quot;&gt;Recent Pew Research&lt;/a&gt; study surveyed children of immigrants and found out that they are more likely to believe in the value of hard work than the general population, and see it as means to get ahead in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_hardwork.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Immigrants are more likely to say hard work is a way to get ahead in life [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2013/02/07/second-generation-americans/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the hard work pays out. While the first generation of migrants has lower salaries and poorer educational outcomes than the native population, the trend equalizes or even reverses already in the following generation. The second generation of immigrants is more likely to graduate from college, and less likely to live in poverty then the general population. They earn the same salaries as locals, and are equally likely to own a home. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While politicians like to picture immigrants as criminals, data overwhelmingly points to the opposite trend. Migrants are &lt;a href=&quot;https://nij.ojp.gov/topics/articles/undocumented-immigrant-offending-rate-lower-us-born-citizen-rate&quot;&gt;less likely&lt;/a&gt; to commit crimes than natives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the trivial aspect of migrants generally being relatively young has important consequences. The median age in Europe has increased on average by 0.25 years over the past decade, reaching 44.5 in in 2023. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The consequence is that fewer and fewer people are in the working population, while increasing share is in retirement, drawing state benefits. Older people also tend to use healthcare more. To maintain sustainability of the retirement model, it is vital to make the population younger on average. This is difficult. People in developed countries are having fewer and fewer children and live longer. The number of U.S. centenarians is projected to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2024/12/06/striking-findings-from-2024/&quot;&gt;quadruple&lt;/a&gt; by 2054. Immigration should be part of the answer to this challenge. European countries with positive net immigration &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/products-eurostat-news/-/ddn-20230222-1&quot;&gt;are aging much slower&lt;/a&gt; than countries with net emigration. Additionally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.org.uk/features-and-opinion/blogs/international-migrants-use-nhs-services-less-frequently-than-non&quot;&gt;immigrants tend to use fewer healthcare services&lt;/a&gt; than comparably aged locals, further adding to their net contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_medianAgeEU.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Some European countries are aging much faster than others [&lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/products-eurostat-news/-/ddn-20230222-1&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to describe the migrant demographic could be to consider their level of attainment of exceptional achievements. If a significant portion of these achievements are met by those foreign-born, it seems likely they are overall better trained and more ambitious than locals, and a net positive to the country. The Nobel Prize is widely regarded as the most important recognition of scientific merit. The U.S. is home to the most winners of this prize, with the proportion of foreign-born winners &lt;a href=&quot;https://nfap.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/REFUGEE-INTEGRATION-IN-AMERICA.NFAP-Policy-Brief.October-2023.pdf&quot;&gt;exceeding 30%, and mostly 40%&lt;/a&gt;, over the past 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_9_immigration_NobelPrizeWinners.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;33-45% of American Nobel Prize winners are immigrants.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above, I highlighted some arguments why I believe countries must position themselves as attractive destinations for international migrants. Over the course of history, migration has been associated with cultural, societal and economic development. Efforts to curb migration produced negative consequences for economies implementing them, and their local workforce. Migration is human universal; people will keep seeking better opportunities and brighter futures for themselves and their children. It tends to be the younger, healthier and more ambitious that decide to migrate. While the USA has historically been the strongest magnet for international migrants, the current political leadership sees this phenomenon as unfavorable. In the fight for international talent, this represents an opportunity for European countries to show better and more forward-looking leadership, becoming relatively more attractive immigration destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I described immigration as net positive, and this is something I believe is well supported by the data I included. However, I understand that immigration, and immigrant population, face and bring about unique challenges. A policy that welcomes everybody, without regard to their situation and motives, is not something I advocate for. In fact, I would argue that while countries must position themselves as attractive destinations for international migration, they should also be selective about whom they allow to settle, and how they distribute benefits to pre-settlers. This position is arguably more economically neoliberal than the European average, but I do consider it important for increasing the competitiveness of the region. An argument for why we need that is something that I am happy to delve into in some future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bRzpiYIR6Xg&quot;&gt;Milton Friedman - Illegal Immigration is Beneficial to the US&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/01/16/686056668/for-seventh-consecutive-year-visa-overstays-exceeded-illegal-border-crossings&quot;&gt;For 7th Consecutive Year, Visa Overstays Exceeded Illegal Border Crossings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.vividmaps.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/through-time.jpg &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.britannica.com/science/human-evolution &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nber.org/papers/w33019 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nber.org/papers/w26536 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nber.org/papers/w30960 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://trac.syr.edu/immigration/reports/559/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.peoplemanagement.co.uk/article/1746632/prosecutions-hiring-illegal-immigrants-fell &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2013/02/07/second-generation-americans/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Population_structure_and_ageing &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #9: European countries must position themselves as attractive destinations for international immigration.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Academia Better, Part 4 – Pursue More Need-Driven Research</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Academia Better, Part 4 – Pursue More Need-Driven Research" /><published>2025-01-08T07:58:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T07:58:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter4.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt; In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #8:&lt;/strong&gt; Need-driven research is a better investment of taxpayers money than research driven by curiosity.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;!---break---&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science and research are cornerstones of human progress. They enable innovations that shape our lives, help address pressing challenges and expand our understanding of Nature and the Universe. Albert Einstein once said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The important thing is not to stop questioning. Curiosity has its own reason for existing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan echoed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Somewhere, something incredible is waiting to be known.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before them, Edwin Hubble described the exploratory nature of scientific discovery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Equipped with his five senses, man explores the universe around him and calls the adventure Science.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These quotes remind us of the awe-inspiring power of discovery and the curiosity that often drives it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; this curiosity drive matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research exists on a spectrum, from purely exploratory endeavors to highly application-driven projects. For example, consider the discovery of the electron, which began as basic inquiry into the nature of electricity. Similarly, the discovery of X-rays, came about as Röntgen experimented with bombarding diverse materials with high-speed electrical current. On the other end of the spectrum, applied research has given us technologies that we cannot imagine our lives without - smartphones, therapeutics, and agricultural pest control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All points on this spectrum are valuable and have their place in the broader ecosystem of discovery. Basic, curiosity-driven research often forms the foundation for future applications. Similarly, applied research directly addresses the needs of society. This diversity in approach has historically driven human progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, given the reality of limited resources and ongoing challenges such as climate change, geopolitical conflicts, pandemics, and food insecurity, the question needs to be asked: &lt;em&gt;How should we prioritize our investments in research?&lt;/em&gt; I argue that in the modern era, need-driven research leads to more overall positive impact than curiosity-driven research does. Even when pursuing fundamental science, grounding the inquiry in well-defined needs helps to ensure relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I describe what issues I see with ’curiosity-driven’ research, and give arguments for, and examples of, adopting more ‘need-based’ approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_8_researcher.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Romantic image of curiosity driven exploration.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-wrong-with-curiosity&quot;&gt;What’s wrong with curiosity?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curiosity-driven research is often portrayed as the heart and soul of scientific inquiry. It conjures romantic images of exploration, where passionate researchers chase the unknown. While this narrative is appealing, it is a mix of fantasy and reality, and needs closer scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-origins-of-curiosity-driven-research&quot;&gt;The origins of ‘curiosity-driven’ research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free scientific exploration was transformative throughout history and up to the early 20th century. Throughout this period nearly everything looked at through a scientific lens led to a discovery. An apple falling from a tree? Bang, science. A light ray passing through a jug of water? More science. Wilhelm Röntgen stumbled upon X-rays when observing unexpected fluorescence in darkened laboratory. Up until fairly recently, research continued resembling fumbling in the dark, metaphorically and literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This legacy helps to understand the overwhelmingly positive image of curiosity in research. Many of the quotes that shape our cultural narrative about science come from this period of groundbreaking discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curiosity-as-a-brand&quot;&gt;Curiosity as a brand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem with the term “curiosity-driven research” is that it is a misnomer. What does it really mean? If a researcher tells you their work is “curiosity-driven,” do you know anything specific about their focus or methodology? Probably not. I believe that curiosity, in some form, is a driver of &lt;em&gt;all research&lt;/em&gt;, whether investigating the mechanisms of photosynthesis or engineering a more efficient solar panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important issue with the curiosity-labeling is that it can justify just about anything. Because curiosity is viewed as an inherently virtuous motivation, it can overshadow important considerations around research, like ethics, societal impact, and practical relevance. By the time the implications become evident, the genie may be out of the bottle. Consider the examples below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples-of-curiosity-driven-research-gone-wrong&quot;&gt;Examples of curiosity-driven research gone wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one example, in the Manhattan Project, scientific curiosity about nuclear fission ultimately led to the development of the atomic bomb. While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalww2museum.org/war/articles/making-the-atomic-bomb-trinity-test&quot;&gt;theoretical groundwork&lt;/a&gt; was undeniably impressive, its application in Hiroshima and Nagasaki was not. Similarly, studies into pathogenic organisms, even if motivated by neutral aim of understanding them better, pose biorisks. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_biological_weapons_program&quot;&gt;Soviet Union’s biological warfare division&lt;/a&gt;, for example, weaponized anthrax and smallpox. In 2002, the same year that Europe and Australia were declared polio-free, American scientists synthesized this virus in an academic laboratory in New York City, spurring &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.2968/066003001&quot;&gt;conversations on ethics of such research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is the ongoing development of advanced surveillance technologies. While curiosity about artificial intelligence and data processing drives these innovations, their misuse for tracking of individuals and manipulation of public opinion are tangible societal risks. In these cases, curiosity unchecked by ethical and value-based frameworks can lead to development of technologies that exacerbate, not address, important challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;curiosity--neither-good-nor-bad&quot;&gt;Curiosity – neither good nor bad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, curiosity is neither inherently good nor bad. Its impact depends entirely on how it is channeled. Below, I suggest that channeling the curiosity towards important needs can generate impactful research directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;need-inspired-research-as-an-impactful-outlet-for-scientific-curiosity&quot;&gt;Need-inspired research as an impactful outlet for scientific curiosity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous section, I cautioned against using “curiosity-driven” as a blanket label for research, while recognizing curiosity as a valuable personal quality and driver of discovery. Here I argue that individuals and funders can maximize the impact of scientific curiosity by channeling it into &lt;em&gt;need-driven&lt;/em&gt;, sometimes referred to also as &lt;em&gt;use-inspired&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mission-based&lt;/em&gt;, research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_8_CuriosityNeedMeme.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-need-driven-research&quot;&gt;What is need-driven research?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need-driven research focuses on addressing specific goals and challenges. It operates at the intersection of scientific exploration and societal relevance, channeling the natural curiosity of scientists into areas where breakthroughs are likely to have transformative impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most renowned organizations embodying this approach is the U.S. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.darpa.mil/&quot;&gt;Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA)&lt;/a&gt;. Founded in 1958 by President Eisenhower, DARPA’s mission is to identify and fund projects at the intersection of frontier scientific capability and societal and national need. Its results speak for themselves: DARPA has played pivotal roles in the development of mRNA vaccines, weather satellites, and even the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the UK-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;Laboratory of Molecular Biology (LMB)&lt;/a&gt; is an example of need-driven research in fundamental science. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02085-2&quot;&gt;recent &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; highlighted the lab’s strategic focus on “identifying new and important scientific questions in uncrowded fields that require pioneering technologies to answer them.” By creating the tools necessary to open new fields, LMB has catalyzed breakthroughs across molecular biology. The authors of the article concluded with a “call for the LMB’s strategy to be used as a blueprint for other institutes focusing on fundamental research.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number of modern organizations are also embracing the need-driven philosophy. ARIA, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wellcomeleap.org/&quot;&gt;Welcome Leap&lt;/a&gt;, and recently the &lt;a href=&quot;Novo Nordisk Foundation&quot;&gt;Novo Nordisk Foundation&lt;/a&gt; are some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claus Felby, Senior Vice President for Biotech at the Novo Nordisk Foundation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/claus-felby-698a09176_missionbasedresearch-climateaction-collaboration-activity-7267794475177934849-v3N3?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; the shift of foundation’s focus on ‘mission-based’ research in late 2024. He highlighted the limitations of traditional research models, pointing out that three-year funding cycles simply cannot deliver on complex and urgent problems like climate change. Felby advocated for mission-based research, which emphasizes prioritization and critical evaluation of scientific pursuits. He underscored this point: “If the path you are following has a very low chance of succeeding […] then you should stop.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome Leap offers a model that I particularly like, based on a framework described in Donald Stokes’s 1997 book, Pasteur’s Quadrant. Stokes formulated the “Theory of Breakthroughs” and categorized research pursuits along two dimensions: whether they have &lt;em&gt;high basic science content&lt;/em&gt; and whether they &lt;em&gt;drive application&lt;/em&gt; (see figure below). He identified the most impactful research by being high along both dimensions. This lands the research into so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasteur%27s_quadrant&quot;&gt;“use-inspired basic research” or “Pasteur’s” quadrant&lt;/a&gt;. This is of course the legacy of Louis Pasteur, whose work on vaccination, fermentation, and pasteurization transformed both science and public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_8_stokesQuadrant.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.org/network-innovation-wellcome-leap-dugan-gabriel/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;need-driven-research-the-way-forward&quot;&gt;Need-driven research, the way forward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By aligning the thrill of discovery with societal impact, need-driven research avoids the pitfalls of curiosity for curiosity’s sake. It encourages accountability, and demands prioritization, and a willingness to pivot when a path proves unproductive. In this way, it offers the best of both worlds: the excitement of exploration and the contribution to addressing important challenges. As we go on to tackle these complex global challenges, embracing more need-driven research isn’t just a strategic choice; it’s a necessity. Through organizations like DARPA, LMB, and Welcome Leap, we have valuable pioneering examples of how to do this in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/claus-felby-698a09176_missionbasedresearch-climateaction-collaboration-activity-7267794475177934849-v3N3?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&quot;&gt;Novo Nordisk Foundation’s video announcing focus on mission-based research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statecraft.pub/p/how-to-build-the-british-arpa&quot;&gt;Statecraft article: “How to Build the British ARPA”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.org/network-innovation-wellcome-leap-dugan-gabriel/&quot;&gt;issues.org - Changing the Business of Breakthroughs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2023.11.039&quot;&gt;The innovation menagerie: New institutional structures are expanding horizons for early-stage research – Paywalled&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02085-2&quot;&gt;The strategy behind one of the most successful labs in the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><category term="essay" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #8: Need-driven research is a better investment of taxpayers money than research driven by curiosity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Academia Better, Part 3 - Foster Foundations of Policymaking</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Academia Better, Part 3 - Foster Foundations of Policymaking" /><published>2025-01-08T07:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T07:57:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter3.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’ with one’s thesis, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #7&lt;/strong&gt;: The foundations and practical experience of policy making must be included in graduate education.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;!---break---&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s interconnected world, politicians are faced with complex decision-making, with consequences on shared resources such as the environment, as well as the national economic competitiveness and societal development. Establishing a dialogue between experts and policymakers is vital to help assure quality of these decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History offers examples of how robust collaboration has led to progress. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC1422744/&quot;&gt;eradication of smallpox&lt;/a&gt;, for example, was made possible by collaboration between scientists, who developed the vaccine and mapped its deployment, and policymakers, who coordinated international vaccination campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when communication falters, progress can turn into regress. Take, for example, the complex regulator landscape around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.labiotech.eu/in-depth/gmo-regulations-europe/&quot;&gt;gene-edited organisms&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cell.ag/blog/ambika-hiranandani-regulatory-policies-on-cell-based-foods-a-global-overview&quot;&gt;cell-based products&lt;/a&gt; in Europe. Policies have hindered agricultural innovation and as a result, Europe continues to lag in developing technologies supporting food security and environmental sustainability. In the US, Drug Abuse Resistance education program &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/07/12/a-brief-history-of-d-a-r-e-the-anti-drug-program-jeff-sessions-wants-to-revive/&quot;&gt;has continued to receive millions of dollars in funding annually&lt;/a&gt;, despite solid evidence that the program is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/death-rate-from-opioid-use?tab=chart&amp;amp;country=BRA~CAN~CHL~FRA~DEU~ITA~JPN~PRT~ESP~GBR~USA&quot;&gt;ineffective&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, hundreds of &lt;a href=&quot;https://evidence2impact.psu.edu/what-we-do/research-translation-platform/results-first-resources/clearing-house-database/&quot;&gt;evidence-based programs&lt;/a&gt; struggled to secure any funding.
Effective policymaking requires that regulators ground new regulations in scientific evidence. Traditional PhD programs, designed to cultivate academic expertise, don’t contribute to preparing future scientific leaders for establishing or maintaining this dialogue. Here I argue for integrating the foundations and practical experience of policymaking into PhD-level education to help address this skill gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-shapes-the-economy-and-directs-progress&quot;&gt;Policy shapes the economy and directs progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policy shapes the course of innovation and technology and can act as an enabler. Number of examples of effective policymaking show how it can steer economies toward growth and drive technological advancements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take patent law, for instance. The legal frameworks for patenting biotechnology have been pivotal in the growth of the biotech industry. The first U.S. patent for an engineered organisms (&lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/em&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.112.2.815-823.1972&quot;&gt;initially filed in 1972&lt;/a&gt;, was approved in June 1980, after long deliberations and several ruling reversals. This decision established robust incentives for the development of engineered organisms, making it one of the pivotal events in the establishment of biotechnology industry. Today, many of these organisms, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oncomouse&quot;&gt;laboratory mice&lt;/a&gt;, represent indispensable resource throughout both fundamental and drug development research in academia and the industry.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, up until 90’s, many countries, in efforts to offer broader access, have excepted pharmaceuticals from patent law, or offered only limited protection.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 1995, the creation of the World Trade Organization, and the introduction of the new Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights, or TRIPS, &lt;a href=&quot;https://asteriskmag.com/issues/05/pepfar-and-the-costs-of-cost-benefit-analysis&quot;&gt;enforced a minimum 20-year long patent proception&lt;/a&gt; on drugs. Consequently, companies became substantially more incentivized to invest in R&amp;amp;D. If successful, the results of a breakthrough, but risky, medical research, would be protected. Overall, this has been an important incentive for innovation and the development of new medicines. Conversations on whether this leads to optimal tradeoff between innovation and access are ongoing.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the energy sector, the European Parliament’s ambitious &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.ec.europa.eu/eu-action/climate-strategies-targets/2040-climate-target_en&quot;&gt;goal to reduce emissions by 90% by 2040&lt;/a&gt; underscores how policy can set the stage for sweeping changes. Meeting this target will require large investments in renewables,  grid infrastructure, as well as transformations across transport and food sectors. Similarly, Europe’s dependence on lithium from China, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/finance/commodities-futures/europe-to-ramp-up-lithium-mining-to-cut-chinas-market-grip-6179790e&quot;&gt;currently accounting for 97% continent’s consumption&lt;/a&gt;, represents a geopolitical and sustainability risk. Recently, Europe set the goal of sourcing at least 10% of lithium from within the continent. Doing so will require establishing a whole new supply chain for lithium refining and processing, as well as open secondary opportunities for battery and other product manufactures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the realm of agriculture, Denmark [recently became the first country] to introduce tax on carbon emissions from this industry. Europe as a whole, overall supportive of the alt-protein space, stands a lot to gain in this transition, as it could decrease its dependance on overseas land &lt;a href=&quot;https://vegconomist.com/sustainability-environment/alternative-proteins-displace-meat-dairy-consumed-in-europe/&quot;&gt;by over 75%&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, policy can also stifle progress. The political divides surrounding &lt;a href=&quot;ttps://www.brookings.edu/articles/raj-chetty-in-14-charts-big-findings-on-opportunity-and-mobility-we-should-know/&quot;&gt;social inequality&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://edition.cnn.com/2024/05/09/politics/climate-trump-biden-what-matters/index.html&quot;&gt;environmental reforms&lt;/a&gt; are examples where science-backed solutions often fail to gain traction. In the U.S., for instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateenergylab.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Caldeira-History-climate-science-2024-04-05.pdf&quot;&gt;despite clear evidence on climate change&lt;/a&gt;, political resistance delays necessary transitions. Similarly, Scientists have &lt;a href=&quot;ttps://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abe9090&quot;&gt;repeatedly spoken&lt;/a&gt; against the global health and environmental impacts of waste and chemical pollution, but policy-response has been lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-history-and-geography-of-science-policy-relationships&quot;&gt;The history and geography of science-policy relationships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between science and politics has evolved through history. In ancient Greece and Rome, philosophers like Aristotle and Cicero were both scientists and politicians, making the exchange of ideas between the two seamless. This interplay persisted through the Renaissance, with figures like Galileo and Leonardo da Vinci influencing public policy. Later, Newton was a member of British Parliament and Leibniz was an advisor to several German rulers. However, as science became more specialized, the gap between scientists and policymakers widened.
Today, this relationship varies also globally. In the U.S., research and innovation are often driven by private industries, helping to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cell.ag/blog/ambika-hiranandani-regulatory-policies-on-cell-based-foods-a-global-overview&quot;&gt;set up innovative policies&lt;/a&gt; relatively quickly in some areas. Simultaneously, ongoing political polarization complicates the adoption of scientific advice in other areas. Europe, on the other hand, places greater emphasis on research-driven policy, which helps it to take the lead in many green initiatives. Singaporean government is exceptionally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrf.gov.sg/rie-ecosystem/ecosystem/&quot;&gt;active in integrating scientific expertise into policymaking&lt;/a&gt;, helping to create one of the most effective and efficient policy and innovation landscapes worldwide. As one example, the country has, increased its life expectancy by 26.3 years over the last 75 years, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/life-expectancy?yScale=log&amp;amp;time=1950..latest&amp;amp;country=SGP~NLD~USA~BRA~CZE&quot;&gt;more than any other developed country&lt;/a&gt; worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scientists-have-a-responsibility-in-improving-the-quality-of-public-discourse&quot;&gt;Scientists have a responsibility in improving the quality of public discourse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In times when issues like climate change and economic inequality demand nuanced solutions, the quality of public dialogue often falls short. Politicians too frequently resort to claims that attract attention over those grounded in evidence. Sensationalism and populism win elections.
Scientists must take an active role in counteracting this trend. By stepping into public conversations, they can anchor debates in facts and offer a counterbalance to misinformation. For example, discussions on immigration &lt;a href=&quot;https://heindehaas.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;often spiral into fearmongering&lt;/a&gt;, sidelining its complex economic and social dynamics. (Read my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/propositions/Migration.html&quot;&gt;post in migration here&lt;/a&gt; for more context.) Similarly, climate policies are too often treated as squabbles, ignoring the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2023/mar/20/ipcc-climate-crisis-report-delivers-final-warning-on-15c&quot;&gt;reality of scientific consensus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;equipping-scientists-with-foundations-of-policymaking&quot;&gt;Equipping scientists with foundations of policymaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have illustrated above, good policymaking requires collaboration and interdisciplinarity. Whether it is addressing climate change or immigration, effective solutions can be shaped only based on balanced input from multiple stakeholders including scientists, industry, and legislators. Number of skills can help scientists navigate this landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improving-the-efficacy-of-scientific-engagement-in-politics&quot;&gt;Improving the efficacy of scientific engagement in politics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A skill or activity that is often regarded as important is communicating scientists’ perspectives on policy agendas. The rise of social media and blogging created a compelling case for scientists - maybe doing the right thing is as straightforward as tweeting about it. Given the processed-based nature of lawmaking, the number of people involved, and the overall nuance, this is simply unlikely. Scientists may be doing meaningful work growing an audience around an important case, but practically speaking, this is mostly preaching to choir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-trust-and-communicating-with-legislative-staff&quot;&gt;Building trust and communicating with legislative staff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those scientists that would like to contribute with their expertise to policymaking, probably the most important activity is building trust-based relationships with actors across the lawmaking process. A vital part of this is inherent to scientists’ work, publishing quality and unbiased research. Another vital part is communicating it. The current skill gap among researchers makes it hard to understand with whom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All decision-makers rely on input and advice to be able to do their work. Naively, scientists would like to influence these decision-makers directly. This tends to be ineffective. Except for rare circumstances, scientists cannot capture enough decision-maker’s bandwidth, neither can they establish a relationship of mutual trust, grounded in empathy and understanding of other sides’ priorities and what motivates them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, scientists should focus their efforts on building relationships and communicating with lower ranking professionals involved in policymaking. These individuals serve as gatekeepers with the influence over which data reaches decision-makers and which context it is interpreted in.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (I like to call this group ‘gov’t back office’.) This group, often technically minded and used to reading and evaluating research, is eventually much easier for scientists to establish a common language with. Once these gatekeepers are identified, scientists can again leverage much of their training. The ability to write audience-specific technical texts is as valuable in science as it is in policy, and so is the establishment of communities that can co-shape research-based agendas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theoretical-foundations&quot;&gt;Theoretical foundations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the basic level, scientists should learn about different policy instruments - regulations, incentives, voluntary agreements, etc. - and develop an understanding of their benefits and limitations in different contexts. As I have illustrated above, scientists must also get a more holistic view of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncchpp.ca/docs/ModeleEtapesPolPubliques_EN.pdf&quot;&gt;policy cycle&lt;/a&gt;, from initiation to evaluation. This is necessary for scientists to be able to identify the relevant parties and processes throughout policymaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scientists may want to go deeper into theoretical frameworks of public policy. Models like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_streams_framework&quot;&gt;Multiple Streams Framework&lt;/a&gt; (MSF) explain how policy change happens and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punctuated_equilibrium&quot;&gt;Punctuated Equilibrium Theory&lt;/a&gt; shows why policies often remain static for long periods. Normative foundations explore the ethical dimensions of decision-making, helping to consider broader societal impact. &lt;a href=&quot;ttps://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_choice&quot;&gt;Public Choice Theory&lt;/a&gt; helps apply economic principles to political decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approaches-to-teaching-the--foundations-of-policymaking&quot;&gt;Approaches to teaching the -foundations of policymaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching policymaking to scientists should happen as a blend of instruction and experiential learning.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Instruction transmits foundational knowledge about policymaking processes, while experiential learning builds the skills and know-how needed to navigate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct instruction can include lectures on policy theories, case studies, and ethical considerations. A highly effective option would be to invite governmental scientific advisors or technical staff from legislative bodies. These professionals can offer practical insights into the mechanics of policymaking, and their presence is a valuable opportunity for building professional relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiential learning should give students the opportunity to work in real-world policy environments. Fellowships play a critical role, offering entry points into governmental and policymaking institutions, where participants can directly engage with policy challenges. Simultaneously, they are widely regarded as attractive contributions to career capital. Competitions, case studies, and team challenges can be also effective, provided they have significant buy-in from government agencies, non-profits, or interest groups to assure their relevance and impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diy-ing-your-policymaking-education&quot;&gt;DIY-ing your policymaking education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of policymaking as a structural component of graduate education. Scientists have to rely on patchwork of resources available online. While these have clear disadvantages, for example the lack of adequate contextualization for scientists’ background and geographies, they still offer invaluable entry points to the field. Below, with the goal to help scientists interested in learning more about policymaking, I have assembled a few tables summarizing fellowships, online courses, relevant organizations, and publications that can support this learning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fellowships&quot;&gt;Fellowships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Country&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Horizon Public Service Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://horizonpublicservice.org/2025-horizon-fellowship-cohort-applications/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Emerging Leaders in Biosecurity Initiative (ELBI) Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://centerforhealthsecurity.org/education-training/elbi-fellowship/apply-to-the-elbi-fellowship&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bellingcat Tech Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bellingcat.com/bellingcat-tech-fellowship-opportunity/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;European Tech Policy Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techpolicyfellowship.eu/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Europe&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fellowship for Ending Bioweapons&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://councilonstrategicrisks.org/2024/03/11/call-for-applications-fellowship-for-ending-bioweapons-2024/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No Patient Left Behind Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nopatientleftbehind.org/nplb-fellowship&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CDC Fellowships for Students&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jobs.cdc.gov/working-at-cdc/students.html&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;U.S. Senate Committee on Biotechnology Fellowships&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biotech.senate.gov/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;AAAS Science &amp;amp; Technology Policy Fellowships&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aaas.org/resources/science-policy-resources&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Council on Strategic Risks Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://council.science/news/call-experts-bwc/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Emerging Tech Policy Careers Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://emergingtechpolicy.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;AAAS Science &amp;amp; Technology Policy Fellowships&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aaas.org/programs/science-technology-policy-fellowships&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FASEB Science Policy Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.faseb.org/professional-development/faseb-science-policy-fellowship&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;New York State Science Policy Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rockinst.org/education-programs/science-and-technology-fellowship/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;National Academies’ Science Policy Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalacademies.org/our-work/science-policy-fellowship&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;California Council on Science and Technology Policy Fellowships&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ccst.us/ccst-science-fellows-program/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mid-Career Biodefense Bootcamp Fellowship&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://councilonstrategicrisks.org/2024/02/29/call-for-applications-mid-career-biodefense-bootcamp-fellowship-2024/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;online-courses&quot;&gt;Online Courses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Addressing Challenges Posed by Chemical and Biological Weapons&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sipri.org/news/2024/addressing-challenges-posed-chemical-and-biological-weapons-intensive-online-introductory-course&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Biorisks Training Camp&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.effisciences.org/en/events/biorisks-training-camp&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Biosecurity Fundamentals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biosecurityfundamentals.com/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bioscience Careers Policy Events&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biosciencecareers.org/education-policy-and-career-events&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Online Tutorial on Epidemic Intelligence&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/initiatives/global-outbreak-alert-and-response-network/resources&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Science Diplomacy Online Course&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sciencediplomacy.org/education&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Public Health Policy Fundamentals&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/public-health-policy&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Risk Governance of Emerging Technologies&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/sti/risk-governance-of-emerging-technologies.htm&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Introduction to Global Biosecurity&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://futurelearn.com/courses/global-biosecurity&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organizations&quot;&gt;Organizations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RAND Corporation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rand.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rethink Priorities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkpriorities.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SecureBio&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://securebio.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Open Philanthropy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openphilanthropy.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Job Portal for Policy Careers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jobs.80000hours.org/organisations/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Future Matters&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://future-matters.org/careers/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Civic Tech Field Guide&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://civictech.guide/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Center for Humane Technology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.humanetech.com/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Good Food Institute (GFI)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gfi.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Research Translation Platform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://evidence2impact.psu.edu/research-translation-platform/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;International Science Council&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://council.science/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Global Catastrophic Risk Institute&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gcrinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Effective Altruism Policy Programs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/policy&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;publications&quot;&gt;Publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Statecraft&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statecraft.pub/&quot;&gt;https://www.statecraft.pub/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Institute for Progress (IFP)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifp.org/&quot;&gt;https://ifp.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Asimov Press&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asimov.press/&quot;&gt;https://www.asimov.press/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Asterisk Magazine&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asteriskmag.com/&quot;&gt;https://asteriskmag.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Quanta Magazine&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.quantamagazine.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Issues in Science and Technology&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.org/&quot;&gt;https://issues.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Works in Progress&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worksinprogress.co/&quot;&gt;https://worksinprogress.co/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The 1991 Project&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://the1991project.com/&quot;&gt;https://the1991project.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kaiser Family Foundation (KFF)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kff.org/&quot;&gt;https://www.kff.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Conversation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/&quot;&gt;https://theconversation.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;considerations-for-policymaking-scientists&quot;&gt;Considerations for policymaking scientists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For scientists who want to step into the policymaking arena, there are important considerations to keep in mind. First, politics often reflects the demographics of those in power - typically older, wealthier, white men. This indirectly shapes policy priorities. Similarly, the scientific community itself can lack diversity, and scientists must be aware of the limits of perspectives they themselves bring to policy discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain public trust, scientists must ensure their recommendations serve the public good, not narrowly benefit some institutions or industries. Similarly, engaging in overtly partisan policymaking can jeopardize a scientist’s credibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the academic system often undervalues policy-related contributions. Increasing the recognition of this type of work within academia is important to encourage more scientists to bridge the gap between research and policymaking and making this experience more valuable for scientists. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/cea/&quot;&gt;High-profile programs&lt;/a&gt; are helpful, but similar initiatives are needed across the career development spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultivating a healthy relationship between science and politics is undoubtedly challenging. It requires trust, patience, and a willingness to bridge diverse perspectives. However, its value for shaping a sustainable and equitable future cannot is vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I have argued that current graduate training mostly fails to equip future scientific leaders with skills and know-how needed to meaningfully contribute to policymaking. Simple changes, such as exposing scientists to professionals involved in the regulatory process, can help cultivate interest among graduates. For those trainees that find policy work interesting, structured curricula should be put in place to help them acquire theoretical foundations. Stakeholders across government, non-profit and academia must work together to facilitate fellowships that give trainees the opportunity to build career capital and professional network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s complex world, we need more collaboration and sharing of expertise. The efforts presented here should enable a greater share of scientists to leverage their technical knowledge to assist the lawmaking process, delivering evidence-based policies that help to protect the climate, address societal disparities, and drive innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scicomm.plos.org/2017/11/30/scientists-and-policymakers-not-such-strange-bedfellows/&quot;&gt;Scientists and Policymakers – Not Such Strange Bedfellows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/connecting-researchers-and-legislators-can-lead-to-policies-that-reflect-scientific-evidence-215572&quot;&gt;Connecting researchers and legislators can lead to policies that reflect scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ccnpps-ncchpp.ca/public-policy-models-and-their-usefulness-in-public-health-the-stages-model/&quot;&gt;Public Policy Models and Their Usefulness in Public Health: The Stages Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://press.asimov.com/articles/gmo-patent &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nber.org/system/files/chapters/c10794/c10794.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/trips_e/pharma_ato186_e.htm &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.iatp.org/sites/default/files/Cut_the_Cost_-_Patent_Injustice_How_World_Trad.htm &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.2012955118 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://psycnet.apa.org/buy/2019-39192-002 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’ with one’s thesis, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #7: The foundations and practical experience of policy making must be included in graduate education.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Academia Better, Part 2 – Actively Adopt Modern Tools and Project Management Practices</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Academia Better, Part 2 – Actively Adopt Modern Tools and Project Management Practices" /><published>2025-01-08T07:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T07:56:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’ with one’s thesis, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #6&lt;/strong&gt;: Universities should establish fellowships that fund stays of industry professionals in academic labs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;MakingAcademiaBetter1.html&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I argued that the culture of work and research management in industry surpasses that of academia. Industry offers higher salaries and better managerial training, has a larger number of specialized support personnel, generally operates with larger R&amp;amp;D budgets, and implements a range of project management and strategic alignment tools. It also prioritizes reproducibility, automation, and data-driven decision-making to maintain high efficiency and competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I build on this argument and propose a solution: universities should establish fellowships that fund stays of industry researchers and research managers in in academic labs. Such fellowships could significantly improve academic culture, productivity, and relevance. This post will focus on the third aspect – relevance - while touching on improvements to work culture and productivity that have been discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;MakingAcademiaBetter1.html&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt; in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;academias-core-roles&quot;&gt;Academia’s core roles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academia serves two primary purposes, &lt;strong&gt;a)&lt;/strong&gt; training the next generation of researchers, and &lt;strong&gt;b)&lt;/strong&gt; generation of new findings. A third, and b) associated, purpose is &lt;strong&gt;c)&lt;/strong&gt; translation of these findings into practice. Let’s look at these purposes in turn, starting with a) the training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;training-the-next-generation-of-researchers&quot;&gt;Training the next generation of researchers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The odds of career as an academic scientist are relatively low. This is an oft discussed feature of the academic career path. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Only about 20% of PhDs will enter the tenure track, and about 60% of these will be eventually given tenure. 10 years after graduation, about 10% of PhDs will hold scientific staff roles in academic research. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://guzey.com/economics/bloom/#:~:text=Further%2C%20the%20biggest%20employer%20of%20Harvard%20and%20MIT%20alumni%20is%20Google%2C%20followed%20by%20Microsoft%20and%20Amazon&quot;&gt;biggest employer&lt;/a&gt; of top-school alumni is big tech. This means that around 90% of all academic trainees will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; end up working as independent academics. Despite this, their training is predominantly, if not exclusively, geared towards academic skills and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data on the extent to which the current nature of academic training negatively impacts workforce productivity is lacking. However, anecdotal evidence is plentiful. Those familiar with academia often know individuals who have struggled to find jobs aligned with their training, whether immediately after earning their PhD or following a period as a postdoc. This frequently results in unplanned unemployment or acceptance of roles for which they are overqualified, undermining the time and financial investment in their education. Such outcomes represent economic losses and highlight a failure to build relevant career capital. Change is essential, and new approaches are needed to enhance the relevance of academic training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can offer some examples on how we could achieve this, drawn from my time as a PhD candidate. During this period, I engaged with smart people through organizations like iGEM, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nucleate.xyz/&quot;&gt;Nucleate&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalbiotechrevolution.com/&quot;&gt;Global Biotech Revolution&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bluedot.org/&quot;&gt;BlueDot Impact&lt;/a&gt;. One type of experience that influenced me was working with young, ambitious, intelligent and kind people. I got to write papers with smart undergrads, learn alongside highly productive teammates, and collaborate with visionary prospective entrepreneurs. These experiences influenced my academic thinking and strategic planning abilities as much as my experience as an academic trainee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another valuable learning experience was founding Nucleate Netherlands. This role exposed me to a culture with an accent on quality of presentation (e.g. branding), and the nature of ‘always being ready’, as well as fostered supportiveness for personal agency and proactive effort. It also allowed me to delve into the Dutch and European startup scene and understand some of its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/2024/05/09/StateOfDutchTech_Problems.html&quot;&gt;challenges&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/2024/06/09/SolutionsForTheDutchTech.html&quot;&gt;opportunities&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, it was another great chance to work alongside bright people, learning from their approaches to managing projects and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generation-of-new-findings&quot;&gt;Generation of new findings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine the second key task of academic institutions, generating new findings, and its corollary, translating them into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic institutions generally excel at creating new knowledge. This aspect is heavily measured and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/nature-index/research-leaders/2024/institution/all/all/global&quot;&gt;ranked&lt;/a&gt;, making it a primary focus for universities and research institutions. However, in my view, not enough attention is given to triage on relevance and significance of these findings. While current approach helps the production of academic papers, their impact outside academia varies widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This variability is inherent to research - some findings and researchers will have an outsized impact. Nonetheless, some aspects of the current system can be improved. We must critically evaluate the research we pursue, prioritizing projects with either breakthrough potential or good pathways to translation. The “middle ground” tends to offer the lowest return on investment (See my &lt;a href=&quot;MakingAcademiaBetter4.html&quot;&gt;other post&lt;/a&gt; on curiosity- vs need-driven research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proposed-solution--fellowships-for-industry-professionals&quot;&gt;Proposed solution – Fellowships for industry professionals&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above, I highlighted two important issues in academia – the inappropriateness of academic training for majority of post-academic careers, and the highly variable level of relevance of academic research. I believe that fellowships funding stays of industry professionals in academic labs and institutions could help address both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;increasing-relevance-of-academic-training&quot;&gt;Increasing relevance of academic training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, inviting industry professionals to spend time in academic labs as scientists and managers establishes a new interface for knowledge transfer. Academic trainees will get the opportunity to consider problems from new perspectives, explore different solutions, and contextualize their research in industry-relevant contexts. Additionally, they will get exposed to more sophisticated managerial culture, develop appreciation for strategic planning, and build valuable professional connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have illustrated through my personal experiences of working with students above, this arrangement can be mutually beneficial. The industry fellows are likely to benefit from meeting young trainees, for example by getting easier access to new research findings, developing better appreciation for younger colleagues, and finding increased job satisfaction through mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;increasing-relevance-of-academic-research&quot;&gt;Increasing relevance of academic research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to enhancing training, inviting industry professionals to academic labs can also help increase the relevance of academic output by helping to identify research that has high potential to be translatable as well as to weed out the one that does not. It can help to suggest new areas for research that correspond to currently pressing industry needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, academics will be freer to dedicate time to focus on developing research paths with breakthrough potential, the most important and impactful domain of academic research. Finally, academic grants frequently require some industry collaboration or co-investment, or at least ideas for commercialization. Connections to industry and opportunities for early vetting of such ideas would be of high value to any academic and facilitated through the type of fellowship proposed here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the benefits to academia, spending time in academic labs is likely to have unique benefits for industry scientists as well. Industry R&amp;amp;D is generally more focused, and, in many cases, unable to dedicate resources for pursuing projects that are longer or riskier than some threshold. This has been subject to much scrutiny, with critiques claiming that ‘the industry ceased to innovate’ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/scitranslmed.3002273&quot;&gt;an example from pharma&lt;/a&gt;). This is overblown. Industry is, by far, the largest R&amp;amp;D spender. I find this quite impressive - the five largest tech companies (Amazon, Google, Meta, Apple and Microsoft), plus one big pharma (Merck) spent nearly as much as the whole industry within European Union. This itself is more than six-fold more than all the EU governments have spent combined. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is, however, true that in the past few decades, industry generally shifted to a model where access to a significant portion of innovation comes through the acquisition of outside firms (although this may be changing &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). Startups are closer to the newest technology, tend to be more time and resource efficient, and are generally the right place for people with a larger appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_6_Rdspending_company_EU.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Comparison of R&amp;amp;D spending in large companies and the EU.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaboration between startups and industry is generally effective, but there is room for improvement through enhanced opportunities for exchange. Consider this, fairly common, example, industry professionals may have advanced understanding of internal bottlenecks and problem spaces, yet no startups are actively developing appropriate solutions to address them. Prioritizing the communication of these needs to the right audiences is an important benefit to industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://nucleate.xyz/&quot;&gt;Nucleate&lt;/a&gt;, a global community for entrepreneurial academic trainees, I’ve observed that students, graduate students, and postdocs are incredibly valuable to industry stakeholders. Many large companies have budgets allocated for startups tackling critical problems and opportunities the industry has identified. These companies are eager to engage students early, supporting them in transforming academic projects into startups and applications more broadly. This creates a win-win dynamic: academics work on relevant problems with commercialization paths, while industry gains access to innovative startups early - often at a relatively low cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The utility of fellowships for industry professionals also holds when we consider the industry as the primary benefactor. It is not uncommon for industry scientists to have solution or product ideas themselves, but they may be unable to pursue them internally due to their technology risk profile, tangency to core business, or long development timelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing industry scientists with opportunities to spend time in academic labs through fellowships could create unique windows for exploring such ideas. One example from my personal experience illustrates this well. As a master’s student, I worked in a lab where several researchers were developing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nnano.2017.168&quot;&gt;focal molography&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The initial concept for this technology came from a scientist at Roche.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This individual took the initiative to establish a collaborative relationship with an academic group, where he was eventually able to incubate the idea through collaboration with PhDs and postdocs. His proactive approach paid off: the technology became a resounding success. In addition to multiple publications, it led to the creation of a startup founded by the academic trainees who developed the technology. That startup was later acquired by a major biopharma supplier company and is now delivering its first commercial instrument to customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this example particularly inspiring, as it represents another multi-party win-win scenario. The inventor was able to translate his vision to reality, while the PhDs and postdocs worked on challenging and meaningful problems, all of them ultimately benefiting from the startup’s establishment and acquisition. Roche, the inventor’s employer, also benefited by gaining a novel instrument for its early R&amp;amp;D pipeline, which specifications and features it even could help shape during development. The professor who hosted the collaboration saw success as well, with his group publishing good papers, filing patents, and receiving industry funding. Finally, the university also benefited by adding a startup they can brag about to its portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion---path-to-implementation&quot;&gt;Conclusion - Path to implementation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the above arguments and examples have made you more inclined to consider the opportunities such fellowship represents for both academic and industry scientists. An important question is, how would we go about implementing this? First, governments should collaborate with universities to allocate funding. Second, implementing organizations would have to work closely with industry to ensure the way the program is implemented does not subtract from the idea’s attractiveness for scientists on both sides. Handling intellectual property, for example, could become a sensitive issue. Similarly, the different cultures of work and the strong emphasis on academic independence may create friction during the program’s early stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col half&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_6_ARIAFellowship.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;ARIA and Pillar VC collaborating on fellowship for AI industry scientists.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These challenges can only be addressed through experience. Aside from isolated examples, like the Roche scientist I mentioned earlier, or an occasional sabbatical taken by a top industry scientist at an academic lab, there are few established models or best practices for such fellowships. That said, promising developments are emerging. This fall, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aria.org.uk/&quot;&gt;ARIA (the Advanced Research and Innovation Agency)&lt;/a&gt;, in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pillar.vc/&quot;&gt;Pillar VC&lt;/a&gt;, has announced a program to fund academic fellowships for leading AI industry scientists. ARIA is the UK’s vehicle for reviving the British innovation engine, so it is really exciting to see them take up this initiative. While the program’s first fellows will only begin in 2025, the initiative merits close attention from other countries. If successful, it could serve as a blueprint for similar initiative elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-024-02351-8#Sec1 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-34809-1.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.rdworldonline.com/top-30-rd-spending-leaders-2023-big-tech-firms-hit-new-heights/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=R%26D_expenditure &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Google published 20 times more papers in 2019 than in 2005. Amazon has grown their publication rate by more than 10 times in just 5 years, as per Maxwell Tabarrok. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/nnano.2017.168 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><category term="science" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’ with one’s thesis, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #6: Universities should establish fellowships that fund stays of industry professionals in academic labs. Introduction In a previous post, I argued that the culture of work and research management in industry surpasses that of academia. Industry offers higher salaries and better managerial training, has a larger number of specialized support personnel, generally operates with larger R&amp;amp;D budgets, and implements a range of project management and strategic alignment tools. It also prioritizes reproducibility, automation, and data-driven decision-making to maintain high efficiency and competitiveness. In this post, I build on this argument and propose a solution: universities should establish fellowships that fund stays of industry researchers and research managers in in academic labs. Such fellowships could significantly improve academic culture, productivity, and relevance. This post will focus on the third aspect – relevance - while touching on improvements to work culture and productivity that have been discussed in my previous post in more detail. Academia’s core roles Academia serves two primary purposes, a) training the next generation of researchers, and b) generation of new findings. A third, and b) associated, purpose is c) translation of these findings into practice. Let’s look at these purposes in turn, starting with a) the training. Training the next generation of researchers The odds of career as an academic scientist are relatively low. This is an oft discussed feature of the academic career path. 1,2 Only about 20% of PhDs will enter the tenure track, and about 60% of these will be eventually given tenure. 10 years after graduation, about 10% of PhDs will hold scientific staff roles in academic research. The biggest employer of top-school alumni is big tech. This means that around 90% of all academic trainees will not end up working as independent academics. Despite this, their training is predominantly, if not exclusively, geared towards academic skills and performance. Data on the extent to which the current nature of academic training negatively impacts workforce productivity is lacking. However, anecdotal evidence is plentiful. Those familiar with academia often know individuals who have struggled to find jobs aligned with their training, whether immediately after earning their PhD or following a period as a postdoc. This frequently results in unplanned unemployment or acceptance of roles for which they are overqualified, undermining the time and financial investment in their education. Such outcomes represent economic losses and highlight a failure to build relevant career capital. Change is essential, and new approaches are needed to enhance the relevance of academic training. I can offer some examples on how we could achieve this, drawn from my time as a PhD candidate. During this period, I engaged with smart people through organizations like iGEM, Nucleate, Global Biotech Revolution and BlueDot Impact. One type of experience that influenced me was working with young, ambitious, intelligent and kind people. I got to write papers with smart undergrads, learn alongside highly productive teammates, and collaborate with visionary prospective entrepreneurs. These experiences influenced my academic thinking and strategic planning abilities as much as my experience as an academic trainee. Another valuable learning experience was founding Nucleate Netherlands. This role exposed me to a culture with an accent on quality of presentation (e.g. branding), and the nature of ‘always being ready’, as well as fostered supportiveness for personal agency and proactive effort. It also allowed me to delve into the Dutch and European startup scene and understand some of its challenges and opportunities. Additionally, it was another great chance to work alongside bright people, learning from their approaches to managing projects and priorities. Generation of new findings Let’s examine the second key task of academic institutions, generating new findings, and its corollary, translating them into practice. Academic institutions generally excel at creating new knowledge. This aspect is heavily measured and ranked, making it a primary focus for universities and research institutions. However, in my view, not enough attention is given to triage on relevance and significance of these findings. While current approach helps the production of academic papers, their impact outside academia varies widely. This variability is inherent to research - some findings and researchers will have an outsized impact. Nonetheless, some aspects of the current system can be improved. We must critically evaluate the research we pursue, prioritizing projects with either breakthrough potential or good pathways to translation. The “middle ground” tends to offer the lowest return on investment (See my other post on curiosity- vs need-driven research). Proposed solution – Fellowships for industry professionals Above, I highlighted two important issues in academia – the inappropriateness of academic training for majority of post-academic careers, and the highly variable level of relevance of academic research. I believe that fellowships funding stays of industry professionals in academic labs and institutions could help address both. Increasing relevance of academic training First, inviting industry professionals to spend time in academic labs as scientists and managers establishes a new interface for knowledge transfer. Academic trainees will get the opportunity to consider problems from new perspectives, explore different solutions, and contextualize their research in industry-relevant contexts. Additionally, they will get exposed to more sophisticated managerial culture, develop appreciation for strategic planning, and build valuable professional connections. As I have illustrated through my personal experiences of working with students above, this arrangement can be mutually beneficial. The industry fellows are likely to benefit from meeting young trainees, for example by getting easier access to new research findings, developing better appreciation for younger colleagues, and finding increased job satisfaction through mentorship. Increasing relevance of academic research In addition to enhancing training, inviting industry professionals to academic labs can also help increase the relevance of academic output by helping to identify research that has high potential to be translatable as well as to weed out the one that does not. It can help to suggest new areas for research that correspond to currently pressing industry needs. In turn, academics will be freer to dedicate time to focus on developing research paths with breakthrough potential, the most important and impactful domain of academic research. Finally, academic grants frequently require some industry collaboration or co-investment, or at least ideas for commercialization. Connections to industry and opportunities for early vetting of such ideas would be of high value to any academic and facilitated through the type of fellowship proposed here. Beyond the benefits to academia, spending time in academic labs is likely to have unique benefits for industry scientists as well. Industry R&amp;amp;D is generally more focused, and, in many cases, unable to dedicate resources for pursuing projects that are longer or riskier than some threshold. This has been subject to much scrutiny, with critiques claiming that ‘the industry ceased to innovate’ (an example from pharma). This is overblown. Industry is, by far, the largest R&amp;amp;D spender. I find this quite impressive - the five largest tech companies (Amazon, Google, Meta, Apple and Microsoft), plus one big pharma (Merck) spent nearly as much as the whole industry within European Union. This itself is more than six-fold more than all the EU governments have spent combined. 3,4 It is, however, true that in the past few decades, industry generally shifted to a model where access to a significant portion of innovation comes through the acquisition of outside firms (although this may be changing 5). Startups are closer to the newest technology, tend to be more time and resource efficient, and are generally the right place for people with a larger appetite for risk. Comparison of R&amp;amp;D spending in large companies and the EU. The collaboration between startups and industry is generally effective, but there is room for improvement through enhanced opportunities for exchange. Consider this, fairly common, example, industry professionals may have advanced understanding of internal bottlenecks and problem spaces, yet no startups are actively developing appropriate solutions to address them. Prioritizing the communication of these needs to the right audiences is an important benefit to industry. From my work with Nucleate, a global community for entrepreneurial academic trainees, I’ve observed that students, graduate students, and postdocs are incredibly valuable to industry stakeholders. Many large companies have budgets allocated for startups tackling critical problems and opportunities the industry has identified. These companies are eager to engage students early, supporting them in transforming academic projects into startups and applications more broadly. This creates a win-win dynamic: academics work on relevant problems with commercialization paths, while industry gains access to innovative startups early - often at a relatively low cost. The utility of fellowships for industry professionals also holds when we consider the industry as the primary benefactor. It is not uncommon for industry scientists to have solution or product ideas themselves, but they may be unable to pursue them internally due to their technology risk profile, tangency to core business, or long development timelines. Providing industry scientists with opportunities to spend time in academic labs through fellowships could create unique windows for exploring such ideas. One example from my personal experience illustrates this well. As a master’s student, I worked in a lab where several researchers were developing focal molography. 6 The initial concept for this technology came from a scientist at Roche. This individual took the initiative to establish a collaborative relationship with an academic group, where he was eventually able to incubate the idea through collaboration with PhDs and postdocs. His proactive approach paid off: the technology became a resounding success. In addition to multiple publications, it led to the creation of a startup founded by the academic trainees who developed the technology. That startup was later acquired by a major biopharma supplier company and is now delivering its first commercial instrument to customers. I find this example particularly inspiring, as it represents another multi-party win-win scenario. The inventor was able to translate his vision to reality, while the PhDs and postdocs worked on challenging and meaningful problems, all of them ultimately benefiting from the startup’s establishment and acquisition. Roche, the inventor’s employer, also benefited by gaining a novel instrument for its early R&amp;amp;D pipeline, which specifications and features it even could help shape during development. The professor who hosted the collaboration saw success as well, with his group publishing good papers, filing patents, and receiving industry funding. Finally, the university also benefited by adding a startup they can brag about to its portfolio. Conclusion - Path to implementation I hope that the above arguments and examples have made you more inclined to consider the opportunities such fellowship represents for both academic and industry scientists. An important question is, how would we go about implementing this? First, governments should collaborate with universities to allocate funding. Second, implementing organizations would have to work closely with industry to ensure the way the program is implemented does not subtract from the idea’s attractiveness for scientists on both sides. Handling intellectual property, for example, could become a sensitive issue. Similarly, the different cultures of work and the strong emphasis on academic independence may create friction during the program’s early stages. ARIA and Pillar VC collaborating on fellowship for AI industry scientists. These challenges can only be addressed through experience. Aside from isolated examples, like the Roche scientist I mentioned earlier, or an occasional sabbatical taken by a top industry scientist at an academic lab, there are few established models or best practices for such fellowships. That said, promising developments are emerging. This fall, ARIA (the Advanced Research and Innovation Agency), in collaboration with Pillar VC, has announced a program to fund academic fellowships for leading AI industry scientists. ARIA is the UK’s vehicle for reviving the British innovation engine, so it is really exciting to see them take up this initiative. While the program’s first fellows will only begin in 2025, the initiative merits close attention from other countries. If successful, it could serve as a blueprint for similar initiative elsewhere. References https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-024-02351-8#Sec1 &amp;#8617; https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-34809-1.pdf &amp;#8617; https://www.rdworldonline.com/top-30-rd-spending-leaders-2023-big-tech-firms-hit-new-heights/ &amp;#8617; https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=R%26D_expenditure &amp;#8617; Google published 20 times more papers in 2019 than in 2005. Amazon has grown their publication rate by more than 10 times in just 5 years, as per Maxwell Tabarrok. &amp;#8617; https://www.nature.com/articles/nnano.2017.168 &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Academia Better, Part 1 - Create New Interfaces for the Interaction with Industry</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Academia Better, Part 1 - Create New Interfaces for the Interaction with Industry" /><published>2025-01-08T07:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T07:55:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2025/01/08/MakingAcademiaBetter1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposition #5&lt;/strong&gt;: The culture of academic research is not keeping pace with advancements in the for-profit sector.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---break---&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am sure I wrote the concentration somewhere… (feverishly looking through a mix of paper and electronic notes) …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can’t get your environment to install on my machine… (I &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; if I try very hard, but didn’t you say it should just work?) …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You should send an email to Tracy if you’d like to get trained to use this instrument… (she works Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, but might be on vacation; anyway, she’ll send you a test, and after the training is over, you’ll fill out a form and be good to go!)…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In academic research, we are often in the business of trying to do something for the very first time. This fosters a culture where unique solutions and one-off tricks are common and celebrated. And honestly, that’s probably unavoidable and mostly alright. In many cases, that’s what I personally love. What’s not alright however, is our tendency to extend this artisanal approach to &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; we do.
The examples at the start of this post will be familiar to most academic scientists. There are countless others. At the university where I did my PhD, orders for laboratory supplies had to be manually reviewed by no less than four people, causing week-long delays. If you didn’t manually enter the item into the ordering system, it would never arrive. Automatic stock monitoring for common chemicals? Forget about it.
Here are more examples: Want to keep your lab notebook old school, pen and paper, scribbling illegibly? Be my guest! Manually entering work hours for every day of 4+ years? Sure - great use of time! (And let’s not forget about somebody having to send reminders about it &lt;em&gt;every month!&lt;/em&gt;). I’m far from the first to argue that research needs a productivity boost: &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_5_ResearcherProductivity.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Increasing number of scientist, larger team size, and increasing complexity of scientific questions have led to decreasing per-scientist research output [&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the for-profit sector, efficiency is the mantra. If a solution can save even 5% of the time it takes to produce a deliverable, it’s likely to be adopted. Deployed across a team or company, such efficiency gains can have a tangible impact on the bottom line. Ignoring them means risking becoming irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The most important contribution management needs to make in the 21st century is […] to increase the productivity of &lt;em&gt;knowledge work&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;knowledge workers&lt;/em&gt;. […] The most valuable asset of a 21st-century institution (whether business or non-business) will be its &lt;em&gt;knowledge workers&lt;/em&gt; and their &lt;em&gt;productivity&lt;/em&gt;.” — &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Drucker&quot;&gt;Peter F. Drucker&lt;/a&gt; (1999)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Productivity isn’t everything, but, in the long run, it is almost everything. A country’s ability to improve its standard of living over time depends almost entirely on its ability to raise its output per worker.” – &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Paul_Krugman&quot;&gt;Paul Krugman&lt;/a&gt; (1994)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this extreme, but illustrative, example of the impact of increasing productivity: In 2018, the CFDA (Chinese FDA) decided to do away with large bureaucratic burden and shifted to an ‘implied license’ system. As a consequence, the time needed for new drug application reviews decreased more than fivefold. [^2, ^3] Chinese biopharma increased candidate drug filings tenfold over the last decade as a result and has already overtaken Europe in clinical trial initiations. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The inability to innovate can clearly lead to a loss of competitiveness and risk of obsolescence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_5_DrugEfficiency.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;More and more new medicines are being developed in China, mostly at the expense of Europe [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-02/big-pharma-s-bet-on-china-biotech-is-a-rare-trade-bright-spot&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example: A recent experiment introduced an AI material discovery tool to a group of scientists at a large company. A 24-month follow-up compared their performance with a control group that continued without the tool. After 16 months, the treatment group discovered 44% more new materials, filed 39.5% more patents, and generated 17% more new product prototypes compared to the control group. As the authors did not neglect to remark, “these effects are large”. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Indeed, they are large, if not massive.
Interestingly, despite increased productivity, scientists who adopted the tool reported lower job satisfaction. While it’s still early, one can easily imagine industry adopting such a tool despite its drawbacks - perhaps compensating for reduced satisfaction with bonuses tied to increased productivity.
In academia, however, where individuals often act as their own boss, adopting a tool with a learning curve that initially increases productivity only gradually - and might decrease job satisfaction - is likely to face resistance. Adoption may either occur much later, or not happen at all. 
Some could argue that adoption of such a tool may not be necessary and insist that efficiencies of industry and academic scientists are anyway too different to compare reliably. The latter is true, to some extent, but I think it still gives enough information and can help find the right direction. An interesting and simple measure to use for the quantitatively inclined could be looking at individuals’ salary. In a market economy, higher productivity leads to higher salary. A valuable goal thus could be to try to drive up academic productivity so as the reduce the size of the pay gap between industry and academia. I believe that, maybe for the first time ever, this could become possible. Not by scientists adopting the exact same tools as the industry, but, if some scientific tasks prove more amenable to be enhanced with AI, by the development of academia-specific tooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/25_propositions_5_aitoolAdoption.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;More and more new medicines are being developed in China, mostly at the expense of Europe [&lt;a href=&quot;https://aidantr.github.io/files/AI_innovation.pdf&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is valuable to look at practices in companies that are proritizing building efficient and productive work cultures. An at-hand example can be Google, which even offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/professional-certificates/google-project-management&quot;&gt;certificates in project management&lt;/a&gt;. The company implements numerous tools and approaches to enhance productivity across teams. For example, Google Docs facilitates real-time collaborative document editing, including meeting notes and SOPs. Google Sheets supports project management tasks like sprint planning, resource allocation, and KPI tracking. Integrating AI and third-party products into these tools allows further automation and workflow orchestration. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For strategic planning, Google’s implementation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objectives_and_key_results&quot;&gt;Objectives and Key Results (OKRs)&lt;/a&gt; framework aligns team goals, measures progress, and drives accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have been sending documents titled &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;paper_v16_AJMHCD.docx&lt;/code&gt;around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, Google is a fairly special place; it spent $45 billion on research in 2023 &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - nearly twice as much as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rathenau.nl/en/science-figures/investments/how-much-does-netherlands-spend-rd/government-funding-rd&quot;&gt;Dutch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-backs-uk-rd-with-record-204-billion-investment-at-autumn-budget&quot;&gt;UK&lt;/a&gt; governments combined. But one doesn’t need Google’s budget to prioritize efficiency, especially when opportunities for improvement in academic research are abundant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electronic records, including lab notebooks and shared documentation, are a must. Here’s a personal example illustrating their utility: I did my PhD in a group that had virtually no shared knowledge base, despite conducting research across several fields for more than 30 years. I do not doubt that this caused knowledge and expertise to get lost or having to be rediscovered from scratch. Contrast this with a lab where I worked on an EMBO fellowship. This lab had an internal online wiki (running on Atlassian’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence&quot;&gt;Confluence&lt;/a&gt;). Shortly after arriving, I had a better overview of the lab’s projects than I’d had in my home lab after several years. I could immediately build on prior work rather than rediscovering the wheel. In fact, my project was only possible because of the work done by previous lab members. Without electronic records, continuity without an in-person overlap and in such a short time would not have been achievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is only a very straightforward application of electronic records. Looking into the future, I don’t see why it would not enable automatic material ordering. Similarly, there should be no reason to continue to write research papers entirely from scratch. Keeping an electronic lab notebook should allow for a draft - including figures, methods and SI - to be autogenerated. And while we are at that, alongside producing a paper version for humans, I expect future automations will produce one for machines as well, with rich metadata, and protocols in standardized language that could be directly implemented by automated labs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall the quotes by Drucker and Krugman. If knowledge workers’ productivity matters to us, and we consider academics as knowledge workers, then these steps seem only natural. They will free scientists’ time for more creative work and represent an implementable solution towards addressing the reproducibility crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, these innovations will never come withing individual scientist’s reach if the whole academic community continues to consider ‘management’ a swear word and looking down on efficiency as something that is below their standards. Of course, efficiency does not always equal productivity. But often it does, even in academia, and when this is the case, eschewing efficiency is hurting science, contributing to research irreproducibility, and wasting taxpayers’ resources. And that’s not a mission I want to be subscribing to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unilever decided to be proactive and slash recruitment times by using machine learning algorithms and natural language processing to analyse speech patterns during virtual interviews. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abcmoney.co.uk/2023/06/examples-of-global-companies-today-using-automation-tools-to-improve-their-efficiency/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-02/big-pharma-s-bet-on-china-biotech-is-a-rare-trade-bright-spot &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://aidantr.github.io/files/AI_innovation.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.itsdart.com/blog/what-does-google-use-for-project-management &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://www.rdworldonline.com/top-30-rd-spending-leaders-2023-big-tech-firms-hit-new-heights/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><category term="science" /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">Background: In the Netherlands, it is customary to include ‘propositions’, essentially opinionated statements defended alongside one’s doctoral work. In this post series, I am outlining the arguments supporting my propositions. Proposition #5: The culture of academic research is not keeping pace with advancements in the for-profit sector.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accelerating Drug Discovery - The Role of AI in Uncovering New Targets</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/11/10/AITargetIdentification.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accelerating Drug Discovery - The Role of AI in Uncovering New Targets" /><published>2024-11-10T16:22:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T16:22:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2024/11/10/AITargetIdentification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/11/10/AITargetIdentification.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This article was co-authored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/merchantkevinwb/&quot;&gt;Kevin Merchant&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/&quot;&gt;Martin Holub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development of novel drugs has been a critical contributor to extending healthspan and fighting diseases, but the process is complex. The involvement of multiple stakeholders and strict regulatory processes are responsible for some of it, but that contribution is dwarfed by our limited understanding of underlying biological processes. Over the past decade, artificial intelligence (AI) has progressed rapidly showing reasoning ability over large multidimensional datasets. AI, indeed, is transforming the drug discovery process as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we highlight the role of AI in a critical task in the early drug discovery process: target identification. We first introduce the technical background. Next, we review the state-of-the-art using industry examples. Finally, we highlight challenges and directions for future development. Questions we address are: &lt;strong&gt;How is AI currently used in target identification?&lt;/strong&gt; And: &lt;strong&gt;What future developments of AI would position it to make the largest positive impact on this task?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-target-identification&quot;&gt;Understanding Target Identification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drug development is a long and complex process, with average estimates of around 12 years from conceptualization to approval — although post-COVID-19, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01276-4&quot;&gt;efforts have been made by approval bodies to shorten it&lt;/a&gt; [1]. This is happening through a number of approaches, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111%2Fcts.12745&quot;&gt;accelerated approval pathways&lt;/a&gt; [2], leveraging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2022/08/10/real-world-data-expedite-drug-approval-process/&quot;&gt;real world data and evidence&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/master-protocols-efficient-clinical-trial-design-strategies-expedite-development-oncology-drugs-and&quot;&gt;changes to clinical trial design&lt;/a&gt; [3]. Lead discovery is the first step, including target identification &amp;amp; screening for compounds or biologics against the target, followed by optimization of lead compound and preclinical testing. If the lead compound manages to get through these hoops, it can finally go into clinical trials, where success can pave the way for approval and the title “drug”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Target identification is an inherent part of academic and industry research. Traditionally, it describes the process of identifying proteins and their roles in specific disease conditions through different experimental methods (Fig.1). A common pipeline is discovering and knocking out the gene coding for the protein of interest and studying the effects on a disease model. Recently, a number of different target types have emerged. Coding and regulatory nucleic acids, both DNA and RNA, different metabolites, and even whole cell types (in the context of cell therapy) all represent potential targets for a drug candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the arrival of methods like &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.asm.org/doi/full/10.1128/mmbr.67.4.657-685.2003&quot;&gt;RNA interference&lt;/a&gt; [4] (see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.martinholub.com/2024/10/16/RNAi.html&quot;&gt;my post on RNAi&lt;/a&gt;), or more recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/full/10.1098/rstb.2015.0496&quot;&gt;CRISPR-based tools&lt;/a&gt; [5], large-scale screens for experimental target identification have become common in well-resourced labs. Using these methods, a range of genes in disease-model cell lines can be knocked out. Subsequent phenotypic and/or genotypic assaying allows the identification of new possible drug target candidates (Fig.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/techbio_targetIdentification.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Fig.1: Overview of target identification approaches. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2023.06.010&quot;&gt;Adapted from Pun et al., 2023&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experimental approaches widen our horizons by characterizing proteins whose functions were not previously known. Most commonly, this knowledge ends up accessible on the internet — through publications — and can be leveraged. Considerable efforts have been made to develop and maintain massive databases containing information on genes, their corresponding proteins, and their function. All of this plays a crucial role in the usage of sequencing technologies, which involve using these databases at some point in their downstream analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last decade, with the increased abundance of genomic data, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have gained a lot of traction. Using GWAS, the genetic makeup of patients suffering from certain ailments can be compared to healthy individuals to identify targets specific to disease pathologies. Similarly, the availability of other omics datasets (transcriptomic, proteomic, epigenomic, metabolomic, etc.) (Fig.1) in the public domain has exponentially increased due to advancements in technologies and lower costs of the corresponding experiments. Consequently, while requiring bioinformatics expertise, leveraging publicly and commercially available multiomics datasets &lt;em&gt;in silico&lt;/em&gt; has become a go-to strategy for identifying promising targets before testing them in the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-ai-in-target-identification&quot;&gt;Understanding AI in Target Identification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the plethora of data and the rapid advances in computer hardware, today there is no domain of biomedical research where AI doesn’t contribute – from information retrieval to clinical diagnoses, and from data processing &amp;amp; integration to protein modeling (&lt;a href=&quot;https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/about&quot;&gt;AlphaFold&lt;/a&gt;). AI is an umbrella term that has been used to denote traditional mathematical models such as regression, to abstract phenomena like artificial general intelligence (AGI). The use cases of AI discussed in this article are in between these two extremes. In the following text, we briefly introduce AI as it is being used in target discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence, or AI, refers to a computer’s ability to perform tasks that are characteristic of intelligent beings. What these algorithms attempt to do is &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt; trends from swathes of data, and apply what they &lt;em&gt;learned&lt;/em&gt; to new, unseen data. For example, an accurate skin cancer detection model has to be fed thousands of images of skin cancer and benign tumors, so that it can &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt; to discriminate between the two. Similarly, large language models (LLMs) like &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.anthropic.com/claude&quot;&gt;Claude&lt;/a&gt; are trained on books, articles, and pretty much every text available on the internet in the public domain, which makes them robust in answering a broad range of questions. On the other hand, specialist models like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BioMedBERT/biomedbert&quot;&gt;BioMedBERT&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/about&quot;&gt;Perplexity AI&lt;/a&gt;, are geared towards scientific conversations and provide resources and citations.  All these models are examples of deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is a vast subfield of AI that makes use of neural networks. Neurons form the fundamental unit of these networks and are similar to biological neurons: receiving multiple signals from surrounding neurons, processing them in a certain way, and having a single output that is then sent to another neuron. Using multiple layers of such neurons leads to neural networks that come in all &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asimovinstitute.org/neural-network-zoo/&quot;&gt;shapes and sizes&lt;/a&gt; and varying complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deep learning models’ ability to learn &amp;amp; generalize makes them extremely versatile in biomedical research. Companies discussed below are using different variations of deep learning to integrate publicly available and self-generated multi-omics datasets along with other types of data like microscopy images, text from biomedical literature, and patient data to capture intricacies and trends that are difficult to detect manually. By training such models biomarkers, perturbation effects, and novel targets can be predicted &lt;em&gt;in silico&lt;/em&gt; and subsequently validated through experimentation. Hence, biomedical data in every available form is being leveraged with complex, computation-heavy, and often proprietary AI architectures for identifying new targets against diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;case-studies-and-real-world-examples&quot;&gt;Case Studies and Real-world Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment of writing, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2023.06.010&quot;&gt;over 20 assets&lt;/a&gt; in clinical trials where AI was leveraged for target identification, as well as along the downstream drug development process [6]. A number of them are already in phase II, and many more are in the Investigational New Drug (IND) enabling phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.recursion.com/&quot;&gt;Recursion Pharmaceuticals&lt;/a&gt; is a pioneer in data-driven, platform-first biotech (known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/cantos-ventures/what-is-techbio-ef01cd61834d&quot;&gt;TechBio&lt;/a&gt;). Since its founding in 2013, the company built up the capacity to run over 2 million experiments every week and collected over 22 PB (that’s 10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;) of data. Their pipeline generates lead candidates by applying reverse-genetic causal machine learning models on patient-specific sequencing data and integrating it with health records, databases on small molecule compounds, their target interaction predictions, and data from scientific publications. To facilitate this workflow, the company developed LOWE (Large Language Model-Orchestrated Workflow Engine) that allows users to interface with the pipeline with natural language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lead molecules are screened in imaging-based and sc-RNA sequencing workflows, generating genome-wide perturbation datasets that are fed into deep learning models.  Recursion differentiates itself from its competition by being an early and bullish adopter of image-based data collection (phenomics). While &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rxrx.ai/rxrx3#about&quot;&gt;a fraction of the generated dataset has been made public&lt;/a&gt; [7], much of it remains proprietary to Recursion. Their phenomics foundation model (trained on the publicly available data) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.recursion.com/news/nothing-short-of-phenomenal-new-deep-learning-model-available-on-nvidias-bionemo-platform&quot;&gt;Phenome-Beta&lt;/a&gt; was released on NVIDIA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/clara/bionemo/&quot;&gt;BioNeMo platform&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year. Recursion’s most advanced model, Phenome-1 remains proprietary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/techbio_recursionPhenomics.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Fig.2: Overview of ‘phenomics’ for high-throughput screening. Top panel: Cell images are collected at different perturbations (middle) and across multiple color channels (right). Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fintel.io/doc/sec-recursion-pharmaceuticals-inc-1601830-10k-2023-february-27-19415-6506&quot;&gt;Recursion’s 2023 annual report&lt;/a&gt;. Bottom panel: Multi-channel images are the training data for a deep learning model that learns their experimentally relevant features. The model can be used for future inference. Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rxrx.ai/rxrx3&quot;&gt;rxrx.ai&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recursion currently has &lt;a href=&quot;https://clinicaltrials.gov/search?spons=Recursion%20Pharmaceuticals%20Inc.&quot;&gt;five small molecule drugs in phase II trials&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.recursion.com/news-releases/news-release-details/recursion-initiates-two-additional-clinical-trials-total-four&quot;&gt;REC-4881&lt;/a&gt; is an orally bioavailable, non-ATP-competitive allosteric small molecule inhibitor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAP2K1&quot;&gt;MAP2K1&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAP2K2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; being developed to reduce polyp burden and cancer progression in people living with FAP (familial adenomatous polyposis). FAP is an inherited disease that leads to formation of polyps in the rectum and colon, eventually manifesting in colorectal cancer (CRC). &lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.recursion.com/news-releases/news-release-details/recursion-announces-completion-phase-1-study-rec-3964&quot;&gt;REC-3964&lt;/a&gt; is a non-antibiotic small molecule inhibitor of C.difficile toxins which is being developed for the potential treatment of gastrointestinal infection. It finished phase I in 2023, and started enrollment for phase II in October 2024. Most recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://ichgcp.net/clinical-trials-registry/NCT06678659&quot;&gt;REC-1245&lt;/a&gt; entered phase I/II clinical trials for advanced metastatic tumors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://insilico.com/&quot;&gt;InSilico Medicine&lt;/a&gt; is another early adopter of AI in small molecule drug discovery and design. The company leverages its end-to-end integrated Pharma.AI platform consisting of three components to drive its drug discovery and development: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01619&quot;&gt;PandaOmics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jcim.2c01191&quot;&gt;Chemistry42&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ascpt.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/cpt.3008&quot;&gt;inClinico&lt;/a&gt; [8-10]. PandaOmics is an AI target identification engine that combines a diverse range of omics data totalling over 10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt; data points across disease-specific and healthy tissue datasets. The platform further integrates text-based analysis on clinical trials, grants and publications, all together allowing for identification of novel targets that meet a large need. “Our target discovery philosophy is to find an optimal balance between commercial tractability, novelty, and confidence,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugdiscoverytrends.com/insilico-ai-cancer-treatment-ism9274/?utm_source=TrendMD&amp;amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Drug_Discovery_and_Development__TrendMD_0&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; Alex Zhavoronkov, founder and CEO of Insilico Medicine for Drug Discovery &amp;amp; Development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company currently has one asset in a phase II trial, &lt;a href=&quot;https://clinicaltrials.gov/search?spons=InSilico%20Medicine%20Hong%20Kong%20Limited&quot;&gt;four more in phase I&lt;/a&gt;, and one preclinical asset. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-024-02143-0&quot;&gt;INS018_055&lt;/a&gt; is an orally available small molecule TRAF2- and NCK-interacting kinase (TNIK) inhibitor with therapeutic potential in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis currently in phase II trials [11]. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230912041846/en/Exelixis-and-Insilico-Medicine-Enter-into-Exclusive-Global-License-Agreement-for-ISM3091-a-Potentially-Best-in-Class-USP1-Inhibitor&quot;&gt;ISM3091/XL309&lt;/a&gt; is a small molecule inhibitor of USP1, an enzyme implicated in DNA damage repair and relevant in the context of some forms of ovarian, prostate, and breast cancers, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugdiscoverytrends.com/insilico-medicines-latest-ai-engineered-drug-ism5411-could-provide-a-novel-approach-for-treating-ibd/&quot;&gt;ISM5411&lt;/a&gt; is an oral prolyl hydroxylase domain (PHD) inhibitor for the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), this investigational drug is supposed to regulate levels of hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha (HIF-1a), which should in turn control gut inflammation. Finally, the firm has a CDK12/13 inhibitor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugdiscoverytrends.com/insilico-ai-cancer-treatment-ism9274/?utm_source=TrendMD&amp;amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Drug_Discovery_and_Development__TrendMD_0&quot;&gt;ISM9274&lt;/a&gt;, in the preclinical pipeline that shows promise against multiple cancers, particularly triple-negative breast cancer and pancreatic cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While others focus purely on target-identification (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://biorelate.com/company&quot;&gt;Biorelate&lt;/a&gt;), most companies integrate AI-driven target identification into a full drug development pipeline (further examples include  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.valohealth.com/&quot;&gt;Valo Health&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://relaytx.com/&quot;&gt;Relay Therapeutics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exscientia.ai/pipeline&quot;&gt;Exscientia&lt;/a&gt; (recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://investors.exscientia.ai/press-releases/press-release-details/2024/Recursion-and-Exscientia-Enter-Definitive-Agreement-to-Create-a-Global-Technology-Enabled-Drug-Discovery-Leader-with-End-to-End-Capabilities/default.aspx&quot;&gt;acquired&lt;/a&gt; by Recursion), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nimbustx.com/&quot;&gt;Nimbus Therapeutics&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benevolent.com/pipeline/&quot;&gt;Benevolent A&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opentargets.org/&quot;&gt;Open Targets&lt;/a&gt; stands out as a notable example of open and collaborative science, bringing multiple industry stakeholders together to share disease and target annotation data in easily accessible format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-outlook-and-challenges&quot;&gt;Future Outlook and Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When applying AI to target discovery, a number of challenges emerge. First, any model is only as good as the data it has been trained on. Failing to collect data in areas of unmet needs or for underserved patient populations is at large risk of leading to biased models that exacerbate health inequality. Second, AI models have only limited transparency, and to an extent function as black boxes. Managing their regulatory compliance and data integrity requires teams to adapt to changing frameworks. Third, training AI models requires substantial computational resources. This presents challenges to equity of access, where well-resourced companies may benefit from preferential access to compute hardware. Finally, a culture of keeping these models, and the data they have been trained on, proprietary is likely to create silos of knowledge and hinder progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges, AI has clearly taken a firm hold across the drug development pipeline, including target identification. The increased volume and modality of datasets, together with more computational power and advances in AI architectures, are increasing the rate at which new candidates are discovered and enter clinical trials. In the future, there is a hope that AI will substantially increase the success rate of these trials as well as be helpful in aiding the development of drugs for previously intractable targets. Examples in this article have focused on protein targets and small-molecule drugs. It is likely that AI-driven models optimized for discovery of different targets than proteins will emerge in the near future. Similarly, other modalities than small molecules are poised to gain more prominence. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01524-x&quot;&gt;Peptide-based therapeutics&lt;/a&gt; [12], for example, have seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://drughunter.com/articles/mk-0616-the-2023-molecule-of-the-year/&quot;&gt;a number of successes&lt;/a&gt; in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of AI in drug discovery is bright. If you want to learn more about how AI is revolutionizing biotech and stay up to date, be sure to check &lt;a href=&quot;https://linktr.ee/aixbiotech_nucleate&quot;&gt;Nucleate’s AI in Biotech&lt;/a&gt; initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We would like to thank Alice Martin, Natalie Losada, Samantha Avina and Shawn Rumrill for feedback on the draft.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Hwang, T. J.; Trinh, Q.-D.; Tibau, A.; Vokinger, K. N. Reforms to Accelerated Approval of New Medicines: Long Overdue. &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2022&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;400&lt;/em&gt; (10349), 357–358. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01276-4&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01276-4&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Cox, E. M.; Edmund, A. V.; Kratz, E.; Lockwood, S. H.; Shankar, A. Regulatory Affairs 101: Introduction to Expedited Regulatory Pathways. &lt;em&gt;Clinical Translational Sci&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2020&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;13&lt;/em&gt; (3), 451–461. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/cts.12745&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/cts.12745&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Master Protocols: Efficient Clinical Trial Design Strategies to Expedite Development of Oncology Drugs and Biologics. &lt;em&gt;Clinical Trial Design&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/master-protocols-efficient-clinical-trial-design-strategies-expedite-development-oncology-drugs-and&quot;&gt;https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/master-protocols-efficient-clinical-trial-design-strategies-expedite-development-oncology-drugs-and&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Agrawal, N.; Dasaradhi, P. V. N.; Mohmmed, A.; Malhotra, P.; Bhatnagar, R. K.; Mukherjee, S. K. RNA Interference: Biology, Mechanism, and Applications. &lt;em&gt;Microbiol Mol Biol Rev&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2003&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;67&lt;/em&gt; (4), 657–685. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.67.4.657-685.2003&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.67.4.657-685.2003&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] Hille, F.; Charpentier, E. CRISPR-Cas: Biology, Mechanisms and Relevance. &lt;em&gt;Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2016&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;371&lt;/em&gt; (1707), 20150496. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0496&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0496&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] Pun, F. W.; Ozerov, I. V.; Zhavoronkov, A. AI-Powered Therapeutic Target Discovery. &lt;em&gt;Trends in Pharmacological Sciences&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2023&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;44&lt;/em&gt; (9), 561–572. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2023.06.010&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2023.06.010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] Fay, M. M.; Kraus, O.; Victors, M.; Arumugam, L.; Vuggumudi, K.; Urbanik, J.; Hansen, K.; Celik, S.; Cernek, N.; Jagannathan, G.; Christensen, J.; Earnshaw, B. A.; Haque, I. S.; Mabey, B. RxRx3: Phenomics Map of Biology. February 8, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.02.07.527350&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.02.07.527350&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8] Kamya, P.; Ozerov, I. V.; Pun, F. W.; Tretina, K.; Fokina, T.; Chen, S.; Naumov, V.; Long, X.; Lin, S.; Korzinkin, M.; Polykovskiy, D.; Aliper, A.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. PandaOmics: An AI-Driven Platform for Therapeutic Target and Biomarker Discovery. &lt;em&gt;J. Chem. Inf. Model.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;64&lt;/em&gt; (10), 3961–3969. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01619&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01619&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9] Ivanenkov, Y. A.; Polykovskiy, D.; Bezrukov, D.; Zagribelnyy, B.; Aladinskiy, V.; Kamya, P.; Aliper, A.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. Chemistry42: An AI-Driven Platform for Molecular Design and Optimization. &lt;em&gt;J. Chem. Inf. Model.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2023&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;63&lt;/em&gt; (3), 695–701. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.2c01191&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.2c01191&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10] Aliper, A.; Kudrin, R.; Polykovskiy, D.; Kamya, P.; Tutubalina, E.; Chen, S.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. Prediction of Clinical Trials Outcomes Based on Target Choice and Clinical Trial Design with Multi‐Modal Artificial Intelligence. &lt;em&gt;Clin Pharma and Therapeutics&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2023&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;114&lt;/em&gt; (5), 972–980. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/cpt.3008&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/cpt.3008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11] Ren, F.; Aliper, A.; Chen, J.; Zhao, H.; Rao, S.; Kuppe, C.; Ozerov, I. V.; Zhang, M.; Witte, K.; Kruse, C.; Aladinskiy, V.; Ivanenkov, Y.; Polykovskiy, D.; Fu, Y.; Babin, E.; Qiao, J.; Liang, X.; Mou, Z.; Wang, H.; Pun, F. W.; Ayuso, P. T.; Veviorskiy, A.; Song, D.; Liu, S.; Zhang, B.; Naumov, V.; Ding, X.; Kukharenko, A.; Izumchenko, E.; Zhavoronkov, A. A Small-Molecule TNIK Inhibitor Targets Fibrosis in Preclinical and Clinical Models. &lt;em&gt;Nat Biotechnol&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-024-02143-0&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-024-02143-0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12] Pal, S.; ‘T Hart, P. Imbuing Peptide Libraries with Drug-Likeness. &lt;em&gt;Nat Chem Biol&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41589-023-01524-x&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41589-023-01524-x&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="biotech" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">This article was co-authored by Kevin Merchant and Martin Holub. Introduction Development of novel drugs has been a critical contributor to extending healthspan and fighting diseases, but the process is complex. The involvement of multiple stakeholders and strict regulatory processes are responsible for some of it, but that contribution is dwarfed by our limited understanding of underlying biological processes. Over the past decade, artificial intelligence (AI) has progressed rapidly showing reasoning ability over large multidimensional datasets. AI, indeed, is transforming the drug discovery process as well. In this article, we highlight the role of AI in a critical task in the early drug discovery process: target identification. We first introduce the technical background. Next, we review the state-of-the-art using industry examples. Finally, we highlight challenges and directions for future development. Questions we address are: How is AI currently used in target identification? And: What future developments of AI would position it to make the largest positive impact on this task? Understanding Target Identification Drug development is a long and complex process, with average estimates of around 12 years from conceptualization to approval — although post-COVID-19, efforts have been made by approval bodies to shorten it [1]. This is happening through a number of approaches, including accelerated approval pathways [2], leveraging real world data and evidence as well as changes to clinical trial design [3]. Lead discovery is the first step, including target identification &amp;amp; screening for compounds or biologics against the target, followed by optimization of lead compound and preclinical testing. If the lead compound manages to get through these hoops, it can finally go into clinical trials, where success can pave the way for approval and the title “drug”. Target identification is an inherent part of academic and industry research. Traditionally, it describes the process of identifying proteins and their roles in specific disease conditions through different experimental methods (Fig.1). A common pipeline is discovering and knocking out the gene coding for the protein of interest and studying the effects on a disease model. Recently, a number of different target types have emerged. Coding and regulatory nucleic acids, both DNA and RNA, different metabolites, and even whole cell types (in the context of cell therapy) all represent potential targets for a drug candidate. With the arrival of methods like RNA interference [4] (see also my post on RNAi), or more recently CRISPR-based tools [5], large-scale screens for experimental target identification have become common in well-resourced labs. Using these methods, a range of genes in disease-model cell lines can be knocked out. Subsequent phenotypic and/or genotypic assaying allows the identification of new possible drug target candidates (Fig.1). Fig.1: Overview of target identification approaches. Adapted from Pun et al., 2023. These experimental approaches widen our horizons by characterizing proteins whose functions were not previously known. Most commonly, this knowledge ends up accessible on the internet — through publications — and can be leveraged. Considerable efforts have been made to develop and maintain massive databases containing information on genes, their corresponding proteins, and their function. All of this plays a crucial role in the usage of sequencing technologies, which involve using these databases at some point in their downstream analysis. In the last decade, with the increased abundance of genomic data, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have gained a lot of traction. Using GWAS, the genetic makeup of patients suffering from certain ailments can be compared to healthy individuals to identify targets specific to disease pathologies. Similarly, the availability of other omics datasets (transcriptomic, proteomic, epigenomic, metabolomic, etc.) (Fig.1) in the public domain has exponentially increased due to advancements in technologies and lower costs of the corresponding experiments. Consequently, while requiring bioinformatics expertise, leveraging publicly and commercially available multiomics datasets in silico has become a go-to strategy for identifying promising targets before testing them in the lab. Understanding AI in Target Identification With the plethora of data and the rapid advances in computer hardware, today there is no domain of biomedical research where AI doesn’t contribute – from information retrieval to clinical diagnoses, and from data processing &amp;amp; integration to protein modeling (AlphaFold). AI is an umbrella term that has been used to denote traditional mathematical models such as regression, to abstract phenomena like artificial general intelligence (AGI). The use cases of AI discussed in this article are in between these two extremes. In the following text, we briefly introduce AI as it is being used in target discovery. Artificial intelligence, or AI, refers to a computer’s ability to perform tasks that are characteristic of intelligent beings. What these algorithms attempt to do is learn trends from swathes of data, and apply what they learned to new, unseen data. For example, an accurate skin cancer detection model has to be fed thousands of images of skin cancer and benign tumors, so that it can learn to discriminate between the two. Similarly, large language models (LLMs) like ChatGPT or Claude are trained on books, articles, and pretty much every text available on the internet in the public domain, which makes them robust in answering a broad range of questions. On the other hand, specialist models like BioMedBERT or Perplexity AI, are geared towards scientific conversations and provide resources and citations. All these models are examples of deep learning. Deep learning is a vast subfield of AI that makes use of neural networks. Neurons form the fundamental unit of these networks and are similar to biological neurons: receiving multiple signals from surrounding neurons, processing them in a certain way, and having a single output that is then sent to another neuron. Using multiple layers of such neurons leads to neural networks that come in all shapes and sizes and varying complexities. The deep learning models’ ability to learn &amp;amp; generalize makes them extremely versatile in biomedical research. Companies discussed below are using different variations of deep learning to integrate publicly available and self-generated multi-omics datasets along with other types of data like microscopy images, text from biomedical literature, and patient data to capture intricacies and trends that are difficult to detect manually. By training such models biomarkers, perturbation effects, and novel targets can be predicted in silico and subsequently validated through experimentation. Hence, biomedical data in every available form is being leveraged with complex, computation-heavy, and often proprietary AI architectures for identifying new targets against diseases. Case Studies and Real-world Examples At the moment of writing, there are over 20 assets in clinical trials where AI was leveraged for target identification, as well as along the downstream drug development process [6]. A number of them are already in phase II, and many more are in the Investigational New Drug (IND) enabling phase. Recursion Pharmaceuticals is a pioneer in data-driven, platform-first biotech (known as TechBio). Since its founding in 2013, the company built up the capacity to run over 2 million experiments every week and collected over 22 PB (that’s 1015) of data. Their pipeline generates lead candidates by applying reverse-genetic causal machine learning models on patient-specific sequencing data and integrating it with health records, databases on small molecule compounds, their target interaction predictions, and data from scientific publications. To facilitate this workflow, the company developed LOWE (Large Language Model-Orchestrated Workflow Engine) that allows users to interface with the pipeline with natural language. The lead molecules are screened in imaging-based and sc-RNA sequencing workflows, generating genome-wide perturbation datasets that are fed into deep learning models. Recursion differentiates itself from its competition by being an early and bullish adopter of image-based data collection (phenomics). While a fraction of the generated dataset has been made public [7], much of it remains proprietary to Recursion. Their phenomics foundation model (trained on the publicly available data) Phenome-Beta was released on NVIDIA’s BioNeMo platform earlier this year. Recursion’s most advanced model, Phenome-1 remains proprietary. Fig.2: Overview of ‘phenomics’ for high-throughput screening. Top panel: Cell images are collected at different perturbations (middle) and across multiple color channels (right). Adapted from Recursion’s 2023 annual report. Bottom panel: Multi-channel images are the training data for a deep learning model that learns their experimentally relevant features. The model can be used for future inference. Adapted from rxrx.ai. Recursion currently has five small molecule drugs in phase II trials. REC-4881 is an orally bioavailable, non-ATP-competitive allosteric small molecule inhibitor of MAP2K1/2 being developed to reduce polyp burden and cancer progression in people living with FAP (familial adenomatous polyposis). FAP is an inherited disease that leads to formation of polyps in the rectum and colon, eventually manifesting in colorectal cancer (CRC). REC-3964 is a non-antibiotic small molecule inhibitor of C.difficile toxins which is being developed for the potential treatment of gastrointestinal infection. It finished phase I in 2023, and started enrollment for phase II in October 2024. Most recently REC-1245 entered phase I/II clinical trials for advanced metastatic tumors InSilico Medicine is another early adopter of AI in small molecule drug discovery and design. The company leverages its end-to-end integrated Pharma.AI platform consisting of three components to drive its drug discovery and development: PandaOmics, Chemistry42 and inClinico [8-10]. PandaOmics is an AI target identification engine that combines a diverse range of omics data totalling over 1012 data points across disease-specific and healthy tissue datasets. The platform further integrates text-based analysis on clinical trials, grants and publications, all together allowing for identification of novel targets that meet a large need. “Our target discovery philosophy is to find an optimal balance between commercial tractability, novelty, and confidence,” said Alex Zhavoronkov, founder and CEO of Insilico Medicine for Drug Discovery &amp;amp; Development. The company currently has one asset in a phase II trial, four more in phase I, and one preclinical asset. INS018_055 is an orally available small molecule TRAF2- and NCK-interacting kinase (TNIK) inhibitor with therapeutic potential in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis currently in phase II trials [11]. ISM3091/XL309 is a small molecule inhibitor of USP1, an enzyme implicated in DNA damage repair and relevant in the context of some forms of ovarian, prostate, and breast cancers, ISM5411 is an oral prolyl hydroxylase domain (PHD) inhibitor for the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), this investigational drug is supposed to regulate levels of hypoxia-inducible factor 1alpha (HIF-1a), which should in turn control gut inflammation. Finally, the firm has a CDK12/13 inhibitor, ISM9274, in the preclinical pipeline that shows promise against multiple cancers, particularly triple-negative breast cancer and pancreatic cancer. While others focus purely on target-identification (e.g. Biorelate), most companies integrate AI-driven target identification into a full drug development pipeline (further examples include Valo Health, Relay Therapeutics, Exscientia (recently acquired by Recursion), Nimbus Therapeutics, and Benevolent A. Finally, Open Targets stands out as a notable example of open and collaborative science, bringing multiple industry stakeholders together to share disease and target annotation data in easily accessible format. Future Outlook and Challenges When applying AI to target discovery, a number of challenges emerge. First, any model is only as good as the data it has been trained on. Failing to collect data in areas of unmet needs or for underserved patient populations is at large risk of leading to biased models that exacerbate health inequality. Second, AI models have only limited transparency, and to an extent function as black boxes. Managing their regulatory compliance and data integrity requires teams to adapt to changing frameworks. Third, training AI models requires substantial computational resources. This presents challenges to equity of access, where well-resourced companies may benefit from preferential access to compute hardware. Finally, a culture of keeping these models, and the data they have been trained on, proprietary is likely to create silos of knowledge and hinder progress. Despite these challenges, AI has clearly taken a firm hold across the drug development pipeline, including target identification. The increased volume and modality of datasets, together with more computational power and advances in AI architectures, are increasing the rate at which new candidates are discovered and enter clinical trials. In the future, there is a hope that AI will substantially increase the success rate of these trials as well as be helpful in aiding the development of drugs for previously intractable targets. Examples in this article have focused on protein targets and small-molecule drugs. It is likely that AI-driven models optimized for discovery of different targets than proteins will emerge in the near future. Similarly, other modalities than small molecules are poised to gain more prominence. Peptide-based therapeutics [12], for example, have seen a number of successes in the last year. The future of AI in drug discovery is bright. If you want to learn more about how AI is revolutionizing biotech and stay up to date, be sure to check Nucleate’s AI in Biotech initiative. We would like to thank Alice Martin, Natalie Losada, Samantha Avina and Shawn Rumrill for feedback on the draft. References [1] Hwang, T. J.; Trinh, Q.-D.; Tibau, A.; Vokinger, K. N. Reforms to Accelerated Approval of New Medicines: Long Overdue. The Lancet 2022, 400 (10349), 357–358. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01276-4. [2] Cox, E. M.; Edmund, A. V.; Kratz, E.; Lockwood, S. H.; Shankar, A. Regulatory Affairs 101: Introduction to Expedited Regulatory Pathways. Clinical Translational Sci 2020, 13 (3), 451–461. https://doi.org/10.1111/cts.12745. [3] Master Protocols: Efficient Clinical Trial Design Strategies to Expedite Development of Oncology Drugs and Biologics. Clinical Trial Design. https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/master-protocols-efficient-clinical-trial-design-strategies-expedite-development-oncology-drugs-and [4] Agrawal, N.; Dasaradhi, P. V. N.; Mohmmed, A.; Malhotra, P.; Bhatnagar, R. K.; Mukherjee, S. K. RNA Interference: Biology, Mechanism, and Applications. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 2003, 67 (4), 657–685. https://doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.67.4.657-685.2003. [5] Hille, F.; Charpentier, E. CRISPR-Cas: Biology, Mechanisms and Relevance. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B 2016, 371 (1707), 20150496. https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0496. [6] Pun, F. W.; Ozerov, I. V.; Zhavoronkov, A. AI-Powered Therapeutic Target Discovery. Trends in Pharmacological Sciences 2023, 44 (9), 561–572. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2023.06.010. [7] Fay, M. M.; Kraus, O.; Victors, M.; Arumugam, L.; Vuggumudi, K.; Urbanik, J.; Hansen, K.; Celik, S.; Cernek, N.; Jagannathan, G.; Christensen, J.; Earnshaw, B. A.; Haque, I. S.; Mabey, B. RxRx3: Phenomics Map of Biology. February 8, 2023. https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.02.07.527350. [8] Kamya, P.; Ozerov, I. V.; Pun, F. W.; Tretina, K.; Fokina, T.; Chen, S.; Naumov, V.; Long, X.; Lin, S.; Korzinkin, M.; Polykovskiy, D.; Aliper, A.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. PandaOmics: An AI-Driven Platform for Therapeutic Target and Biomarker Discovery. J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2024, 64 (10), 3961–3969. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01619. [9] Ivanenkov, Y. A.; Polykovskiy, D.; Bezrukov, D.; Zagribelnyy, B.; Aladinskiy, V.; Kamya, P.; Aliper, A.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. Chemistry42: An AI-Driven Platform for Molecular Design and Optimization. J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2023, 63 (3), 695–701. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.2c01191. [10] Aliper, A.; Kudrin, R.; Polykovskiy, D.; Kamya, P.; Tutubalina, E.; Chen, S.; Ren, F.; Zhavoronkov, A. Prediction of Clinical Trials Outcomes Based on Target Choice and Clinical Trial Design with Multi‐Modal Artificial Intelligence. Clin Pharma and Therapeutics 2023, 114 (5), 972–980. https://doi.org/10.1002/cpt.3008. [11] Ren, F.; Aliper, A.; Chen, J.; Zhao, H.; Rao, S.; Kuppe, C.; Ozerov, I. V.; Zhang, M.; Witte, K.; Kruse, C.; Aladinskiy, V.; Ivanenkov, Y.; Polykovskiy, D.; Fu, Y.; Babin, E.; Qiao, J.; Liang, X.; Mou, Z.; Wang, H.; Pun, F. W.; Ayuso, P. T.; Veviorskiy, A.; Song, D.; Liu, S.; Zhang, B.; Naumov, V.; Ding, X.; Kukharenko, A.; Izumchenko, E.; Zhavoronkov, A. A Small-Molecule TNIK Inhibitor Targets Fibrosis in Preclinical and Clinical Models. Nat Biotechnol 2024. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587-024-02143-0. [12] Pal, S.; ‘T Hart, P. Imbuing Peptide Libraries with Drug-Likeness. Nat Chem Biol 2024. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41589-023-01524-x.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RNA Interference - Field Recap</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/10/16/RNAi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RNA Interference - Field Recap" /><published>2024-10-16T19:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-16T19:22:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2024/10/16/RNAi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/10/16/RNAi.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This field recap was writen at end of Q22024. Events that took place after this date are not reflected.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I provide a brief field recap on RNA interference as therapeutic modality. First, I provide background on its biological mechanisms. Next, I follow up with an overview of the siRNA therapeutics field, highlighting approved drugs, as well major ongoing trials. I conclude with a short recap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanism-of-rna-interference&quot;&gt;Mechanism of RNA Interference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RNA interference (RNAi) is a process by which RNA molecules suppress gene expression in sequence specific fashion. The process was initially described in late 80’s and early 90’s, [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(84)90050-3&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.113.2.503&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], and elucidated at the turn of the century with work that yielded the 2006 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/35888&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. RNAi is a natural process of gene regulation that has physiological role in wide range of organisms, including mammals and plants. Despite some important differences, the process is mostly conserved among species. In the following, we describe it in broad strokes, focusing on its mechanism in eukaryotic and human cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In RNAi, double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) enters cells where it is recognized by the Dicer enzyme. Dicer contains two RNAse III domains. When recruited to dsRNA, two Dicer enzymes work in tandem to cleave the molecule at a regular interval of ~22 nucleotides. The cleavage generates 2 nucleotide overhangs at the 3’ end. The 5’ end, left unprotected, is rapidly phosphorylated. The resulting RNA molecule is the &lt;strong&gt;small interfering RNA (siRNA)&lt;/strong&gt;, which sets off silencing. Notably, exogenously administered siRNAs are also capable of triggering silencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The siRNA molecule prompts the assembly of an effector nuclease complex &lt;strong&gt;RISC (RNA-induced silencing complex)&lt;/strong&gt;, whereby the RISC complex binds the siRNA and unwinds it. The sense strand, also called passenger strand, is digested by Ago2, a member of the complex and of the Argonaut protein family. The antisense strand, also called guide strand, guides RISC complex towards a complementary mRNA sequence. Upon recognition, the mRNA sequence is cleaved and digested, effectively leading to silencing of corresponding gene. Once the RISC complex is activated, it is capable of targeting numerous mRNA transcript copies, producing an effect that is sustained over several weeks in non-dividing cells [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nrd2742&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description we gave given so far is accurate, but omits some details that are relevant to applications. &lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, the mRNA cleavage and digestion is only one mechanism by which siRNA produces silencing. Chromatin modification and remodeling, as well translational inhibition, have been shown to play a role, albeit to smaller extent. &lt;strong&gt;Second&lt;/strong&gt;, siRNA is capable of silencing sequences other than its perfect complements. This can happen in two ways: a) by extension of the silencing signal in the 3’ -&amp;gt; 5’ direction, effectively leading to silencing of sequences left to the target, and b) by RISC’s tolerance to mismatches, particularly at the ends of the guide sequence [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2022.02.004&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. &lt;strong&gt;Third&lt;/strong&gt;, mammalian somatic cells exhibit nonspecific response to delivery of dsRNA, and so does the innate immune system react to it by raising interferon levels. This precludes dsRNA use from silencing applications [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncb0200_70&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Fortunately, the direct delivery of siRNAs is generally well tolerated. &lt;strong&gt;Fourth&lt;/strong&gt;, studies in simpler organisms demonstrated the spreading of silencing signal into cell types beyond the target [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1068836&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. The extent to which this plays a role in human cells is not fully understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspects-of-therapeutic-sirna-design&quot;&gt;Aspects of Therapeutic siRNA Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only ~22 nucleotides (practically between 19 and 25), siRNA is a relatively simple molecule. The intense work over the past two decades demonstrated that this is by no way a limitation to sophistication of designs and modifications that it can lend itself to. In the following we describe several of the most widely adopted design features, including &lt;strong&gt;formulation&lt;/strong&gt;, chemical &lt;strong&gt;modification&lt;/strong&gt; of individual bases, and &lt;strong&gt;conjugation&lt;/strong&gt; to additional moieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest examples of siRNA’s were minimally modified, and their formulation was as much as subcutaneous injection of a solution in physiological buffer. Motivated by the need to prevent siRNAs from degradation, and to target their delivery to specific tissues, in the 2000’s the field explored different formulation methods. These included polymer nanoparticles and liposomes (or lipid nanoparticles, LNPs) [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nmat3765&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. The latter, LNPs, become part of the first siRNA therapy, approved by both the FDA and the EMA in 2018 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41565-019-0591-y&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the right formulation for LNPs was, however, a substantial undertaking [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41565-019-0591-y&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Consequently, the field shifted away from encapsulation formulations. Instead, the focus turned to chemically modifying siRNAs, and conjugating them to moieties that garner tissue specificity. Variants of this approach are dominant among all the approved therapies, as well as siRNA drug candidates currently in clinical trials. We illustrate this at detail on the example of givosiran [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1807838&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- All modifications featured on this molecule are also present on both clinical assets of Silence Therapeutics \[[ref](https://patents.google.com/patent/US20190119676A1)\]. 
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Givosiran is a siRNA therapeutic agent for reducing levels of expression of delta aminolevulinic acid synthase 1 (ALAS1). Givosiran is approved in patients with acute intermittent porphyria, with authorizations issued at the end of 2019 by the FDA, and two months later by the EMA. It is marketed under the brand name Givlaari by Alnylam Pharmaceuticals. Givosiran is a fully chemically modified siRNA (Fig.1). Apart from featuring the canonical two nucleotide 3’ overhang and 5’ phosphate, it includes a number of modifications. All RNA bases are modified at the 2’ position of a ribose: either with &lt;strong&gt;2’-Fluoro (2’-F)&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;2’-O-Methyl (2’-OMe)&lt;/strong&gt;. Both modifications improve target binding affinity [&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3765&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. The 2’-OMe modification has been further shown to foster nuclease resistance, and reduce immune stimulation [&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3765&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. 5’ end is modified with &lt;strong&gt;E-vinyl phosphonate (5’-E-VP)&lt;/strong&gt;. 5’-E-VP is a phosphatase resistant 5’-phosphate analog, improving tissue accumulation by increasing chemical stability [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkx507&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Number of phosphodiester bonds at the end of each strand have been replaced by phosphorothioate, increasing the molecule’s stability, as well as facilitating its trafficking and uptake [&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3765&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Finally the 3’ end of the sense strand is conjugated to a trivalent GalNAc (Fig. 2). &lt;strong&gt;GalNAc, N-Acetyl galactosamine&lt;/strong&gt;, is an amino-derivative of galactose and the ligand for asialoglycoprotein receptor (ASGPR), and abundant transmembrane protein in hepatocytes. The moiety is responsible for guiding the siRNA molecule to these cells, which are targets of the therapeutic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rnai_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Figure 1: Schematic depiction of the molecular composition of Givosiran. AS – antisense, S – sense strands. See text for detailed description.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rnai_fig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Figure 2: The molecular structure of the (GalNAc)3 conjugate shown in Fig. 1.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the position and type of the modifications have effect on number of therapeutically relevant parameters including toxicity, target binding and tissue accumulation. Despite large body of research available to date, and because number of modifications other than described are possible [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41392-020-0207-x&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], the discovery of siRNA molecules for therapeutic applications continues to be heavily empirical. The best performing molecules must be found by extensive candidate screening. Due to difficulty of translating in-vitro to in-vivo results, this happens largely in animal models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, so far we have discussed only one type of targeting moiety, GalNAc. Clearly, the utility of siRNA therapeutics is not limited to hepatocytes. However, targeting other cell types requires careful choice and optimization of the 3’ sense-strand conjugate, as well as its linker. Number of extrahepatic targeting ligands have been demonstrated so far. These include lipids [&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/nar/article/47/3/1082/5245439&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], peptides [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.0c12043&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], centyrins [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.02.015&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], antibodies [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgkaa286&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], aptamers [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2017.12.015&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;], as well as branched siRNA arrangements [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-019-0205-0&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Finally, recent advances in mRNA-based therapeutics, commonly encapsulated as LNPs, have spurred new wave of interest in liposomes, particularly in advanced formulations with newly synthesized lipids [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41563-024-01867-3&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview-of-sirna-therapeutic-applications&quot;&gt;Overview of siRNA Therapeutic Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;siRNA has become a popular therapeutic modality, and is pursued for number of targets across tens of indications by sizeable number of companies. As of Q12024, there were 6 FDA approved siRNA drugs (Table 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rnai_table1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Table 1: FDA approved siRNA therapeutics [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-023-02105-y/tables/1&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. (h)ATTR– (hereditary) transthyretin-mediated amyloidosis. ‡ in phase III for a) major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), and b) ASCVD and elevated LDL-C. 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, several investigational molecules were in stage phase III trials (Table 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rnai_table2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Table 2: siRNA investigational drugs in stage phase III trials. NAION - nonarteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy. gMG - generalized myasthenia gravis, PNH - paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria, sHTG- severe hypertriglyceridemia, (AS)CVD – (atherosclerotic) cardiovascular disease, AATD - alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency, ‡ - company deck [&lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.arrowheadpharma.com/static-files/5aeef413-bfc6-4ef0-9a33-bdb8ad939483&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;].
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is number of candidates in phase II trials (Table 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/rnai_table3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Header&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;Table 3: Examples of siRNA investigational drugs in phase II trials [&lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.bioconjchem.3c00205&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-022-01334-x&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. Con. – conjugate, CAA - cerebral amyloid angiopathy.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an exciting time for both developers of RNAi therapeutics as well as patients that stand to benefit from them, with number of recently approved drugs and several potential blockbusters queuing up in the pipeline. However, two aspects darken this otherwise rosy picture. &lt;strong&gt;I)&lt;/strong&gt; Cardiovascular disease is by far the largest pursued indication, but, at the moment of writing, there are at least five late stage clinical assets going after it! This is great news for patients, but bad news for developers, who will see the blockbuster potential of their drugs dwindle. &lt;strong&gt;II)&lt;/strong&gt; There is a very apparent lack of diversity of targeting strategies, with majority of the (investigational) drugs leveraging GalNAc conjugation for delivery to hepatocytes. Some target eye or skin. Only three clinical trials for lungs and kidneys have reached phase II, as did one trial for the brain [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s12276-023-00998-y&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. The sustained success of RNAi therapeutics will be conditioned on RNAi companies’ ability to devise strategies for extrahepatic delivery, with muscle and brain representing particularly attractive, but also elusive, targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading everyone! Did you enjou this recap? And what area would you like to see covered next? Let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="biotech" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">This field recap was writen at end of Q22024. Events that took place after this date are not reflected. In this post, I provide a brief field recap on RNA interference as therapeutic modality. First, I provide background on its biological mechanisms. Next, I follow up with an overview of the siRNA therapeutics field, highlighting approved drugs, as well major ongoing trials. I conclude with a short recap. Mechanism of RNA Interference RNA interference (RNAi) is a process by which RNA molecules suppress gene expression in sequence specific fashion. The process was initially described in late 80’s and early 90’s, [ref, ref], and elucidated at the turn of the century with work that yielded the 2006 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine [ref]. RNAi is a natural process of gene regulation that has physiological role in wide range of organisms, including mammals and plants. Despite some important differences, the process is mostly conserved among species. In the following, we describe it in broad strokes, focusing on its mechanism in eukaryotic and human cells. In RNAi, double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) enters cells where it is recognized by the Dicer enzyme. Dicer contains two RNAse III domains. When recruited to dsRNA, two Dicer enzymes work in tandem to cleave the molecule at a regular interval of ~22 nucleotides. The cleavage generates 2 nucleotide overhangs at the 3’ end. The 5’ end, left unprotected, is rapidly phosphorylated. The resulting RNA molecule is the small interfering RNA (siRNA), which sets off silencing. Notably, exogenously administered siRNAs are also capable of triggering silencing. The siRNA molecule prompts the assembly of an effector nuclease complex RISC (RNA-induced silencing complex), whereby the RISC complex binds the siRNA and unwinds it. The sense strand, also called passenger strand, is digested by Ago2, a member of the complex and of the Argonaut protein family. The antisense strand, also called guide strand, guides RISC complex towards a complementary mRNA sequence. Upon recognition, the mRNA sequence is cleaved and digested, effectively leading to silencing of corresponding gene. Once the RISC complex is activated, it is capable of targeting numerous mRNA transcript copies, producing an effect that is sustained over several weeks in non-dividing cells [ref]. The description we gave given so far is accurate, but omits some details that are relevant to applications. First, the mRNA cleavage and digestion is only one mechanism by which siRNA produces silencing. Chromatin modification and remodeling, as well translational inhibition, have been shown to play a role, albeit to smaller extent. Second, siRNA is capable of silencing sequences other than its perfect complements. This can happen in two ways: a) by extension of the silencing signal in the 3’ -&amp;gt; 5’ direction, effectively leading to silencing of sequences left to the target, and b) by RISC’s tolerance to mismatches, particularly at the ends of the guide sequence [ref]. Third, mammalian somatic cells exhibit nonspecific response to delivery of dsRNA, and so does the innate immune system react to it by raising interferon levels. This precludes dsRNA use from silencing applications [ref]. Fortunately, the direct delivery of siRNAs is generally well tolerated. Fourth, studies in simpler organisms demonstrated the spreading of silencing signal into cell types beyond the target [ref]. The extent to which this plays a role in human cells is not fully understood. Aspects of Therapeutic siRNA Design With only ~22 nucleotides (practically between 19 and 25), siRNA is a relatively simple molecule. The intense work over the past two decades demonstrated that this is by no way a limitation to sophistication of designs and modifications that it can lend itself to. In the following we describe several of the most widely adopted design features, including formulation, chemical modification of individual bases, and conjugation to additional moieties. The earliest examples of siRNA’s were minimally modified, and their formulation was as much as subcutaneous injection of a solution in physiological buffer. Motivated by the need to prevent siRNAs from degradation, and to target their delivery to specific tissues, in the 2000’s the field explored different formulation methods. These included polymer nanoparticles and liposomes (or lipid nanoparticles, LNPs) [ref]. The latter, LNPs, become part of the first siRNA therapy, approved by both the FDA and the EMA in 2018 [ref]. Finding the right formulation for LNPs was, however, a substantial undertaking [ref]. Consequently, the field shifted away from encapsulation formulations. Instead, the focus turned to chemically modifying siRNAs, and conjugating them to moieties that garner tissue specificity. Variants of this approach are dominant among all the approved therapies, as well as siRNA drug candidates currently in clinical trials. We illustrate this at detail on the example of givosiran [ref]. Givosiran is a siRNA therapeutic agent for reducing levels of expression of delta aminolevulinic acid synthase 1 (ALAS1). Givosiran is approved in patients with acute intermittent porphyria, with authorizations issued at the end of 2019 by the FDA, and two months later by the EMA. It is marketed under the brand name Givlaari by Alnylam Pharmaceuticals. Givosiran is a fully chemically modified siRNA (Fig.1). Apart from featuring the canonical two nucleotide 3’ overhang and 5’ phosphate, it includes a number of modifications. All RNA bases are modified at the 2’ position of a ribose: either with 2’-Fluoro (2’-F), or 2’-O-Methyl (2’-OMe). Both modifications improve target binding affinity [ref]. The 2’-OMe modification has been further shown to foster nuclease resistance, and reduce immune stimulation [ref]. 5’ end is modified with E-vinyl phosphonate (5’-E-VP). 5’-E-VP is a phosphatase resistant 5’-phosphate analog, improving tissue accumulation by increasing chemical stability [ref]. Number of phosphodiester bonds at the end of each strand have been replaced by phosphorothioate, increasing the molecule’s stability, as well as facilitating its trafficking and uptake [ref]. Finally the 3’ end of the sense strand is conjugated to a trivalent GalNAc (Fig. 2). GalNAc, N-Acetyl galactosamine, is an amino-derivative of galactose and the ligand for asialoglycoprotein receptor (ASGPR), and abundant transmembrane protein in hepatocytes. The moiety is responsible for guiding the siRNA molecule to these cells, which are targets of the therapeutic. Figure 1: Schematic depiction of the molecular composition of Givosiran. AS – antisense, S – sense strands. See text for detailed description. Figure 2: The molecular structure of the (GalNAc)3 conjugate shown in Fig. 1. Both the position and type of the modifications have effect on number of therapeutically relevant parameters including toxicity, target binding and tissue accumulation. Despite large body of research available to date, and because number of modifications other than described are possible [ref], the discovery of siRNA molecules for therapeutic applications continues to be heavily empirical. The best performing molecules must be found by extensive candidate screening. Due to difficulty of translating in-vitro to in-vivo results, this happens largely in animal models. Similarly, so far we have discussed only one type of targeting moiety, GalNAc. Clearly, the utility of siRNA therapeutics is not limited to hepatocytes. However, targeting other cell types requires careful choice and optimization of the 3’ sense-strand conjugate, as well as its linker. Number of extrahepatic targeting ligands have been demonstrated so far. These include lipids [ref], peptides [ref], centyrins [ref], antibodies [ref], aptamers [ref], as well as branched siRNA arrangements [ref]. Finally, recent advances in mRNA-based therapeutics, commonly encapsulated as LNPs, have spurred new wave of interest in liposomes, particularly in advanced formulations with newly synthesized lipids [ref]. Overview of siRNA Therapeutic Applications siRNA has become a popular therapeutic modality, and is pursued for number of targets across tens of indications by sizeable number of companies. As of Q12024, there were 6 FDA approved siRNA drugs (Table 1). Table 1: FDA approved siRNA therapeutics [ref]. (h)ATTR– (hereditary) transthyretin-mediated amyloidosis. ‡ in phase III for a) major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), and b) ASCVD and elevated LDL-C. Additionally, several investigational molecules were in stage phase III trials (Table 2). Table 2: siRNA investigational drugs in stage phase III trials. NAION - nonarteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy. gMG - generalized myasthenia gravis, PNH - paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria, sHTG- severe hypertriglyceridemia, (AS)CVD – (atherosclerotic) cardiovascular disease, AATD - alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency, ‡ - company deck [ref]. Finally, there is number of candidates in phase II trials (Table 3). Table 3: Examples of siRNA investigational drugs in phase II trials [ref, ref]. Con. – conjugate, CAA - cerebral amyloid angiopathy. Conclusions It is an exciting time for both developers of RNAi therapeutics as well as patients that stand to benefit from them, with number of recently approved drugs and several potential blockbusters queuing up in the pipeline. However, two aspects darken this otherwise rosy picture. I) Cardiovascular disease is by far the largest pursued indication, but, at the moment of writing, there are at least five late stage clinical assets going after it! This is great news for patients, but bad news for developers, who will see the blockbuster potential of their drugs dwindle. II) There is a very apparent lack of diversity of targeting strategies, with majority of the (investigational) drugs leveraging GalNAc conjugation for delivery to hepatocytes. Some target eye or skin. Only three clinical trials for lungs and kidneys have reached phase II, as did one trial for the brain [ref]. The sustained success of RNAi therapeutics will be conditioned on RNAi companies’ ability to devise strategies for extrahepatic delivery, with muscle and brain representing particularly attractive, but also elusive, targets. Thanks for reading everyone! Did you enjou this recap? And what area would you like to see covered next? Let me know in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fifteen Insights from the Nucleate Alumni 2024 Summit</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/09/06/Summit24Insights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fifteen Insights from the Nucleate Alumni 2024 Summit" /><published>2024-09-06T09:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T09:22:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2024/09/06/Summit24Insights</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/09/06/Summit24Insights.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I returned from the Nucleate &lt;a href=&quot;https://nucleate.xyz/summit_2024/&quot;&gt;Alumni 2024 Summit&lt;/a&gt;. I had high expectations, but the event did not disappoint and managed to meet them. Never have I ever been to an event where networking with a diverse group of prospective founders, investors and industry professionals was so seamless. I can’t wait to see the innovation and collaboration that these connections will spark and want to send out a huge thank you to the fellow members of Nucleate leadership, speakers and sponsors &amp;lt;3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was packed with panel discussions, interviews, pitches and fireside chats. Below I summarize my favorite insights across five key areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Career Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Company Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnerships and Dealmaking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Startup Strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive right in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;insights-on-career-planning&quot;&gt;Insights on Career Planning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_001.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_002.png&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_006.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ask-for-mentoring-in-career-transitions&quot;&gt;Ask for mentoring in career transitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiating mentorship relationships can be anxiety-provoking, certainly if you are already more on the introverted side. But, judging from experiences within my network, it is very clear that those who do ask for mentorship achieve far better career outcomes. Career transitions are a natural way to go out and approach people who are in positions and industries you hope to break into. It also gives you a clear ask: “Would you be available to meet me for 30 minutes to share advice that could help me transition to the X industry, and land the Y or Z roles?” setting a clear agenda for your meeting and increasing chances for positive response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Christalyn Rhoades and @Michelle Briggs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-networking-first-connect-on-a-human-level&quot;&gt;When networking, first connect on a human level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People you would like to reach out to (including mentors) have one thing in common – their agendas are packed. Of course, you are reaching out to them for a reason – they are successful and recognized in their fields. A good intention, respecting their time, can make you feel pressured to make your ask as quickly as possible. Surprisingly, this tends to be counterproductive. Be succinct, but don’t do this at the expense of sharing where you are coming from, and highlighting why you are reaching to them. You don’t have to know everything, and being vulnerable about your unknowns will likely strengthen the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Madelyn Heart&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-shy-away-from-short-term-opportunities-or-non-conventional-career-moves&quot;&gt;Don’t shy away from short-term opportunities or non-conventional career moves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem that great careers must be carefully forethought and emerge only from a sequence of upward steps. Some certainly do, but many don’t. As you are thinking about your next career move, don’t over-index on security. If there is a short-term opportunity (ballpark 6-12 months) that you are excited about, don’t discard it, even if it seems risky or is in an area different from your existing expertise. It is likely to open doors to opportunities you could not access otherwise, and will help you build unique career capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Alex Titus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;insights-on-company-culture&quot;&gt;Insights on Company Culture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-culture-from-the-day-one&quot;&gt;Build culture from the day one&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building culture is not easy, but it is way easier than changing it. Prioritize the culture you want to build from the get go. Hire slow, and, if necessary, fire fast. To increase diversity, make sure that you have a diverse hiring panel, and look beyond the CV. Not all jobs require a degree and you are better off hiring for attitude and training for aptitude than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Arun Skaria, @Cameron Pye and @Madelyn Heart &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;every-day-is-an-opportunity-to-demonstrate-good-culture&quot;&gt;Every day is an opportunity to demonstrate good culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building company culture does not stop with hiring great employees. To prevent it from deteriorating by neglect in the messiness of ups and downs of your business, find ways to demonstrate it every day. Social media can be good for that, but think also about your relationships with suppliers, and your daily interactions with employees. Treat these as everyday opportunities to reinforce the culture you want to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Jon Chee, @Arun Skaria&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;praise-in-public-give-feedback-in-private&quot;&gt;Praise in public, give feedback in private&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a helpful reminder and the title says it all. Feedback is the breakfast of champions, and if you care about the satisfaction and development of your team, you absolutely should give both, positive as well as critical feedback. However, save the latter for one-on-one interactions, where there is space for more context and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Jon Chee&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;insights-on-partnerships-and-dealmaking&quot;&gt;Insights on Partnerships and Dealmaking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_004.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_005.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_007.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;partner-and-make-deals-only-with-people-whom-you-really-trust&quot;&gt;Partner and make deals only with people whom you really trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a founder, you are inherently in a risky environment and will not be able to predict the outcome of many actions you take. Sometimes the results will be great, and sometimes less so. When you encounter these uncertainties it is helpful to know that the people whom you have entered into agreements with have your best interest in mind. Pick partners and investors who will be your champions in thick and thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Marie Noe and @Josh Felts&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-transparent-about-risks-and-unknowns&quot;&gt;Be transparent about risks and unknowns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When courting partners and investors, you may be tempted to show only the best case scenario, or to discount the size of risk and uncertainties you are inevitably facing. Doing so will hurt you, if not now, certainly later. Be transparent about risks, and use interactions with partners to polish your de-risking strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Nicholas Hertz and @Christalyn Rhoades&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-building-new-relationships-as-well-as-managing-the-old-ones&quot;&gt;Keep building new relationships, as well as managing the old ones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have secured a partner or investor, you should pat yourself on the back, and then get back to work. Good relationships require good communication and it is your responsibility to keep stakeholders engaged and informed. Additionally, no matter how good, no partner is granted to stick with you forever. Especially corporate VCs, while generally very friendly and helpful with feedback, may walk away easily if their strategy changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Deepa Talpade and @Nicholas Hertz&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;insights-on-leadership&quot;&gt;Insights on Leadership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embrace-emotional-intelligence&quot;&gt;Embrace emotional intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a scientist, you are likely to have the IQ you need to be successful. But to become a good leader, you will have to lean more into your ‘softer’ side and work on developing your emotional intelligence. Proving you are right serves little purpose aside from ego inflation if it alienates others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Jon Chee, @Arun Skaria &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;craft-steel-strong-narratives-and-build-teams-around-it&quot;&gt;Craft steel-strong narratives and build teams around it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a leader, your most important goal is to articulate a bullet-proof narrative you whole-heartedly believe in, in a form that is easily digestible and motivates others. If you don’t have that, you cannot lead effectively and have to go back to the (proverbial) whiteboard. Only once you have it, should you go ahead to building rockstar teams and communities, and rising funds to do so. The most groundbreaking narratives are at the very end of what seems technically plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Rick Klausner&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;insights-on-startup-strategy&quot;&gt;Insights on Startup Strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_003.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_008.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col one&quot; src=&quot;/img/summit24_009.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;startup-should-be-20-innovation-and-80-strategy&quot;&gt;Startup should be 20% innovation, and 80% strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific founders will often see startups as an opportunity to continue pursuing their favorite research project. While understandable, this should not be the case. The technological innovation should have happened prior to founding, and work ahead should be primarily focused on turning this innovation into a successful commercial opportunity. This involves identifying go-to-market strategy, and establishing partnerships necessary to effectively pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Mariola Szenk and @Sofia Guerra&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;measure-speed-and-capital-efficiency&quot;&gt;Measure speed and capital efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gets measured gets managed. You should always be on the lookout for what you can measure in your startup. Many of the things you decide to measure will be product, field or company specific, but some are generalizable. Measure your &lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt; (how quickly you reach milestones), and &lt;em&gt;capital efficiency&lt;/em&gt; (how much it costs you) as soon as possible. Investors care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Vasudev Bailey, @Vineeta Agarwala&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-and-when-not-to-bootstrap&quot;&gt;When, and when not, to bootstrap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bootstrapping refers to building your business while not taking in dilutive funding. Whether to bootstrap or not is a choice that requires evaluation of the market and your personal fit. Bootstrapping is appealing because it allows founders to keep a high stake in their companies and offers unique opportunities for independence and agency. One advantage of bootstrapping is that it is likely to make you very capital efficient. To be able to bootstrap, you should have carried market analysis and identified a clear customer profile for your product. If you are bootstrapping, you should also incentivize your employees with a profit sharing scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases in biotech, bootstrapping will not be the optimal choice. You should not bootstrap if you are in a competitive environment where other firms have a lot of cash on hand, or if bootstrapping would require you to pursue assets that will distract you from your core mission. Bootstrapping can lead to lower valuations, as the valuation will be tied to sales of your non-core assets, and not a potential of your crown-jewel. Additionally, bootstrapping can make you spending-averse, which can delay the time you decide to outsource, or purchase the right tools, and negatively impact productivity (i.e. your speed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Jon Chee and @Cameron Pye&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-simple-blueprint-for-building-in-biotech&quot;&gt;A simple blueprint for building in biotech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All plans will be reductionist, but some may be helpful. Here is one that seems about right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate IP (most commonly in academia)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify killer experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get funding to do the experiments (preferably non-dilutive)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If results are positive, raise more money, otherwise restart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, plan back from milestones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Series B: Efficacy in the clinic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Series A: Identification of development candidates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seed: Figure out your pipeline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Credits: @Mariola Szenk and @Ben Portney&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were just fifteen of my favorite insights. I tried to attribute them correctly but my notes are not perfect, and my memory is far from that too. Please correct me if necessary! Did you attend the event and caught an insight I missed? Did you find one of these fifteen particularly helpful? Let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="biotech" /><category term="nucleate" /><category term="startup" /><summary type="html">Earlier this week I returned from the Nucleate Alumni 2024 Summit. I had high expectations, but the event did not disappoint and managed to meet them. Never have I ever been to an event where networking with a diverse group of prospective founders, investors and industry professionals was so seamless. I can’t wait to see the innovation and collaboration that these connections will spark and want to send out a huge thank you to the fellow members of Nucleate leadership, speakers and sponsors &amp;lt;3. The event was packed with panel discussions, interviews, pitches and fireside chats. Below I summarize my favorite insights across five key areas: Career Planning Company Culture Partnerships and Dealmaking Leadership Startup Strategy Let’s dive right in. Insights on Career Planning Ask for mentoring in career transitions Initiating mentorship relationships can be anxiety-provoking, certainly if you are already more on the introverted side. But, judging from experiences within my network, it is very clear that those who do ask for mentorship achieve far better career outcomes. Career transitions are a natural way to go out and approach people who are in positions and industries you hope to break into. It also gives you a clear ask: “Would you be available to meet me for 30 minutes to share advice that could help me transition to the X industry, and land the Y or Z roles?” setting a clear agenda for your meeting and increasing chances for positive response. Credits: @Christalyn Rhoades and @Michelle Briggs When networking, first connect on a human level People you would like to reach out to (including mentors) have one thing in common – their agendas are packed. Of course, you are reaching out to them for a reason – they are successful and recognized in their fields. A good intention, respecting their time, can make you feel pressured to make your ask as quickly as possible. Surprisingly, this tends to be counterproductive. Be succinct, but don’t do this at the expense of sharing where you are coming from, and highlighting why you are reaching to them. You don’t have to know everything, and being vulnerable about your unknowns will likely strengthen the relationship. Credits: @Madelyn Heart Don’t shy away from short-term opportunities or non-conventional career moves It may seem that great careers must be carefully forethought and emerge only from a sequence of upward steps. Some certainly do, but many don’t. As you are thinking about your next career move, don’t over-index on security. If there is a short-term opportunity (ballpark 6-12 months) that you are excited about, don’t discard it, even if it seems risky or is in an area different from your existing expertise. It is likely to open doors to opportunities you could not access otherwise, and will help you build unique career capital. Credits: @Alex Titus Insights on Company Culture Build culture from the day one Building culture is not easy, but it is way easier than changing it. Prioritize the culture you want to build from the get go. Hire slow, and, if necessary, fire fast. To increase diversity, make sure that you have a diverse hiring panel, and look beyond the CV. Not all jobs require a degree and you are better off hiring for attitude and training for aptitude than the other way around. Credits: @Arun Skaria, @Cameron Pye and @Madelyn Heart Every day is an opportunity to demonstrate good culture Building company culture does not stop with hiring great employees. To prevent it from deteriorating by neglect in the messiness of ups and downs of your business, find ways to demonstrate it every day. Social media can be good for that, but think also about your relationships with suppliers, and your daily interactions with employees. Treat these as everyday opportunities to reinforce the culture you want to build. Credits: @Jon Chee, @Arun Skaria Praise in public, give feedback in private This is a helpful reminder and the title says it all. Feedback is the breakfast of champions, and if you care about the satisfaction and development of your team, you absolutely should give both, positive as well as critical feedback. However, save the latter for one-on-one interactions, where there is space for more context and discussion. Credits: @Jon Chee Insights on Partnerships and Dealmaking Partner and make deals only with people whom you really trust As a founder, you are inherently in a risky environment and will not be able to predict the outcome of many actions you take. Sometimes the results will be great, and sometimes less so. When you encounter these uncertainties it is helpful to know that the people whom you have entered into agreements with have your best interest in mind. Pick partners and investors who will be your champions in thick and thin. Credits: @Marie Noe and @Josh Felts Be transparent about risks and unknowns When courting partners and investors, you may be tempted to show only the best case scenario, or to discount the size of risk and uncertainties you are inevitably facing. Doing so will hurt you, if not now, certainly later. Be transparent about risks, and use interactions with partners to polish your de-risking strategy. Credits: @Nicholas Hertz and @Christalyn Rhoades Keep building new relationships, as well as managing the old ones Once you have secured a partner or investor, you should pat yourself on the back, and then get back to work. Good relationships require good communication and it is your responsibility to keep stakeholders engaged and informed. Additionally, no matter how good, no partner is granted to stick with you forever. Especially corporate VCs, while generally very friendly and helpful with feedback, may walk away easily if their strategy changes. Credits: @Deepa Talpade and @Nicholas Hertz Insights on Leadership Embrace emotional intelligence As a scientist, you are likely to have the IQ you need to be successful. But to become a good leader, you will have to lean more into your ‘softer’ side and work on developing your emotional intelligence. Proving you are right serves little purpose aside from ego inflation if it alienates others. Credits: @Jon Chee, @Arun Skaria Craft steel-strong narratives and build teams around it As a leader, your most important goal is to articulate a bullet-proof narrative you whole-heartedly believe in, in a form that is easily digestible and motivates others. If you don’t have that, you cannot lead effectively and have to go back to the (proverbial) whiteboard. Only once you have it, should you go ahead to building rockstar teams and communities, and rising funds to do so. The most groundbreaking narratives are at the very end of what seems technically plausible. Credits: @Rick Klausner Insights on Startup Strategy Startup should be 20% innovation, and 80% strategy Scientific founders will often see startups as an opportunity to continue pursuing their favorite research project. While understandable, this should not be the case. The technological innovation should have happened prior to founding, and work ahead should be primarily focused on turning this innovation into a successful commercial opportunity. This involves identifying go-to-market strategy, and establishing partnerships necessary to effectively pursue it. Credits: @Mariola Szenk and @Sofia Guerra Measure speed and capital efficiency What gets measured gets managed. You should always be on the lookout for what you can measure in your startup. Many of the things you decide to measure will be product, field or company specific, but some are generalizable. Measure your speed (how quickly you reach milestones), and capital efficiency (how much it costs you) as soon as possible. Investors care. Credits: @Vasudev Bailey, @Vineeta Agarwala When, and when not, to bootstrap Bootstrapping refers to building your business while not taking in dilutive funding. Whether to bootstrap or not is a choice that requires evaluation of the market and your personal fit. Bootstrapping is appealing because it allows founders to keep a high stake in their companies and offers unique opportunities for independence and agency. One advantage of bootstrapping is that it is likely to make you very capital efficient. To be able to bootstrap, you should have carried market analysis and identified a clear customer profile for your product. If you are bootstrapping, you should also incentivize your employees with a profit sharing scheme. In many cases in biotech, bootstrapping will not be the optimal choice. You should not bootstrap if you are in a competitive environment where other firms have a lot of cash on hand, or if bootstrapping would require you to pursue assets that will distract you from your core mission. Bootstrapping can lead to lower valuations, as the valuation will be tied to sales of your non-core assets, and not a potential of your crown-jewel. Additionally, bootstrapping can make you spending-averse, which can delay the time you decide to outsource, or purchase the right tools, and negatively impact productivity (i.e. your speed). Credits: @Jon Chee and @Cameron Pye A simple blueprint for building in biotech All plans will be reductionist, but some may be helpful. Here is one that seems about right: Generate IP (most commonly in academia) Identify killer experiments Get funding to do the experiments (preferably non-dilutive) Do the experiments If results are positive, raise more money, otherwise restart Alternatively, plan back from milestones: Series B: Efficacy in the clinic Series A: Identification of development candidates Seed: Figure out your pipeline Credits: @Mariola Szenk and @Ben Portney These were just fifteen of my favorite insights. I tried to attribute them correctly but my notes are not perfect, and my memory is far from that too. Please correct me if necessary! Did you attend the event and caught an insight I missed? Did you find one of these fifteen particularly helpful? Let me know in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keynes vs. Hayek - The Economics (Rap)Battle</title><link href="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/07/17/KeynesHayek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keynes vs. Hayek - The Economics (Rap)Battle" /><published>2024-07-17T18:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-07-17T18:22:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.martinholub.com/2024/07/17/KeynesHayek</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.martinholub.com/2024/07/17/KeynesHayek.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-keynes-vs-hayek-debate&quot;&gt;The Keynes vs. Hayek Debate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Keynes vs. Hayek debate centers on contrasting economic theories about how to manage economies, especially during downturns. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Maynard_Keynes&quot;&gt;John Maynard Keynes&lt;/a&gt; advocated for active government intervention, suggesting that during recessions, increased government spending can boost demand and pull economies out of downturns. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Hayek&quot;&gt;Friedrich Hayek&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, argued that such interventions distort market signals and lead to inefficiencies, believing that free markets and minimal government interference lead to better economic outcomes by allowing natural corrections through the price mechanism. Essentially, Keynes emphasized short-term government action to stabilize the economy, while Hayek stressed long-term market processes and individual liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;economics-everyday-role&quot;&gt;Economics’ Everyday Role&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you like it or not, economics is a force that influences the decisions we make and the opportunities we are dealt with. From stagnation to growth, from inequality to prosperity, from housing scarcity to tight job market, all these are issues that are intimately tied with economics. Ignoring this is at one’s peril. For the longest time it seems like nothing is going wrong, until suddenly you are in for an unpleasant surprise.
Unfortunately, the way economics is taught tends to be dull, if not downright unpalatable. Trying to catch up on the education by following politics is bound to leave you more confused then you started. Yet, grasping some key concepts in economics is important to reaching personal goals as it is to being a more conscious citizen. If I have painted a pessimistic picture, don’t despair, here comes a plot twist: a rap battle on one of the most pertinent topics in macroeconomics – how much control should the government interfere with the free market?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fear-the-boom-and-bust-keynes-vs-hayek---the-original-economics-rap-battle&quot;&gt;Fear the Boom and Bust: Keynes vs. Hayek - The Original Economics Rap Battle!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/d0nERTFo-Sk?si=2uQtdenaFZSNU2di&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- https://www.chunkhang.com/blog/responsive-youtube-video-with-jekyll use as include youtube.html id=&apos;....&apos;  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you but I thought the rap was not even that bad! So did the authors, I guess, because they made a sequel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fight-of-the-century-keynes-vs-hayek---economics-rap-battle-round-two&quot;&gt;Fight of the Century: Keynes vs. Hayek - Economics Rap Battle Round Two&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_row&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTQnarzmTOc?si=GuNki18Ppdy1VdDx&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- https://www.chunkhang.com/blog/responsive-youtube-video-with-jekyll use as include youtube.html id=&apos;....&apos;  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I will let you make your own opinion about the subject matter. You could argue it is not all that simple, and you would probably be right. However, now you are unlikely to forget what did Keynes or Hayek stand for. And you will be able see the pattern emerging in politics and to explain it to others too. And that seems like a good thing. Thanks for reading &amp;amp; watching everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="finance" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">The Keynes vs. Hayek Debate The Keynes vs. Hayek debate centers on contrasting economic theories about how to manage economies, especially during downturns. John Maynard Keynes advocated for active government intervention, suggesting that during recessions, increased government spending can boost demand and pull economies out of downturns. Friedrich Hayek, on the other hand, argued that such interventions distort market signals and lead to inefficiencies, believing that free markets and minimal government interference lead to better economic outcomes by allowing natural corrections through the price mechanism. Essentially, Keynes emphasized short-term government action to stabilize the economy, while Hayek stressed long-term market processes and individual liberty. Economics’ Everyday Role Whether you like it or not, economics is a force that influences the decisions we make and the opportunities we are dealt with. From stagnation to growth, from inequality to prosperity, from housing scarcity to tight job market, all these are issues that are intimately tied with economics. Ignoring this is at one’s peril. For the longest time it seems like nothing is going wrong, until suddenly you are in for an unpleasant surprise. Unfortunately, the way economics is taught tends to be dull, if not downright unpalatable. Trying to catch up on the education by following politics is bound to leave you more confused then you started. Yet, grasping some key concepts in economics is important to reaching personal goals as it is to being a more conscious citizen. If I have painted a pessimistic picture, don’t despair, here comes a plot twist: a rap battle on one of the most pertinent topics in macroeconomics – how much control should the government interfere with the free market? Fear the Boom and Bust: Keynes vs. Hayek - The Original Economics Rap Battle! I don’t know about you but I thought the rap was not even that bad! So did the authors, I guess, because they made a sequel. Fight of the Century: Keynes vs. Hayek - Economics Rap Battle Round Two Well, I will let you make your own opinion about the subject matter. You could argue it is not all that simple, and you would probably be right. However, now you are unlikely to forget what did Keynes or Hayek stand for. And you will be able see the pattern emerging in politics and to explain it to others too. And that seems like a good thing. Thanks for reading &amp;amp; watching everyone!</summary></entry></feed>